<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>The paradyse of daynty deuises Conteyning sundry pithy preceptes, learned counsels, and excellent inuentions, right pleasant and profitable for all estates. Deuised and written for the most part, by M. Edwardes, sometimes of her Maiesties Chappell: the rest, by sundry learned gentlemen, both of honor, and worship, whose names hereafter folowe.</title>
            <title>Paradise of daynty devises</title>
            <author>Edwards, Richard, 1523?-1566.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1578</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 201 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 45 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-12">2011-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A21162</idno>
            <idno type="STC">STC 7517</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC S111775</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99847045</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99847045</idno>
            <idno type="VID">12052</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A21162)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 12052)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1475-1640 ; 219:06)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>The paradyse of daynty deuises Conteyning sundry pithy preceptes, learned counsels, and excellent inuentions, right pleasant and profitable for all estates. Deuised and written for the most part, by M. Edwardes, sometimes of her Maiesties Chappell: the rest, by sundry learned gentlemen, both of honor, and worship, whose names hereafter folowe.</title>
                  <title>Paradise of daynty devises</title>
                  <author>Edwards, Richard, 1523?-1566.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>50 [i.e.44] leaves   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>By [R. Jones for?] Henry Disle, dwelling in Paules Churchyard, at the Southwest doore of Saint Paules Church, and are there to be solde,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>Imprinted at London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1578.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Printer's name suggested by STC.</note>
                  <note>A rearrangement, with omissions and additions, of the first edition of 1576 (STC 7516)--STC.</note>
                  <note>In verse.</note>
                  <note>Numerous errors in foliation; foliation derived from signature collation.</note>
                  <note>The British Library copy has an extra bifolium (chi K2) with foliation in large roman type; it is not present in the Bodleian Library copy and may represent a later issue of this edition--STC.</note>
                  <note>Signatures: A-I⁴ K²  L⁴ M² .</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the Bodleian Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>English poetry --  Early modern, 1500-1700 --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2010-12</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-12</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-01</date>
            <label>Susie Lorand</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-01</date>
            <label>Susie Lorand</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-06</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:12052:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:12052:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>THE PARADYSE of daynty deuiſes.</p>
            <p>Conteyning ſundry pithy preceptes, learned Counſels, and excellent inuentions, right pleaſant and profitable for all eſtates.</p>
            <p>Deuiſed and written for the most part, by M. Edwardes, ſometimes of her Maiesties Chappell: the rest, by ſundry learned Gentlemen, both of honor, and worſhip, whoſe names here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>after folowe.</p>
            <figure>
               <head>EGO SVM VIA ET VERITAS</head>
            </figure>
            <p>Jmprinted at London, by Henry Diſle, dwelling in Paules Churchyard, at the Southweſt doore of Saint Paules Church, and are there to be ſolde.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>1578.</hi>
            </p>
         </div>
         <div type="illustration">
            <pb facs="tcp:12052:2"/>
            <p>
               <figure>
                  <figDesc>blazon or coat of arms</figDesc>
                  <head>IE NE CHERCHE Q'VNE</head>
               </figure>
            </p>
            <list>
               <item>Saint Barnard</item>
               <item>E. O.</item>
               <item>Lord Vaux, the elder.</item>
               <item>VV. Hunis.</item>
               <item>Iaſper Heyvvod.</item>
               <item>F. Kindlemarſh.</item>
               <item>D. Sand.</item>
               <item>M. Yloop.</item>
            </list>
         </div>
         <div type="dedication">
            <pb facs="tcp:12052:2"/>
            <head>TO THE RIGHT HO<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>norable Sir Henry Compton Knight, Lord Compton of Compton.</head>
            <p>
               <hi>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">R</seg>IGHT HONORABLE, AND</hi> my verye good Lord, (preſuming vpon your curteſy) I am bolde to preſent vnto your honor, this ſmale volume Entituled The Paradiſe of deyntye deuiſes, being pen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned by diuers learned Gentlemen and collected togea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther through the trauell of one, both of vvorſhippe and credite, for his priuate vſe: who not long ſine departed this life, vvhich vvhen I had peruſed ouer, not vvithout the aduiſe of ſundry my freendes, I determined by their good motion, to ſet the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> in print, who therunto great<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lye perſwaded me, vvith theſe and like vvords: The vvryters of them, were both of honor and worſhippe, beſides that our ovvne country men, and ſuch as for their learning and grauitie, might be accompted of among the wiſeſt. Furthermore, the dittis both pithy &amp; pleaſant, as wel for the inuentio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> as meter, and vvill yeelde a farre greater delight, being as they are ſo aptly made to be ſette to any ſong in .5. partes, or ſong to inſtrument. VVhich well conſidering, I porpoſed not to forſake ſo good an occaſion, beſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ching your honor to accept it in good parte, cheefely for the au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thours ſake: who thoughe ſome of them are departed this life, yet their worthy doings ſhall continue for euer: for like as the ſhadow folovveth the body, ſo praiſe foloweth ver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tue: and as the ſhadow goeth ſomtimes before, and ſometimes behind, ſo doth praiſe alſo to vertue: but the later it commeth, the greater it is. &amp; to be the better eſteemed. Thus fearing to offend your honor with theſe my rude ſpeaches, I ende, wiſhing your L. many yeeres of ioy</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>
                  <hi>Your good Lordſhips wholy to <hi>commaund.</hi> H. D.</hi>
               </signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div type="poem">
            <pb facs="tcp:12052:3"/>
            <head>The tranſlation of the bleſſed S. Barnards verſes, conteining the vnſtable felicitie of this wayfaring world.</head>
            <lg xml:lang="lat">
               <l>
                  <hi>CVR mundus militat, ſub vana gloria, cuius proſperitas est tranſitoria?</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Tam cito labitur, eius potentia quam vaſa figula, que ſunt fragilia.</hi>
               </l>
            </lg>
            <l>WHY dooth eache ſtate apply it ſelfe to worldly prayſe?</l>
            <l>And vndertake ſuch toyle, to heape vp honours gayne:</l>
            <l>Whoſe ſeate, though ſeeming ſure, on fickle fortune ſtayes,</l>
            <l>Whoſe giftes were neuer proued, perpetuall to remayne.</l>
            <l>But euen as earthen pot, with euery fillip fayles,</l>
            <l>So fortunes fauour flits, and fame with honour quayles.</l>
            <lg xml:lang="lat">
               <l>
                  <hi>Plus crede litteris, ſcriptis in glacia, quam mundi fragilis, venae fallabiae.</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Fallſax in premijs, vertutis ſpecie, que nunquam habuit, tempus fiduciae.</hi>
               </l>
            </lg>
            <l>Thinke rather firme to find, a figure grauen in Iſe,</l>
            <l>Whoſe ſubſtance ſubiect is, to heate of ſhining ſunne:</l>
            <l>Then hope for ſtedfaſt ſtay, in wanton worlds deuiſe,</l>
            <l>Whoſe fayned fond delightes, from falſhed forge doo come.</l>
            <l>And vnder Vertues veyle, are largely dealt about,</l>
            <l>Deceiuing thoſe, who thinke their date will neuer out.</l>
            <lg xml:lang="lat">
               <l>
                  <hi>Magis credendu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> est viris fallacibus, quam mundi miſeris proſperitatibus</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Falſis inſanijs &amp; voluptatibus, falſis quoquae studijs &amp; vanitatibus.</hi>
               </l>
            </lg>
            <l>The trifeling truthles tongue, of rumours lying lippes,</l>
            <l>Deſerues more truſt, then dooth the higheſt happy hap:</l>
            <l>That world to worldlinges giues, for ſee how honour ſlippes,</l>
            <l>To fooliſh fond conceytes, to pleaſures poyſoned ſap.</l>
            <l>To ſtudyes falſe in proofe, to artes applied to gayne,</l>
            <l>To fickle fancies toyes, which wiſedome deemeth vayne.</l>
            <lg xml:lang="lat">
               <l>
                  <hi>Dic vbi Salomon, olim tam nobilis? vel vbi Sampſon est, dux inuincibilis?</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Vel dulcis Ionathas, multum amabilis? vel pulcher Abſoln, vultu mirabilis</hi>
               </l>
            </lg>
            <l>Where is the ſacred king, that Salomon the wiſe?</l>
            <l>Whoſe wyſedome, former time of duety did commend:</l>
            <l>Where is that Sampſon ſtrong, that monſtrous man in ſyze?</l>
            <l>Whoſe forced arme, dyd cauſe the mighty pillers bend.</l>
            <l>Where is the pearles Prince, the freendly Ionathas?</l>
            <l>Or Abſolon, whoſe ſhape and fauour did ſurpaſſe.</l>
            <lg xml:lang="lat">
               <l>
                  <pb facs="tcp:12052:3" rendition="simple:additions"/>
                  <hi>Quo Caeſar abijt? celſus imperio, vel diues ſplendidus, totus in prandio.</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Dic vbi Tullius, clarus eloquio, vel Aristoteles, ſummus ingenio.</hi>
               </l>
            </lg>
            <l>Where is that <hi>Caeſar</hi> now, whoſe high renowmed fame,</l>
            <l>Of ſundry conqueſtes wonne, through out the world did ſound:</l>
            <l>Or <hi>Diues</hi> rich in ſtore, and rich in richly name,</l>
            <l>Whoſe cheſt with gold and diſhe with daynties did abound.</l>
            <l>Where is the paſſing grace of <hi>Tullies</hi> pleding ſkill?</l>
            <l>Or <hi>Aristotles</hi> vayne, whoſe pen had witte and will?</l>
            <lg xml:lang="lat">
               <l>
                  <hi>O eſca vermium, ò maſſa pulueris, ò ros, ò vanitas, cur ſic extolleris?</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Ignoras penitus vtru<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> cras vixeris, fac bonum omnibus, quam diu poteris.</hi>
               </l>
            </lg>
            <l>O foode of filthy worme, oh lump of lothſome clay,</l>
            <l>O life ful like the dewe, which morning ſunne doth waſt:</l>
            <l>O ſhadow vayne, whoſe ſhape with ſunne dooth ſhrinke away.</l>
            <l>Why glorieſt thou ſo much, in honour to be plaſte?</l>
            <l>Sith that no certayne houre of life thou doſte enioy,</l>
            <l>Moſt fyt it were thy time to goodneſſe to employ.</l>
            <lg xml:lang="lat">
               <l>
                  <hi>Quam breue festu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> est, haec mundi gloria, vt vmbra hominu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, ſic eius gaudia.</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Que ſemper ſubtrahit aeterna praemia, &amp; ducunt hominum, ad dura eruia.</hi>
               </l>
            </lg>
            <l>How ſhort a banquet ſeemes the pomp of high renowne?</l>
            <l>How like the ſenſeles ſhape of ſhiuering ſhadow thine?</l>
            <l>Are wanton worldly toyes, whoſe pleaſure plucketh downe,</l>
            <l>Our harts from hope, &amp; hands from works, which heauen ſhould win.</l>
            <l>And takes vs from the trod, which guides to enleſſe gayne,</l>
            <l>And ſets vs in the way, that leades to laſting payne</l>
            <lg xml:lang="lat">
               <l>
                  <hi>Haec mundi gloria, quae magni penditur, ſacris in litteris, flos faeni dicitur.</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Vt leue folium, quod vento rapitur, ſic vita hominum, hac vita tollitur.</hi>
               </l>
            </lg>
            <l>The pompe of worldly prayſe, which worldlings hold ſo déere,</l>
            <l>In holy ſacred booke, is likened to a flowre:</l>
            <l>Whoſe date dooth not conteyne, a weeke, a moonth, or yeere,</l>
            <l>But ſpringing now, dooth fade againe within an houre.</l>
            <l>And as the lighteſt leafe, with wind about is throwne,</l>
            <l>So light is life of man, and lightly hence is blowne.</l>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
            <epigraph>
               <q>My luke is loſse.</q>
            </epigraph>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <div type="acrostic_poem">
               <pb facs="tcp:12052:4" rendition="simple:additions"/>
               <head>
                  <hi>1.</hi> Our pleaſures are vanities.</head>
               <lg>
                  <l>
                     <hi>BEholde</hi> the blaſt, which blowes the bloſſomes from the tree,</l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>The end</hi> whereof, conſumes and comes to nought we ſee:</l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Ere thou</hi> therefore, be blowen from life that may not laſt,</l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Begin</hi> for grace to call, for time miſpent and paſt.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Haue mind</hi> on brittle lyfe, whoſe pleaſures are but vayne,</l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>On death</hi> likewiſe bethinke, how thou maieſt not remayne:</l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>And feare</hi> thy Lord to greeue, which ſought thy ſoule to ſaue,</l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>To ſinne</hi> no more be bent, but mercy aſke and haue.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>
                     <hi>For death</hi> who dooth not ſpare, the kings on earth to kill,</l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Shall reape</hi> alſo from thee, thy pleaſure, life, and will:</l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>That lyfe</hi> which yet remaynes, and in thy breſt appeares,</l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Hath ſowen</hi> in thee ſuch ſeedes, you ought to weede with teares.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>
                     <hi>And life</hi> that ſhall ſucceede, when death is worne and paſt,</l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Shall ſpring</hi> for euer then, in ioy or payne to laſt:</l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Where death</hi> on life hath power ye ſee, that life alſo,</l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Hath mowen</hi> the fruites of death, which neuer more ſhall grow.</l>
               </lg>
               <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
               <closer>
                  <signed>W. Hunis.</signed>
               </closer>
            </div>
            <div n="2" type="poem">
               <head>2.
<l>Who wayteth on this wauering world, and veweth each estate.</l>
                  <l>By tryall taught ſhall learne it best, to liue in ſimple rate.</l>
               </head>
               <l>AMid the vale the ſclender ſhrubbe, is hid from all miſhap,</l>
               <l>When taller tree that ſtandes aloft, is rent with thunder clap.</l>
               <l>The Turrets tops which touch the cloudes, are beat with euery blaſt,</l>
               <l>Soone ſhiuered are their ſtones with ſtorme, and quickly ouer caſt.</l>
               <l>Beſt bodyed tree in all the wood, for tymber beame is found,</l>
               <l>And to the axe the ſturdieſt Oxe, dooth yeeld and fall to ground.</l>
               <l>The higheſt hill dooth ſooneſt feele, the flaſh of lightnings flame,</l>
               <l>And ſoone decayes the pomp and pryde, of high renowmed name.</l>
               <l>Of all the heard the huntman ſeekes, by proofe as dooth appere,</l>
               <l>With double forked arrowe head, to wound the greateſt Deare.</l>
               <l>The hautieſt head of all the droue, enioyes the ſhorteſt life,</l>
               <l>And ſtaines the ſlaughter houſe with blood, at pricke of butchers knife.</l>
               <l>
                  <pb n="1" facs="tcp:12052:4"/>Thus what thing hyeſt place atteynes, is ſooneſt ouerthrowne,</l>
               <l>What euer Fortune ſets a loft, ſhe threates to throw it downe.</l>
               <l>And though no force reſiſt thy power, nor ſeeke thee to confound,</l>
               <l>Yet dooth the payſe of weighty things, decline it ſelfe to ground.</l>
               <l>For reſtleſſe tipe of roulling wheele, example hath it tryde,</l>
               <l>To heauy burden yeelde it muſt ful ſoone, and ſlip aſyde.</l>
               <l>What vayles the rich his bed of down, y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> ſighes for ſlepleſſe thought,</l>
               <l>What time in couch of flock the poore, ſleepes ſound &amp; feareth nought.</l>
               <l>At homely boord his quiet foode, his drinkes in treene be tane,</l>
               <l>When oft the proud in cuppes of gold, with wine receiue their bane.</l>
               <l>The bed, the boord, the dread in dout, with trayne to be oppreſt,</l>
               <l>When fortune frounes, their power muſt yeelde, as wyre vnto y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> wreſt.</l>
               <l>If <hi>Icarus</hi> had not preſumed to high to take his flight,</l>
               <l>He had not yet ben drowned in Seas, that now <hi>Itarion</hi> hight.</l>
               <l>If <hi>Phaeton</hi> had not enterpriſed to guide his fathers ſeate,</l>
               <l>His fires had not enflamed the world, nor ben deſtroyed with heate.</l>
               <l>But who ſo climes aboue the meane, there is no hope of ſtay,</l>
               <l>The higher vp the ſonner downe, and nearer his decay.</l>
               <l>Then you that here in pompe or place, to guide the golden maſe,</l>
               <l>Let crowne and Septer both obay the meane of Vertues race.</l>
               <l>For neither ſhall renowmed Vertue ſee the pit of hell,</l>
               <l>Nor yet in toombe of Marble ſtone, ſhe may abide to dwell.</l>
               <l>But from Sepulcher flies ſhe hence, beyond the ſkies aboue,</l>
               <l>And gliſtering in the bliſful ſtares, ſhe raines with mighty Ioue.</l>
               <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
               <closer>
                  <signed>Iaſper Heywood.</signed>
               </closer>
            </div>
            <div n="3" type="poem">
               <head>
                  <hi>3.</hi> The perfect tryall of a faythfull freend</head>
               <l>NOt ſtayed ſtate, but feeble ſtay, not coſtly robes, but bare aray:</l>
               <l>Not paſſed welth, but preſe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t wa<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t, not heped ſtore but ſcle<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>der ſka<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t</l>
               <l>Not plenties purſe, but poore eſtate, not happy hap, but troward fate:</l>
               <l>Not wiſh at wil, but wa<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t of ioy, not harts good helth but harts annoy:</l>
               <l>No fredomes vſe, but priſoners thrall, not coſtly ſeate, but loweſt fall:</l>
               <l>Not weale I meane, but wretched wo, doth truely try, y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> feend fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> foe:</l>
               <l>And nowght but frowarde Fortune prooues, who fauning faines, or ſimply loues.</l>
               <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
               <closer>
                  <signed>M. Yloop.</signed>
               </closer>
            </div>
            <div n="4" type="poem">
               <pb facs="tcp:12052:5" rendition="simple:additions"/>
               <head>
                  <hi>4.</hi> Being aſked the occaſion of his white head, he annſwereth thus.</head>
               <lg>
                  <l>WHere ſeething ſighes and ſorow ſobbes,</l>
                  <l>Hath ſlaine the ſlippes that nature ſet:</l>
                  <l>And ſkalding ſhowers with ſtony throbbes,</l>
                  <l>The kindly ſappe from them hath fet.</l>
                  <l>What woonder then though that you ſee,</l>
                  <l>Vpon my head white heares to be.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>Where thought hath thrild and throwne his ſpeares,</l>
                  <l>To hurt the hart that harmeth him not:</l>
                  <l>And groning griefe hath ground forth teares,</l>
                  <l>Myne eyne to ſtaine, my face to ſpot.</l>
                  <l>What woonder then though that you ſee,</l>
                  <l>Vpon my head white heares to be.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>Where pinching payne himſelfe hath plaſte,</l>
                  <l>There peace with pleaſures were poſſeſt:</l>
                  <l>And where the walles of wealth lye waſte,</l>
                  <l>And pouertye in them is preſt.</l>
                  <l>What woonder then though that you ſee,</l>
                  <l>Vpon my head white heares to be.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>Where wretched woe will weaue her webbe,</l>
                  <l>Where care the clewe can catch and caſt:</l>
                  <l>And flooddes of ioy are fallen to ebbe,</l>
                  <l>So loe, that life may not long laſt.</l>
                  <l>What woonder then though that you ſee,</l>
                  <l>Vpon my head white heares to be.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>Theſe heares of age are meſſengers,</l>
                  <l>Which bidde me faſt, repent, and pray:</l>
                  <l>They be of death the harbingers,</l>
                  <l>That dooth prepare and dreſſe the way,</l>
                  <l>Wherefore I ioy that you may ſee,</l>
                  <l>Vpon my head ſuch heares to be.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <pb n="2" facs="tcp:12052:5" rendition="simple:additions"/>
                  <l>They be the lines that lead the length,</l>
                  <l>How farre my race is for to runne:</l>
                  <l>They ſay my youth, is fled with ſtrength,</l>
                  <l>And how olde age is weake begunne.</l>
                  <l>The which I feele, and you may ſee,</l>
                  <l>Vpon my head ſuch lines to be.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>They be the ſtringes of ſober ſound,</l>
                  <l>Whoſe muſicke is harmonicall:</l>
                  <l>Their tunes declare a time from ground</l>
                  <l>I came, and how there to I ſhall.</l>
                  <l>Wherefore I ioy that you may ſee,</l>
                  <l>Vpon my head ſuch ſtringes to be.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>God graunt to thoſe that white heares haue,</l>
                  <l>No worſe them take then I haue ment:</l>
                  <l>That after they be layde in graue,</l>
                  <l>Their ſoules may ioy their liues wel ſpent.</l>
                  <l>God graunt likewiſe that you may ſee.</l>
                  <l>Vpon your head ſuch heares to be.</l>
               </lg>
               <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
               <closer>
                  <signed>W. Hunis.</signed>
               </closer>
            </div>
            <div n="5" type="poem">
               <head>
                  <hi>5.</hi> Beware of had I wyst.</head>
               <lg>
                  <l>BEware of had I wyſt, whoſe fine brings care and ſmart,</l>
                  <l>Eſteeme of all as they deſerue, and deeme as deemd thou art;</l>
                  <l>So ſhall thy perfect freend, enioy his hoped hyre,</l>
                  <l>And faithleſſe fawning foe, ſhall miſſe theffect of his deſyre.</l>
                  <l>Good will ſhall haue his gayne, and hate ſhall heape deſpite,</l>
                  <l>A faithleſſe freend ſhall find diſtruſt, and loue ſhall reape delite.</l>
                  <l>Thy ſelfe ſhall reſt in peace, thy freend ſhall ioy thy fate,</l>
                  <l>Thy foe ſhall fret at thy good happe, and I ſhall ioy thy ſtate.</l>
                  <l>But this my fond aduiſe, may ſeeme purchaunce but vayne,</l>
                  <l>As rather teaching how to loſe, then howe a freend to gayne.</l>
                  <l>But this not my intent, to teach to find a freend,</l>
                  <l>But ſafely how to loue and leaue, is all that I entend.</l>
                  <l>And yf you prooue in part, and find my counſell true,</l>
                  <l>Then wyſh me well for my good wyll, tis all I craue adue.</l>
               </lg>
               <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
               <epigraph>
                  <q>My lucke is loſse.</q>
               </epigraph>
            </div>
            <div n="6" type="poem">
               <pb facs="tcp:12052:6" rendition="simple:additions"/>
               <head>
                  <hi>6.</hi> M. Edwards MAY.</head>
               <lg>
                  <l>WHen <hi>MAY</hi> is in his prime, then <hi>MAY</hi> eche hart reioyce,</l>
                  <l>When <hi>MAY</hi> bedecks eche branch with greene, ech bird ſtreins forth his voice</l>
                  <l>The liuely ſappe creepes, vp into the bloming throne,</l>
                  <l>The flowres, which cold in priſon kept, now laughes y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> froſt to ſkorne.</l>
                  <l>All natures Impes triumphes, whiles ioyful may doth laſt,</l>
                  <l>When <hi>MAY</hi> is gone, of all the yeere the pleaſant time is paſt.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>
                     <hi>MAY</hi> makes the cheerfull hue, <hi>MAY</hi> breedes &amp; bringes new blood.</l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>MAY</hi> marcheth throughout euery lim, <hi>MAY</hi> makes y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> mery mood.</l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>MAY</hi> pricketh tender harts, their warbling notes to tune,</l>
                  <l>Ful ſtrange it is, yet ſome we ſee, doe make their <hi>MAY</hi> in <hi>Iune.</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>Thus thinges are ſtrangly wrought, whiles ioyful <hi>MAY</hi> doth laſt,</l>
                  <l>Take <hi>MAY</hi> in time, when <hi>MAY</hi> is gone, the pleaſant time is paſt.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>All ye that liue on earth, and haue your <hi>MAY</hi> at will,</l>
                  <l>Reioyce in <hi>MAY,</hi> as I doe now, and vſe your <hi>MAY</hi> with ſkill.</l>
                  <l>Vſe <hi>MAY,</hi> whyle that you may, for <hi>MAY</hi> hath but his time,</l>
                  <l>When all the fruite is gone, it is to late the tree to clime.</l>
                  <l>Your liking and your luſt, is freſhe whyles <hi>MAY</hi> dooth laſt,</l>
                  <l>When <hi>MAY</hi> is gone, of all the yeere, the pleaſant time is paſt.</l>
               </lg>
               <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
               <closer>
                  <signed>M. Edwardes.</signed>
               </closer>
            </div>
            <div n="7" type="poem">
               <head>
                  <hi>7.</hi> Faire words make fooles faine.</head>
               <lg>
                  <l>JN youthful yeeres when firſt my young deſyres began,</l>
                  <l>To pricke me forth to ſerue in Court a ſclender tal young man:</l>
                  <l>My fathers bleſſing then I aſkt vpon my knnee,</l>
                  <l>Who bleſſing me with trembling hand, theſe words gan ſay to me:</l>
                  <l>My ſonne, God guide thy way, and ſhild thee from miſchaunce,</l>
                  <l>And make thy iuſt deſartes in Court, thy poore eſtate to aduaunce:</l>
                  <l>Yet when thou art become one of the Courtly trayne,</l>
                  <l>Thinke on this prouerbe old (qd he) that faire words make foles fain.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>This counſell grauely giuen, moſt ſtraunge appeares to me,</l>
                  <l>Till tract of time with open eyes, had made me plainely ſee:</l>
                  <l>What ſubtill fleightes are wrought by painted tales deuiſe,</l>
                  <l>When hollow harts with freendly ſhewes the ſimple do entiſe.</l>
                  <l>
                     <pb n="3" facs="tcp:12052:6" rendition="simple:additions"/>To thinke all gold that ſhines to feede their fond deſire,</l>
                  <l>Whoſe ſheuering cold is warmde with ſmoke, in ſtead of flaming fire:</l>
                  <l>Sith talke of tickle truſt, dooth breede a hope moſt vayne,</l>
                  <l>This prouerbe true by profe I find, that faire words make fooles fain.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>Faire ſpeach alway doth wel, where deedes inſue faire words,</l>
                  <l>Faire ſpeach agayn alway dooth euill, that buſhes giues for birdes.</l>
                  <l>Who hopes to haue faire words, to trye his lucky lot.</l>
                  <l>If I may counſell, let him ſtrike it whyle the iron is hot.</l>
                  <l>But them that feede on cloddes, in ſtead of pleaſant grapes,</l>
                  <l>And after warning often giuen, for better lucke ſtill gapes</l>
                  <l>Ful loth I am, yet muſt I tel them in words playne,</l>
                  <l>This prouerbe old proues true in them, that faire words makes fooles fayne.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>Wo worth the time that words, ſo ſlowly turne to deedes,</l>
                  <l>Wo worth the time y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> faire ſwete flouers, are growen to rotten weedes</l>
                  <l>But thriſe wo worth the time, that truth away is fled,</l>
                  <l>Wherein I ſee how ſimple harts, with words are vaynely fed.</l>
                  <l>Truſt not faire words therfore, Where no deedes do enſue,</l>
                  <l>Truſt words, as ſkilful falkeners do truſt Haukes that neuer flewe.</l>
                  <l>Truſt deedes, let words be words, which neuer wrought me gaine,</l>
                  <l>Let my experience make you wiſe, and let words make foles faine.</l>
               </lg>
               <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
               <closer>
                  <signed>M. Edwardes.</signed>
               </closer>
            </div>
            <div n="8" type="poem">
               <head>
                  <hi>8.</hi> In his extreame ſickneſſe.</head>
               <lg>
                  <l>WHat greeues my bones, and makes my body faint?</l>
                  <l>What prickes my fleſh and teares my head in twayne?</l>
                  <l>Why doe I wake, when reſt ſhould me attaint?</l>
                  <l>When others laugh, why do I liue in payne?</l>
                  <l>I toſſe, I turne, I chaunge from ſide to ſide,</l>
                  <l>And ſtretch me oft, in ſorowes linkes betyde.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>I toſſe, as one betoſt in waues of care,</l>
                  <l>I turne, to flee the woes of lothſome life:</l>
                  <l>I change, to ſpy if death this corpes might ſpare,</l>
                  <l>I ſtretch, to heauen to ridde me of this ſtrife:</l>
                  <l>Thus doe I ſtretch, and change, and toſſe, and turne,</l>
                  <l>Whyle I in hope of heauen my life do burne.</l>
                  <l>
                     <pb facs="tcp:12052:7" rendition="simple:additions"/>Then hold the ſtill, let be thy heauineſſe,</l>
                  <l>Aboliſh care, forgeat thy pining woe:</l>
                  <l>For by this meanes ſoone ſhalt thou find redreſſe,</l>
                  <l>When oft betoſt, hence thou to heauen muſt goe.</l>
                  <l>Then toſſe, and turne, and tumble franke and free,</l>
                  <l>O happy thryſe, when thou in heauen ſhalt be.</l>
               </lg>
               <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
               <closer>
                  <signed>L. Vaux.</signed>
               </closer>
            </div>
            <div n="9" type="poem">
               <head>9. For Christmas day.</head>
               <lg rend="italic">
                  <l>Reioyce reioyce with heart and voyce,</l>
                  <l>In Christes birth this day reioyce.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>FRom Virgins wombe this day did ſpring,</l>
                  <l>The precious ſeede that only ſaued man:</l>
                  <l>This day let man reioyce and ſweetely ſing,</l>
                  <l>Since on this day ſaluacion firſt began.</l>
                  <l>This day did Chriſt man ſoule from death remoue.</l>
                  <l>With glorious ſaintes to dwell in heauen aboue.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>This day to man, came pledge of perfect peace,</l>
                  <l>This day to man, came loue and vnitie:</l>
                  <l>This day mans griefe began for to ſurceaſe,</l>
                  <l>This day did man receiue a remedie.</l>
                  <l>For each offence and euery deadly ſinne,</l>
                  <l>With guiltie hart that erſt he wandred in.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>In Chriſtes flocke, let loue be ſurely plaſte,</l>
                  <l>From Chriſtes flocke, let concord hate expel:</l>
                  <l>Of Chriſtes flocke let loue be ſo embraſte,</l>
                  <l>As we in Chriſt, and Chriſt in vs may dwel.</l>
                  <l>Chriſt is the authour of all vnitie,</l>
                  <l>From whence proceedeth all felicitie.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>O ſing vnto this glittering glorious king,</l>
                  <l>O prayſe his name let euery liuing thing:</l>
                  <l>Let hart and voyce like Belles of ſiluer ring,</l>
                  <l>The comfort that this day did bring.</l>
                  <l>Let Lute, let Shalme, with ſound of ſweete delight,</l>
                  <l>The ioy of Chriſtes birth this day reſight.</l>
               </lg>
               <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
               <closer>
                  <signed>F. Kindlemarſh.</signed>
               </closer>
            </div>
            <div n="10" type="poem">
               <pb n="5" facs="tcp:12052:7" rendition="simple:additions"/>
               <head>
                  <hi>10.</hi> For Easter dcy.</head>
               <lg>
                  <l>ALl mortal men this day reioice, in Chriſte that you redemed hath,</l>
                  <l>By death w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> death ſing we w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> voice, to him y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> hath appeſd gods wrath</l>
                  <l>Due vnto man for ſinful path, wherein before he went aſtray,</l>
                  <l>Giue thankes to him with perfect faith that for man kinde hath made this glorious day.</l>
                  <l>This day he roſe fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> tombe again, wherin his precious corſe was laid,</l>
                  <l>Whom cruelly y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> Iewes had ſlaine, with blooddy wounds ful il araid:</l>
                  <l>O man be now no more diſmaid, if thou henceforth from ſin do ſtay,</l>
                  <l>Of death thou needeſt not be afraide, Chriſte conquered death for thys his glorious day.</l>
                  <l>His death preuailed had not whitt, As Paule y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> apoſtle wel doth write:</l>
                  <l>Except he had vpriſen yet, from death to life by Godlike might:</l>
                  <l>With moſt triumphant glittering light,</l>
                  <l>This day his glorye ſhined I ſay, and made vs brighte as ſunne thys glorious day</l>
                  <l>O man ariſe with Chriſt therfore, ſince he from ſin hath made thee fre,</l>
                  <l>Beware thou fall in ſinne no more, but riſe as Chriſt did riſe for thee:</l>
                  <l>So maiſt thou him in glory ſee, when he at day of doome ſhall ſay,</l>
                  <l>Come thou my child and dwell with me, God graunt vs all to ſee that glorious day.</l>
               </lg>
               <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
               <closer>
                  <signed>qoth Iaſper Haywood.</signed>
               </closer>
            </div>
            <div n="11" type="poem">
               <head>
                  <hi>11.</hi> For Whitſunday.</head>
               <lg>
                  <l>COme holy ghoſt eternall God, and eaſe the wofull greefe,</l>
                  <l>That through the heapes of heauy ſin, can no where find releefe.</l>
                  <l>Doo thou O God redreſſe</l>
                  <l>The great diſtreſſe</l>
                  <l>Of ſinful heauineſſe.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>Come comfort the afflicted thoughtes of my conſumed hart,</l>
                  <l>O ryd the pearcing pricking paynes of my tormenting ſmart:</l>
                  <l>O holy ghoſt graunt me</l>
                  <l>That I by thee</l>
                  <l>From ſinne may purged be.</l>
                  <l>
                     <pb facs="tcp:12052:8" rendition="simple:additions"/>Thou art my God, to thee alone I will commend my cauſe,</l>
                  <l>Nor glittering gold nor precious ſtone, ſhall make me leaue thy laws:</l>
                  <l>O teach me then the way</l>
                  <l>Whereby I may</l>
                  <l>Make thee my onely ſtay.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>My lippes, my tongue, my hart and al, ſhall ſpread thy mighty name,</l>
                  <l>My voyce ſhall neuer ceaſe to ſound, the prayſes of the ſame:</l>
                  <l>Yea euery liuing thing</l>
                  <l>Shall ſweetely ſing</l>
                  <l>To thee (O heauenly king.)</l>
               </lg>
               <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
               <closer>
                  <signed>F. K.</signed>
               </closer>
            </div>
            <div n="12" type="poem">
               <head>
                  <hi>12.</hi> No pleaſure without ſome payne.</head>
               <lg>
                  <l>SWeete were the ioyes that both might like and laſt,</l>
                  <l>Strange were the ſtate exempt from all diſtreſſe:</l>
                  <l>Happy the life that no miſhap ſhould toſt,</l>
                  <l>Bleſſed the chaunce might neuer change ſucceſſe.</l>
                  <l>Were ſuch a life to lead, or ſtate to proue,</l>
                  <l>Who would not wiſh that ſuch a life were loue.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>But O the ſoury ſauce of ſweete vnſure,</l>
                  <l>When pleaſures flye and flit with waſt of wind:</l>
                  <l>The truſtleſſe traynes that hoping harts allure,</l>
                  <l>When ſweete delightes do but allure the mind.</l>
                  <l>When care conſumes and waſtes the wretched wight,</l>
                  <l>Whyle fancie feedes and drawes of her delight.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>What life were loue, if loue were free from paine?</l>
                  <l>But O that paine with pleaſure match ſhould meete:</l>
                  <l>Why did the courſe of nature ſo ordayne,</l>
                  <l>That ſugred ſowre muſt ſauſe the bitter ſweete.</l>
                  <l>Which ſowre from ſweete might any meanes remoue,</l>
                  <l>What hap, what heauen, what life, were like to loue.</l>
               </lg>
               <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
               <closer>
                  <signed>W. R.</signed>
               </closer>
            </div>
            <div n="13" type="poem">
               <pb n="5" facs="tcp:12052:8" rendition="simple:additions"/>
               <head>13.
<l>Who mindes to bring his Shippe to happy ſhore</l>
                  <l>Must care to know the lawes of wiſedomes love.</l>
               </head>
               <lg>
                  <l>MY freend, if thou wilt credite me in ought,</l>
                  <l>To whom the truth by tryall well appeares:</l>
                  <l>Nought worth is wit til it be dearely bought,</l>
                  <l>There is no wiſedome but in hoary heares.</l>
                  <l>Yet if I may of wiſedome oft define,</l>
                  <l>As well as others haue of happineſſe:</l>
                  <l>Then to my words my freend thy eare encline,</l>
                  <l>The thinges that make thee wiſe are theſe I geſſe,</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>Feare God, and know thy ſelfe in each degree,</l>
                  <l>Be freend to all, familiar but to fewe:</l>
                  <l>To light of credite ſee thou neuer be,</l>
                  <l>For tryall ought in truſt dooth treaſon ſhewe.</l>
                  <l>To others faultes caſt not too much thy eye,</l>
                  <l>Accuſe no man of guilt, amend thy owne:</l>
                  <l>Of medling much doth miſchiefe ought ariſe,</l>
                  <l>And oft debate by tickle tongue is ſowne.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>What thing thou wilt haue hyd, to none declare,</l>
                  <l>In word or deede beware of had I wiſt:</l>
                  <l>So ſpend thy good that ſome thou euer ſpare,</l>
                  <l>For freendes like Haukes doo ſoare from emptie fiſt.</l>
                  <l>Cut out thy coate according to thy cloth,</l>
                  <l>Suſpected perſons ſee thou alwayes flee,</l>
                  <l>Beleeue not him that once hath broke his troth,</l>
                  <l>Nor yet of gift with out deſert be free.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>Time quickly ſlips beware how thou it ſpend,</l>
                  <l>Of wanton youth repents a paynful age:</l>
                  <l>Begin nothing without an eye to thend,</l>
                  <l>Nor how thine eare from counſell of the ſage.</l>
                  <l>If thou too farre let out thy fancy ſlip,</l>
                  <l>And witleſſe will from reaſons rule outſtart:</l>
                  <l>Thy folly ſhall at length be made thy whip,</l>
                  <l>And ſore the ſtripes of ſhame ſhall cauſe the ſmart.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <pb facs="tcp:12052:9" rendition="simple:additions"/>
                  <l>To doo too much for old men is but loſt,</l>
                  <l>Of freendſhip had to women comes like gayne:</l>
                  <l>Beſtow not thou on children too much coſt,</l>
                  <l>For what thou doeſt for theſe is all in vaine.</l>
                  <l>The olde man, or he can requite, he dyes,</l>
                  <l>Vnconſtant is the womans wauering mind:</l>
                  <l>Ful ſoone the boy thy freendſhip will deſpyſe,</l>
                  <l>And him for loue thou ſhalt vngreatfull ſind.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>The aged man is like the barraine ground,</l>
                  <l>The woman like the Reede that wagges with wind:</l>
                  <l>There may no truſt in tender yeeres be found,</l>
                  <l>And of the three, the boy is moſt vnkind.</l>
                  <l>If thou haue found a faithful freend in deede,</l>
                  <l>Beware thou loſe not loue of ſuch a one:</l>
                  <l>He ſhall ſometime ſtand thee in better ſteede,</l>
                  <l>Then treaſure great of gold or precious ſtone.</l>
               </lg>
               <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
               <closer>
                  <signed>Iaſper Heywood.</signed>
               </closer>
            </div>
            <div n="14" type="poem">
               <head>
                  <hi>14.</hi> Of the vnconstant stay of Fortunes giftes.</head>
               <lg>
                  <l>Jf Fortune be thy ſtay, thy ſtate is very tickle,</l>
                  <l>She beares a double face, diſguiſed, falſe, and fickle:</l>
                  <l>This day ſhe ſeemes to ſmile, to morow will ſhe frowne,</l>
                  <l>What now ſhee ſets aloft, anone ſhe throweth downe:</l>
                  <l>Fly Fortunes ſlye deceytes, let Vertue be thy guide,</l>
                  <l>If that you doo intend in happy ſtate to abide.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>Vpon the ſetled rocke thy building ſureſt ſtandes,</l>
                  <l>Away it quickly weares, that reſteth on the ſandes:</l>
                  <l>Dame Vertue is the rocke, that yeeldes aſſured ſtay,</l>
                  <l>Dame Fortune is the ſand, tha ſkoureth ſoone away:</l>
                  <l>Chooſe that is certaine, let thinge vncertayne paſſe,</l>
                  <l>Preferre the precious gold, before the brittle glaſſe.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>Sly Fortune hath her ſlightes, ſhe plaies vpon the packe,</l>
                  <l>Looke whom ſhe fauours moſt, at length ſhe turnes to wracke:</l>
                  <l>
                     <pb n="6" facs="tcp:12052:9"/>But Vertue ſimply deales, ſhe ſhuns deceitful trayne,</l>
                  <l>Who is by Vertue rayſed vp, ſhall neuer fal agayne:</l>
                  <l>Sticke faſt to Vertue then, that giues aſſured truſt,</l>
                  <l>And flye from Fortunes frekes, that euer proue vniuſt</l>
               </lg>
               <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
               <closer>
                  <signed>F. K.</signed>
               </closer>
            </div>
            <div n="15" type="poem">
               <head>
                  <hi>15.</hi> Promiſe is debt.</head>
               <lg>
                  <l>JN my accompt the promiſe that is vowed,</l>
                  <l>Among the good is holden ſuch a debt:</l>
                  <l>As he is thought no whit to be allowed,</l>
                  <l>That ſetteth light his promiſe to forget.</l>
                  <l>And for my part I will not linke in loue,</l>
                  <l>With fickle folke whoſe fancies ought remoue.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>My happy gaine I do eſteeme for ſuch,</l>
                  <l>As fewe haue found in theſe our doubtful dayes:</l>
                  <l>To find a freend I thinke it be as much,</l>
                  <l>As to win a fort ful fraught of noble prayſe.</l>
                  <l>Of all the goods that there may be poſſeſt,</l>
                  <l>A faithfull freend I iudge to be the beſt.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>O freendly league although to late begun,</l>
                  <l>Yet time ſhall trye our troth as well imployed:</l>
                  <l>And that we both ſhall ſee that we haue won,</l>
                  <l>Such faſtned faith as can not be deſtroyed.</l>
                  <l>By enuious rage or ſlaunders bitter blowe,</l>
                  <l>That alwayes ſeekes the good to ouerthrowe.</l>
               </lg>
               <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
               <closer>
                  <signed>R. Hill.</signed>
               </closer>
            </div>
            <div n="16" type="poem">
               <head>
                  <hi>16.</hi> No words, but deedes.</head>
               <lg>
                  <l>THE wrong is great, the payne aboue my power,</l>
                  <l>That yeeldes ſuch care in doubtfull dens to drowne:</l>
                  <l>Such hap is hard wher Fortune doth ſo lower,</l>
                  <l>As freendly looke is turnd to froward frowne.</l>
                  <l>
                     <pb facs="tcp:12052:10"/>Is this the truſt that faithfull freendes can finde?</l>
                  <l>With thoſe that yet haue promiſe broke?</l>
                  <l>By deedes in dout, as though no wordes can binde,</l>
                  <l>A vowed freend to hold him to his yoke.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>O faithleſſe freend, what can aſſure your mind,</l>
                  <l>That doubtes ſo ſoone before you haue cauſe why?</l>
                  <l>To what hard hap doth Fortune here me bind,</l>
                  <l>When words nor deedes can no where ſatiſfye.</l>
                  <l>What can I write? that hath not oft bine ſaide,</l>
                  <l>What haue I ſayd? that hath not bind affyrmed:</l>
                  <l>What not approued? that ought to be aſſayed,</l>
                  <l>Or what is vowed? that ſhall not be perfourmed.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>Caſt of miſtruſt, in haſt no credite giue,</l>
                  <l>To this or that, that breedeth freendes vnreſt:</l>
                  <l>No doubt at all, but truſt me if I liue,</l>
                  <l>My deedes ſhall proue, that all is for the beſt.</l>
                  <l>And this beleeue, the Sea ſhall ceaſe to flowe,</l>
                  <l>The Sunne to ſhine within the ſetled ſkye:</l>
                  <l>All thinges on earth ſhall leaue to ſpring and growe,</l>
                  <l>Yea euery Foule ſhall want his winges to flye.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>Eare I in thought ſhall ſeeme once to retyre,</l>
                  <l>If you my freend remaine as I deſyre:</l>
                  <l>Nowe loſe no time, but vſe that while you may,</l>
                  <l>Forget not this, a dogge ſhall haue a day.</l>
               </lg>
               <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
               <closer>
                  <signed>R. D.</signed>
               </closer>
            </div>
            <div n="17" type="poem">
               <head>
                  <hi>17.</hi> He deſyreth exchange of life.</head>
               <lg>
                  <l>THE day delayed, of that I moſt do wiſhe,</l>
                  <l>Wherewith I feede and ſtarue in one degree:</l>
                  <l>With wiſh and want ſtill ſerued in one diſhe,</l>
                  <l>Aliue as dead, by proofe as you may ſee.</l>
                  <l>To whom of old this prouerbe wel it ſerues,</l>
                  <l>While graſſe dooth grow, the ſelly horſe he ſterues.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <pb n="7" facs="tcp:12052:10"/>
                  <l>Tweene theſe extreames thus doo I rome the race,</l>
                  <l>Of my poore life, this certaynly I know:</l>
                  <l>Tweene would and want vnwarely that do paſſe,</l>
                  <l>More ſwift then ſhot out of Archers bow.</l>
                  <l>As Spider drawes her line all day,</l>
                  <l>I watch the net, and others haue the pray.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>And as by proofe the greedy dogge doth gnawe,</l>
                  <l>The bared bone all onely for the taſte:</l>
                  <l>So to and fro this lothſome life I draw,</l>
                  <l>With fancies forſt and fed with vaine repaſt.</l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Narſiſſus</hi> brought vnto the water brinke,</l>
                  <l>So aye thirſt I, the more that I do drinke.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>Loe thus I dye, and yet I ſeeme not ſicke,</l>
                  <l>With ſmart vnſeene my ſelfe, my ſelfe I weare:</l>
                  <l>With prone deſire and power that is not quicke,</l>
                  <l>With hope aloft now drenched in diſpayre.</l>
                  <l>Trained in truſt for no reward aſſignd,</l>
                  <l>The more I haſt, the more I come behind.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>With hurt to heale, in frozen yſe to frie,</l>
                  <l>With loſſe to laugh, this is a wonderous caſe:</l>
                  <l>Faſt fetred here, is forſt away to flie,</l>
                  <l>As hunted Hare, that Hound hath in the chaſe.</l>
                  <l>With winges and ſpurres, for all the haſt I make,</l>
                  <l>As like to loſe, as for to draw the ſtake.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>The dayes be long that hang vpon deſert,</l>
                  <l>The life is irke of ioyes that be delayed:</l>
                  <l>The time is ſhort for to requite the ſmart,</l>
                  <l>That dooth proceede of promiſe long vnpayed.</l>
                  <l>That to the laſt of this my fainting breath,</l>
                  <l>I wiſh exchange of life for happy death.</l>
               </lg>
               <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
               <closer>
                  <signed>L. Vaux.</signed>
               </closer>
            </div>
            <div n="18" type="poem">
               <pb facs="tcp:12052:11" rendition="simple:additions"/>
               <head>
                  <hi>18.</hi> Of the instabilitie of youth.</head>
               <lg>
                  <l>WHEN I looke backe and in my ſelfe behold,</l>
                  <l>The wandring wayes that youth could not deſcry:</l>
                  <l>And markt the fearful courſe that youth did hold,</l>
                  <l>And mette in mind, eache ſteppe youth ſtrayed a wry.</l>
                  <l>My knees I bowe, and from my hart I call,</l>
                  <l>O Lord, forget theſe faultes and folies all.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>For now I ſee, how voyde youth is of ſkill,</l>
                  <l>I ſee alſo his prime time and his end:</l>
                  <l>I doo confeſſe my faultes and all my ill,</l>
                  <l>And ſorow ſore, for that I did offend,</l>
                  <l>And with a mind repentant of all crimes,</l>
                  <l>Pardon I aſke for youth, ten thouſand times.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>The humble hart, hath daunted the proud mind,</l>
                  <l>Eke wyſedome hath giuen ignorance a fall:</l>
                  <l>And wit hath taught, that folly could not find,</l>
                  <l>And age hath youth, her ſubiect and her thrall.</l>
                  <l>Therfore I pray, O Lord of life and truth,</l>
                  <l>Pardon the faultes committed in my youth.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>Thou that diddeſt graunt the wiſe-king his requeſt,</l>
                  <l>Thou that in the Whale, thy prophet didſt preſerue:</l>
                  <l>Thou that forgaueſt the wounding of thy breſt,</l>
                  <l>Thou that didſt ſaue the theefe in ſtate to ſterue.</l>
                  <l>Thou onely God, the giuer of all grace,</l>
                  <l>Wipe out of mind, the path of youthes vaine race.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>Thou that by power, to life didſt raiſe the dead.</l>
                  <l>Thou that reſtoreſt the blind to ſight:</l>
                  <l>Thou that for loue, thy life and loue out bled,</l>
                  <l>Thou that of fauour, madeſt the lame goe right.</l>
                  <l>Thou that canſt heale, and helpe in all aſſayes,</l>
                  <l>Forgiue the gilth, that grewe in youthes vaine wayes.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <pb n="8" facs="tcp:12052:11" rendition="simple:additions"/>
                  <l>And now ſince I, with faith and doubtleſſe mind,</l>
                  <l>Doo flye to thée by prayer to appeaſe thy yre:</l>
                  <l>And ſince that thee I onely ſeeke to finde,</l>
                  <l>And hope by faith to attayne my iuſt deſire.</l>
                  <l>Lord mind no more youthes error and vnſkill,</l>
                  <l>And able age, to doo thy holy will.</l>
               </lg>
               <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
               <closer>
                  <signed>L. Vaux.</signed>
               </closer>
            </div>
            <div n="19" type="poem">
               <head>19.
<l>Most happy is that state alone,</l>
                  <l>Where words and deedes agree in one.</l>
               </head>
               <lg>
                  <l>BY paynted words, the ſilly ſimple man,</l>
                  <l>To truſtleſſe trap, is trayned now and than:</l>
                  <l>And by conſeyt, of ſweete alluring tale,</l>
                  <l>He bites the baits, that breedes his bitter bale.</l>
                  <l>To beawties blaze, caſt not thy rouing eye:</l>
                  <l>In pleaſant greene, doo ſtinging ſerpents lye.</l>
                  <l>The golden Pill, hath but a bitter taſt,</l>
                  <l>In glittering glaſſe, a poyſon ranckeſt plaſte.</l>
                  <l>So pleaſant wordes, without performing deedes:</l>
                  <l>May well be deemed to ſpring of Darnel ſeedes.</l>
                  <l>The freendly deede is it, that quickly tryes:</l>
                  <l>Where truſty faith, and freendly meaning lyes.</l>
                  <l>That ſtate therefore moſt happy ſeemes to be:</l>
                  <l>Where wordes and deedes, moſt faithfully agree.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>My freend yf thou wilt keepe thy honeſt name:</l>
                  <l>Fly from the blot, of barking ſlaunders blame.</l>
                  <l>Let not in word thy promiſe be more large:</l>
                  <l>Then thou in deede, art willing to diſcharge.</l>
                  <l>Abhorred is that falſe diſſembling broode:</l>
                  <l>That ſeemes to beare two faces in one hoode.</l>
                  <l>to ſay a thing, and not to meane the ſame:</l>
                  <l>Wyll turne at length to loſſe of thy good name.</l>
                  <l>Wherefore my freend, let double dealing goe:</l>
                  <l>In ſtead whereof, let perfect playneneſſe flowe.</l>
                  <l>
                     <pb facs="tcp:12052:12" rendition="simple:additions"/>Doo thou no more, in idle wordes exceede:</l>
                  <l>Then thou intendes to doe, in very deede.</l>
                  <l>So good report, ſhall ſpread thy worthy prayſe:</l>
                  <l>For being iuſt in word and deede alwayes.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>You worldly wightes that worldly dooers are:</l>
                  <l>Before you let your word ſlip out to farre,</l>
                  <l>Conſider well, what inconuenience ſpringes:</l>
                  <l>By breache of promiſe made, in lawfull thinges.</l>
                  <l>Firſt, God miſlikes where ſuch deceit doth ſwarme:</l>
                  <l>Next, it renoundeth vnto thy neighboures harme.</l>
                  <l>And laſt of all, which is not leaſt of all:</l>
                  <l>For ſuch offence, thy conſcience ſuffer ſhall.</l>
                  <l>As barren groundes, bringes forth but rotten weedes:</l>
                  <l>From barren words, ſo fruitleſſe chaffe proceedes.</l>
                  <l>As ſauery flowres, doo ſpring in fertil ground:</l>
                  <l>So truſty freendes, by tryall ſoone are found.</l>
                  <l>To ſhunne therefore the woorſt, that may enſue:</l>
                  <l>Let deedes alway, approue thy ſayings true.</l>
               </lg>
               <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
               <closer>
                  <signed>F. K.</signed>
               </closer>
            </div>
            <div n="20" type="poem">
               <head>20.
<l>Who wyll aſpire to dignitie.</l>
                  <l>By learning must aduaunced be.</l>
               </head>
               <lg>
                  <l>THE poore that liue in needy rate, by learning doo great riches gayne:</l>
                  <l>The rich that liue in welthy ſtate, by learning do their welth maintayne.</l>
                  <l>Thus rich and poore, are furthered ſtill,</l>
                  <l>By ſacred rules of learned ſkill.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>All fond conceites of franticke youth, the golden gift of learning ſtayes:</l>
                  <l>Of doubtfull things to ſearch the truth, learning ſets foorth the reddy wayes.</l>
                  <l>O happy him doo I repute,</l>
                  <l>Whoſe breſt is fraught with learning fruite.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>There growes no corne within the fielde, that Oxe and Plough did neuer tyll,</l>
                  <l>Right ſo the mind no fruite can yeeld, that is not lead by learnings ſkill.</l>
                  <l>Of ignoraunce comes rotten weedes,</l>
                  <l>Of learning ſpringes right noble deedes.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <pb n="9" facs="tcp:12052:12" rendition="simple:additions"/>
                  <l>Like as the Captayne hath reſpect, to trayne his ſouldiers in aray:</l>
                  <l>So learning doth mans mind direct, by Vertues ſtaffe his life to ſtay.</l>
                  <l>Though Freendes and Fortune waxeth ſkant,</l>
                  <l>Yet learned men ſhall neuer want.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>You Impes therfore in youth be ſure, to fraught your mindes w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> learned thinges,</l>
                  <l>For learning is the fountayne pure, out from the which all glory ſpringes.</l>
                  <l>Who ſo therefore will glory win,</l>
                  <l>With learning firſt muſt needes begin.</l>
               </lg>
               <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
               <closer>
                  <signed>F. K.</signed>
               </closer>
            </div>
            <div n="21" type="poem">
               <head>21.
<l>Mans flittyng life findes ſurest stay.</l>
                  <l>Where ſacred Vertue beareth ſway.</l>
               </head>
               <lg>
                  <l>THE ſturdy Rocke for all his ſtrength, by raging Seas is rent in twayne:</l>
                  <l>The Marble ſtone is pearſt at length, with little droppes of drifling rayne.</l>
                  <l>The Oxe dooth yeeld vnto the yoke,</l>
                  <l>The Steele obeyeth the hammer ſtroke.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>The ſtately Stagge that ſeemes ſo ſtout, by yalping hounds at bay is ſet:</l>
                  <l>The ſwifteſt bird that flees aboue, is caught at length in Fowlers net.</l>
                  <l>The greateſt Fiſh in deepeſt Brooke,</l>
                  <l>Is ſoone deceiued with ſubtill hooke.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1+ letters">
                        <desc>•…</desc>
                     </gap>e man him ſelfe, vnto whoſe will, all thinges are bounden to obey:</l>
                  <l>For all his witte and worthy ſkill, dooth fade at length and fall away.</l>
                  <l>There is nothing, but time doth waſt,</l>
                  <l>The Heauens, the Earth, conſume at laſt.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>But Vertue ſittes triumphing ſtill, vpon the Trone of glorious Fame:</l>
                  <l>Though ſpitfull death mans body kill, yet hurtes he not his vertuous name.</l>
                  <l>By life or death, what ſo betides,</l>
                  <l>The ſtate of Vertue, neuer ſlides.</l>
               </lg>
               <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
               <closer>
                  <signed>M. Y.</signed>
               </closer>
            </div>
            <div n="22" type="poem">
               <pb facs="tcp:12052:13" rendition="simple:additions"/>
               <head>
                  <hi>22.</hi> Nothing is comparable vnto a faithfull freend,</head>
               <lg>
                  <l>SIth this our time of Freendſhip is ſo ſkant,</l>
                  <l>Sith Freendſhip now in euery place doth want.</l>
                  <l>Sith euery man of Freendſhip is ſo hollowe,</l>
                  <l>As no man rightly knowes which way to followe.</l>
                  <l>Seaſe not my Muſe, ſeaſe not in theſe our dayes,</l>
                  <l>To ring loude peales, of ſacred Freendſhips prayſe.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>If men be now, their owne peculier freendes,</l>
                  <l>And to their neighbours freendſhip none pertendes.</l>
                  <l>If men of Freendſhip ſhewe them ſelues ſo bare,</l>
                  <l>And of their brethren take no Freendly care.</l>
                  <l>Forbeare not then my Muſe, nor feare not then,</l>
                  <l>To ring diſprayſe of theſe vnfreendly men.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>Did man of Freendſhip know the mighty power?</l>
                  <l>How great effectes it worketh euery houre.</l>
                  <l>What ſtore of hidden freendſhip it retaynes,</l>
                  <l>How ſtill it powreth forth aboundaunt gaines.</l>
                  <l>Man would with thee my muſe in theſe our dayes,</l>
                  <l>Ring out loude peales, of ſacred Freendſhips prayſe.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>Freendſhip releeueth mans neceſſitie,</l>
                  <l>Freendſhip, comforteth mans aduerſitie.</l>
                  <l>Freendſhip augmenteth mans proſperitie,</l>
                  <l>Freendſhip preferres man to felicitie.</l>
                  <l>Then ring my muſe, ring out in theſe our dayes,</l>
                  <l>Ring out loude peales, of ſacred freendſhips prayſe.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>Of Freendſhip, growes loue and charitie,</l>
                  <l>By Freendſhip, men are linked in amitie:</l>
                  <l>From Freendſhip ſpringeth all commoditie,</l>
                  <l>The fruite of Freendſhip, is fidelitie.</l>
                  <l>Oh ring my muſe, ring out in theſe our dayes,</l>
                  <l>Peale vpon peale, of ſacred Freendſhips prayſe.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <pb n="10" facs="tcp:12052:13" rendition="simple:additions"/>
                  <l>That man with man, true freendſhip may embrace,</l>
                  <l>That man to man, may ſhew a freendly face:</l>
                  <l>That euery man, may ſow ſuch freendly ſeedes,</l>
                  <l>As freendſhip may be found in freendly deedes.</l>
                  <l>And ioyne with thee my Muſe in theſe our dayes,</l>
                  <l>To ring loud peales of ſacred Freendſhips prayſe.</l>
               </lg>
               <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
               <closer>
                  <signed>F. K.</signed>
               </closer>
            </div>
            <div n="23" type="poem">
               <head>
                  <hi>23.</hi> Remember thy ende.</head>
               <lg>
                  <l>TO be as wiſe as <hi>CATO</hi> was, or rich as <hi>CRESVS</hi> in his life:</l>
                  <l>To haue the ſtrength of <hi>Hercules,</hi> which did ſubdue by force or ſtrife.</l>
                  <l>What helpeth it when Death doth call,</l>
                  <l>The happy ende exceedeth all.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>The Rich may well the Poore releeue, the Rulers may redreſſe each wrong:</l>
                  <l>The learned may good counſell giue, but marke the end of this my ſong:</l>
                  <l>Who doth theſe thinges, happy they call,</l>
                  <l>Their happy end exceedeth all.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>The happieſt end, in theſe our dayes, that all do ſeeke, both ſmall and great:</l>
                  <l>Is ey<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ther for Fame, or els for Prayſe, or who may ſitte in higheſt ſeate.</l>
                  <l>But of theſe thinges, hap what hap ſhall,</l>
                  <l>The happy end exceedeth all.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>A good beginning ought we ſee, but ſeeldome ſtanding at one ſtay:</l>
                  <l>For few do like the meane degree, then prayſe at parting ſome men ſay.</l>
                  <l>The thinges wherto each wight is thrall,</l>
                  <l>The happy end exceedeth all.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>The meane eſtate, that happy life, which liueth vnder gouernance:</l>
                  <l>Who ſeekes no hate, nor breedes no ſtrife, but takes in worth his happy chance.</l>
                  <l>If contentation him befall,</l>
                  <l>His happy end exceedeth all.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>The longer-life that we deſire, the more offence doth dayly grow:</l>
                  <l>The greater payne it doth require, Except the Iudge ſome mercy ſhew.</l>
                  <l>Wherfore I thinke and euer ſhall,</l>
                  <l>The happy end exceedeth all.</l>
               </lg>
               <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
               <closer>
                  <signed>D. S.</signed>
               </closer>
            </div>
            <div n="24" type="poem">
               <pb facs="tcp:12052:14" rendition="simple:additions"/>
               <head>24.
<l>He perſwadeth his freend,</l>
                  <l>from the fond Affectes of loue.</l>
               </head>
               <lg>
                  <l>WHY art thou bound &amp; maiſt go fre, ſhal reaſon yeld to raging wil?</l>
                  <l>Is thraldom like to libertye? wilt thou exchange thy good for ill?</l>
                  <l>Then ſhalt thou learne a childiſh play, and of each part to taſt and proue:</l>
                  <l>The lookers on ſhall iudge and ſay, loe this is he that liues by loue.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>Thy wittes with thoughts, ſhall ſtand at ſtay, thy head ſhall haue but heauy reſt.</l>
                  <l>Thy eyes ſhal watch for wanton prayes, thy tongue ſhall ſhew thy harts requeſt.</l>
                  <l>Thy eares ſhall heare a thouſand noyſe, thy hand ſhall put thy pen to payne:</l>
                  <l>And in the ende, thou ſhalt diſprayſe, thy life ſo ſpent, for ſuch ſmall gaine.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>If loue and liſt might euer cope, or youth might runne in reaſons race:</l>
                  <l>Or if ſtrong ſute might win ſure hope, I would leſſe blame a louers caſe.</l>
                  <l>For loue is hotte, with great deſire, and ſweete delight makes youth ſo fond,</l>
                  <l>That little ſparkes will proue great fyre, and bring free harts to endleſſe bond.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>Firſt count the care and then the coſt, and marke what fraude in faith is found:</l>
                  <l>Then after come and make thy boſt, and ſhew ſome cauſe why thou art bound.</l>
                  <l>For when the wine doth runne full low, you ſhall be faine to drinke the lies:</l>
                  <l>And eate the fleſh ful well I know, that hath ben blowne with many flies.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>We ſee where great deuotion is, the people kneele and kiſſe the croſſe:</l>
                  <l>And though we find ſmall fault of this, Yet ſome will gilld a bridles boſſe.</l>
                  <l>A foole his bable will not change, not for the ſepter of a king,</l>
                  <l>A louers life is nothing ſtrange, for youth delightes none other thing.</l>
               </lg>
               <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
               <closer>
                  <signed>Tho. Churchyard.</signed>
               </closer>
            </div>
            <div n="25" type="poem">
               <head>
                  <hi>25.</hi> Wanting his deſyre he complayneth.</head>
               <lg>
                  <l>THe ſayling ſhips with ioy at length, doo touch their long deſired port,</l>
                  <l>The hewing axe the Oke doth waſt, the battring Canon breakes the fort.</l>
                  <l>Hard hagard haukes ſtoope to the lure, wild coltes in time the bridle tames:</l>
                  <l>There is nothing ſo out of vre, but to his kind long time it frames.</l>
                  <l>Yet this I find in time, no time can winne my ſute,</l>
                  <l>Though oft the tree I climbe, I can not catch the fruite.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <pb n="11" facs="tcp:12052:14" rendition="simple:additions"/>
                  <l>And yet the pleaſant branches oft, in yeelding wiſe to me do bow,</l>
                  <l>When I would touch they ſpring aloft, ſoone are they gone I wot not how</l>
                  <l>Thus I preſent the fleeting floode, like <hi>Tantalus</hi> in hel below,</l>
                  <l>Would God my caſe ſhee vnderſtoode, whirh can full ſoone releeue my woe</l>
                  <l>Which if to her were knowen, the fruite were ſurely mine,</l>
                  <l>She would not let me grone, and brouſe vpon the rine.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>But if my ſhip with tackle torne, with rented ſailes muſt needs retire.</l>
                  <l>And ſtreame and wind hath plainly ſworn, by force to hinder my deſire</l>
                  <l>Like one y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> ſtricks vpon y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> rocks, my wearie wracke I ſhoulde bewayle</l>
                  <l>And learn to knowe falſe fortunes mockes, who ſmiles on me to ſmall auaile.</l>
                  <l>Yet ſith ſhe onely can, my rented ſhip reſtore,</l>
                  <l>To helpe her wracked man, but once I ſeeke no more.</l>
               </lg>
               <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
               <closer>
                  <signed>M. Ewardes.</signed>
               </closer>
            </div>
            <div n="26" type="poem">
               <head>
                  <hi>26.</hi> Trye before you truste.</head>
               <l>IN freendes are found a heape of doubts, that double dealing vſe,</l>
               <l>A ſwarme of ſuch I could find out, whoſe craft I can accuſe:</l>
               <l>A face for loue, a hart for hate, theſe faigned freendes can beare,</l>
               <l>A tongue for troth, a head for wyles, to hurt each ſimple eare.</l>
               <l>In humble port, is poyſon pact, that plaineneſſe can not ſpie.</l>
               <l>Which creadites all, and can not ſee, where ſtinging ſerpents lye.</l>
               <l>Through haſtie truſt, the harmeleſſe heart, is eaſely hampred in,</l>
               <l>And made beleeue it is good gold, when it is lead and tin.</l>
               <l>The firſt deceit that bleares myne eyes, is faigned faith profeſt,</l>
               <l>The ſecond trappe is grating talke, that gripes each ſtrangers breſt.</l>
               <l>The third deceite is greeting wordes, with colours painted out,</l>
               <l>Which bids ſuſpect to feare no ſmart, nor dread no dangerous doubt.</l>
               <l>The fourth, and laſt is long repaire, which creepes in freendſhips lap,</l>
               <l>And dayly hauntes, that vnder truſt, deuiſeth many a trap.</l>
               <l>Loe how falſe freendes can frame a fetch, to win the will with wils,</l>
               <l>To ſauce their ſlightes with ſugred ſops, and ſhadow harme w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> ſmiles.</l>
               <l>To ſerue their luſtes, are ſundry ſorts, by practiſe diuers kindes,</l>
               <l>Some carries honnie in their mouthes, and venime in their mindes.</l>
               <l>Mee thinkes the ſtones within the ſtreetes, ſhould cry out in this caſe,</l>
               <l>And euery one that doth them meete, ſhould ſhunne their double face.</l>
               <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
               <closer>
                  <signed>D. S.</signed>
               </closer>
            </div>
            <div n="27" type="poem">
               <pb facs="tcp:12052:15" rendition="simple:additions"/>
               <head>
                  <hi>27.</hi> A Lady forſaken complayneth.</head>
               <l>JF pleaſures be in paynfulnes? in pleaſures dooth my body reſt,</l>
               <l>If ioyes accord with carefulnes? a ioyful hart is in my breſt:</l>
               <l>If priſon ſtrong is libertie? in libertie long haue I bene,</l>
               <l>If ioyes accord with miſerye? who can compare a life to mine.</l>
               <l>Who can vnbind y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> is ſore bound? who can make free y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> is ſore thrall,</l>
               <l>Or how can any meanes be found to comfort ſuch a wretch withall.</l>
               <l>None can, but he y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> hath my hart, conuert my paynes to comfort then.</l>
               <l>Yet ſince his ſeruant I became, moſt like a bondman haue I beene:</l>
               <l>Since firſt in bondage I became, my words &amp; deedes were euer ſuch,</l>
               <l>That neuer once he could me blame, except from louing him too much.</l>
               <l>Which I can iudge no iuſt offence, nor cauſe that I deſerue diſdaine,</l>
               <l>Except he mean through falſe pretence, through forged loue to make a train.</l>
               <l>Nay, nay, alas, my fained thoughts, my fre<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ded &amp; my fained ruth</l>
               <l>My pleaſures paſt my preſent plaints, ſhew wel I mean but to much truth</l>
               <l>But ſince I can not him attain, againſt my wil I let him goe.</l>
               <l>And leſt he glory at my paine, I will attempt to cloke my woe.</l>
               <l>Youth, learn by me, but do not proue, for I haue proued to my paine,</l>
               <l>What greeuous griefes do grow by loue, &amp; what it is to loue in vaine.</l>
               <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
               <closer>
                  <signed>M. D.</signed>
               </closer>
            </div>
            <div n="28" type="poem">
               <head>
                  <hi>28.</hi> Finding worldly ioyes but vanities, he wiſheth death.</head>
               <l>FOrlorne in filthy froward fate, wherin a thouſand cares I find,</l>
               <l>By whom I do lament my ſtate, annoid with fond afflicted minde</l>
               <l>A wretch in woe, and dare not cry,</l>
               <l>I liue, and yet I wiſh to dye.</l>
               <l>The day in dole, that ſemeth long, I pas with ſighes &amp; heauy cheere.</l>
               <l>And with theſe eyes I vewe the wrong, that I ſuſtain by liuing here:</l>
               <l>Where my miſhaps as rife doo dwell,</l>
               <l>As plagues within the pit of hell.</l>
               <l>A wailing wight I walke alone, in deſart dennes there to complaine,</l>
               <l>Among the ſauage ſort to mone, I flee my freends wher they remain:</l>
               <l>And pleaſure take to ſhun the ſight,</l>
               <l>Where erſt I felt my great delight.</l>
               <l>
                  <pb n="12" facs="tcp:12052:15" rendition="simple:additions"/>A captaine clapt in chaynes of care, lapt in the lawes of lethal loue,</l>
               <l>My fleſh and bones conſumed bare, w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> crauling greefes full ſtrange to proue:</l>
               <l>Though hap doth bid me hope at leaſt,</l>
               <l>Whyles graſſe doth grow, yet ſtarues the beaſt.</l>
               <l>A ſeeged fort with forrain force, for want of ayde, muſt yeeld at laſt,</l>
               <l>So muſt my weried pined corſe, ſubmit it ſelfe to bitter taſt:</l>
               <l>Of crauling care, that carkes my breſt,</l>
               <l>Till hope or death, ſhall breede my reſt.</l>
               <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
               <closer>
                  <signed>F. M.</signed>
               </closer>
            </div>
            <div n="29" type="poem">
               <head>
                  <hi>29.</hi> A replie to M. Edwards MAY.</head>
               <lg>
                  <l>
                     <hi>J</hi> Read a maying rime of late delighted much my eare,</l>
                  <l>It may delight as many moe, as it ſhall reade or heare.</l>
                  <l>To ſee how there is ſhewed, how May is much of price,</l>
                  <l>And eake to May when that you may, euen ſo is his aduice.</l>
                  <l>It ſeemes he meant to may himſelfe, and ſo to vſe his ſkill,</l>
                  <l>For that the time did ſerue ſo well, in May to haue his will.</l>
                  <l>His onely May was eaſe of mind, ſo farre as I can geſſe,</l>
                  <l>And that his may his mind did pleaſe, a man can iudge no leſſe.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>And as himſelfe did reape the fruites, of that his pleaſant May,</l>
                  <l>He wils his freende the ſame to vſe, in time when as he may.</l>
                  <l>He is not for him ſelfe it ſeemes, but wiſheth well to all,</l>
                  <l>For y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> he would they ſhould, take May in time when it doth fall.</l>
                  <l>So vſe your May, you may, it can not hurtful be,</l>
                  <l>And May well vſed in time and place, may make you mery gle:</l>
                  <l>Modeſt maying metteſt is, of this you may be ſuer,</l>
                  <l>A modeſt maying quietnes, to Mayers doth procure.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>Who may and will not take, may wiſh he had ſo done,</l>
                  <l>Who may and it doth take, may thinke he tooke too ſone.</l>
                  <l>So ioyne your May with wiſedomes lore, and then you may be ſuer,</l>
                  <l>Who makes his May in other ſort, his vnreſt may procuer.</l>
                  <l>Some May before May come, ſome May when May is paſt,</l>
                  <l>Some make their May to late, and ſome doe May poſthaſt.</l>
                  <l>Let wiſedome rule I ſay your May, and thus I make anende,</l>
                  <l>And May, that when you liſt to May, a good may God you ſende.</l>
               </lg>
               <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
               <closer>
                  <signed>M. S.</signed>
               </closer>
            </div>
            <div n="30" type="poem">
               <pb facs="tcp:12052:16" rendition="simple:additions"/>
               <head>
                  <hi>30.</hi> Hauing marryed a worthy Lady, and taken away by death, he com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>playneth his miſhap.</head>
               <l>JN youth when I at large did lead, my life in luſty libertie,</l>
               <l>When heuy thoughts no one did ſpread, to let my pleaſant fantaſy:</l>
               <l>No fortune ſeemd, ſo hard could fall,</l>
               <l>This freedome then, that might make thrall.</l>
               <l>And twentie yeeres I ſkarſe had ſpent, whe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> to make ful my happy fate</l>
               <l>Both treaſures great were on me caſt, with lands &amp; titles of eſtate:</l>
               <l>So as more bleſt then I, ſtoode than,</l>
               <l>Eke as me thought was neuer man.</l>
               <l>For of Dame Fortune who is he, could more deſire by iuſt requeſt,</l>
               <l>Then health, with wealth, and liberty, al which at once I this poſſeſt:</l>
               <l>But maſking in this ioly ioy,</l>
               <l>A ſoden ſyght, prooud al a toy.</l>
               <l>For paſſing on theſe mery dayes, w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> new deuice of pleaſures great,</l>
               <l>And now and then to view y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> rayes of beauties works w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> cunning feat:</l>
               <l>In heauenly hewes, all which as one,</l>
               <l>I oft behelde, but bound to none.</l>
               <l>And one day rowling thus my eyes, vpon theſe bleſſed wights at eaſe,</l>
               <l>Amongſt y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> reſt one did I ſe, who ſtraight my wa<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>dring lokes did ſeaſe:</l>
               <l>And ſtayed them firme, but ſuch a ſight,</l>
               <l>Of beauty yet ſaw neuer wight.</l>
               <l>What ſhal I ſeke to praiſe it more, wher tongs cannot wel praiſe y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſa<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>e</l>
               <l>But to be ſhort to louers lore, I ſtraight my ſences all did frame:</l>
               <l>And were it wit, or were it chaunce,</l>
               <l>I woonne the Garland in this daunce.</l>
               <l>And thus wher I before had thought, no hap my fortu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>e might encreſe</l>
               <l>A double blis this cha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce forth brought, ſo did my ladies loue me pleaſe</l>
               <l>Her faith ſo firme, and conſtant ſuch,</l>
               <l>As neuer hart, can praiſe too much,</l>
               <l>But now with torments ſtrange I taſt, y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> fickle ſtay of fortunes whele,</l>
               <l>And where ſhee raiſed from high to caſt, with greater force of grefe to feele:</l>
               <l>For from this hap of ſoden frowne,</l>
               <l>Of Princes face ſhe threw me downe,</l>
               <l>
                  <pb n="13" facs="tcp:12052:16" rendition="simple:additions"/>And thus exchange now hath it made, by liberty a thing moſt deare,</l>
               <l>In hateful priſon for to fade, where ſundred from my louing feare,</l>
               <l>My wealth and health, ſtands at like ſtay,</l>
               <l>Obſcurely to conſume away.</l>
               <l>And laſt when humain force was none, could part our loue wherin we liued,</l>
               <l>My ladies life alas is gon, moſt cruel death hath it bereued:</l>
               <l>Whoſe vertues, her, to God, hath wonne,</l>
               <l>And left me here, a man vndone.</l>
               <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
               <closer>
                  <signed>F. G.</signed>
               </closer>
            </div>
            <div n="31" type="poem">
               <head>31. A worthy ditie, ſong before the Queenes Maiestie at Bristowe.</head>
               <lg>
                  <l>MIſtruſt not troth, that truely meanes, for euery ielous freke,</l>
                  <l>In ſtead of wrong, conde<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ne not right, no hidden wrath to wreke:</l>
                  <l>Looke on the light of faultleſſe life, how bright her vertues ſhine,</l>
                  <l>And meaſure out her ſteppes each one, by leuel and by line.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>Deeme eche deſert by vpright geſſe, wherby your prayſe ſhall liue,</l>
                  <l>If malice would be match with might, let hate no iudgement giue:</l>
                  <l>Enforce no feare with wreſting wittes, in quiet conſcience breſt.</l>
                  <l>Lend not your eares to buſie tongues, which breedeth much vnreſt.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>In doubtfull drifts wade not to farre, it weries but the mind,</l>
                  <l>Seeke not to ſearch the ſecreat harts, whoſe thoughts are hard to finde</l>
                  <l>Auoide from you thoſe hateful heads, that helpes to heape miſhap,</l>
                  <l>Be ſlow to heare the flatterers voice, that creepeth in your lap.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>Embrace their loue that wills you good, and ſport not at their prayſe,</l>
                  <l>Truſt not too much vnto your ſelfe, for feeble are your ſtayes:</l>
                  <l>How can your ſeate be ſetled faſte, or ſtand on ſtedfaſt ground,</l>
                  <l>ſo propped vp with hollow harts, whoſe ſurety is vnſound.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>Giue faith to thoſe that feare for loue, and not that loue for feare,</l>
                  <l>Regard not them that force compels, to pleaſe you euery where:</l>
                  <l>All this well waid and borne away, ſhall ſtabliſh long your ſtate,</l>
                  <l>Continually with perfect peace, in ſpite of puſſing hate.</l>
               </lg>
               <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
               <closer>
                  <signed>D. S.</signed>
               </closer>
            </div>
            <div n="32" type="poem">
               <pb facs="tcp:12052:17" rendition="simple:additions"/>
               <head>32. An Epitaph vpon the death of Syr Edward Saunders. Knight, Lord cheefe Boron of the Exchequer.</head>
               <l>YOV Muſes weare your mourning weeds, ſtrike on y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> fatal Drome</l>
               <l>Sound <hi>Triton</hi> out the trumpe of fame, in ſpite of <hi>Pareas</hi> dome.</l>
               <l>Diſtill <hi>Parnaſſus</hi> pleaſant drops, poſſeſſe <hi>Pierides</hi> plaſe,</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Apollo</hi> helpe with dolefull tune, to wayle this wofull caſe.</l>
               <l>Wring hard you hands, waile on you loſſe, lament the fate that fell,</l>
               <l>With ſobs and ſighes to <hi>Saunders</hi> ſay, oh <hi>Saunders</hi> now farewell.</l>
               <l>Whom <hi>Phaebus</hi> fed with <hi>Pallas</hi> pappe, as one of <hi>Sibils</hi> ſeede,</l>
               <l>Loe here where death did reſt his corpes, the vermine foule to feede.</l>
               <l>Whom Impes of <hi>Ioue</hi> with <hi>Necter</hi> ſweete, long in <hi>Libethres</hi> nourſht,</l>
               <l>Behold how dreadful death him brought, to y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> whence he came firſt.</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Lycurgus</hi> he for learned lawes, <hi>Rhadamanthus</hi> race that ranne,</l>
               <l>Another <hi>Nestor</hi> for aduiſe, <hi>Zalucus</hi> fame that wanne.</l>
               <l>A <hi>Damon</hi> deare vnto his freend, in faith like <hi>Phocion</hi> found,</l>
               <l>A <hi>Cato</hi> that could counſel giue, to prince a ſubiect ſound.</l>
               <l>Not <hi>Athens</hi> for their <hi>Solon</hi> ſage, not <hi>Rome</hi> for <hi>Numa</hi> waile,</l>
               <l>As we for <hi>Saunders</hi> death haue cauſe, in fods of teares to ſaile.</l>
               <l>Not <hi>Sparta</hi> card for <hi>Chilos</hi> death, ne proud <hi>Prienna</hi> preſt,</l>
               <l>To weepe for <hi>Bias</hi> as we wayle, for <hi>Saunders</hi> late poſſeſt.</l>
               <l>His learned pathes his talentes rare, ſo now by death appeares,</l>
               <l>As he that <hi>Salomon</hi> ſought to ſerue, in prime and youthful yeeres,</l>
               <l>His counſel ſad, his rules, his lawes, in country ſoyle ſo wrought,</l>
               <l>As though in <hi>Cuma</hi> he had benn, of ſage <hi>Sibilla</hi> taught.</l>
               <l>His vertuous life was ſuch I ſay, as Vertue did embrace,</l>
               <l>By Vertue taught in Vertues ſchoole, to grow in vertues race.</l>
               <l>Might tender babes, might orphants weak, might widows rere y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> cry,</l>
               <l>The ſound thereof ſhoulde pearce the cloudes, to ſkale y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> empire ſky.</l>
               <l>To bid the gods to battel bend, and to diſſend in ſight,</l>
               <l>Though ffarre vnfit, and mates vnmeete, with mortal men to fight.</l>
               <l>Too late (alas) we wiſh his life, to ſoone deceiued vs Death.</l>
               <l>Too little wit we haue to ſeeke, the dead agayne to breath.</l>
               <l>What helpleſſe is, muſt careleſſe be, as Natures courſe doth ſhewe,</l>
               <l>For death ſhal reape what life hath ſowen, by nature this we know.</l>
               <l>
                  <pb n="14" facs="tcp:12052:17"/>Where is that ferce <hi>Achilles</hi> fled, where is king <hi>Turnus</hi> ſhroude,</l>
               <l>What is be come of <hi>Priamus</hi> ſtate, where is <hi>Periander</hi> proude:</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Hector, Hanno, Hanibal,</hi> dead, <hi>Pompei, Pirrhus</hi> ſpild,</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Scipio, Cirus, Caeſar</hi> ſlaine, and <hi>Alexander</hi> kild.</l>
               <l>So long there Fortune faſt did floe, and charged Fame to ſound,</l>
               <l>Tyll frowning Fortune foyld by fate, which fawning fortune found:</l>
               <l>Shun Fortunes feates, ſhake fortune of to none is fortune ſound,</l>
               <l>Sith none may ſay of Fortune ſo, I Fortune faithful found.</l>
               <l>Beholde where Fortune flowed ſo faſt, and fauoured Saunders lure,</l>
               <l>Till fickle Fortune falſe again did Saunders death procure.</l>
               <l>Lo clothed could in cloddes of clay, in droſſy duſt remaine,</l>
               <l>By fate returnd from whence he came, to his mothers wombe againe.</l>
               <l>Who welnigh thirtie yeeres was Iudge, before a Iudge dyd fall,</l>
               <l>And iudged by that mighty Iudge, which Iudge ſhall iudge vs all.</l>
               <l>The heauens may of right reioyce, and earth may it bewayle,</l>
               <l>Sith heauen wan, and earth hath loſt, the guide and arke of vaile.</l>
               <l>There gaine is much, our loſſe is great, there mirth our mone is ſuch,</l>
               <l>That they may laugh as cauſe doo yeeld, and we may weepe as much:</l>
               <l>O happy he, vnhappy we, his hap doth aye encreaſe,</l>
               <l>Happy he, and hapleſſe we, his hap ſhall neuer ceaſe.</l>
               <l>We liue to dye, he dyed to liue, we want, and he poſſeſt,</l>
               <l>We bide in bands, he bathes in bliſſe, the Gods aboue him bleſt.</l>
               <l>Being borne to liue, he liued to dye, and dyed to God ſo plaine,</l>
               <l>That birth, that life, that death, doo ſhew, that he ſhall liue againe:</l>
               <l>His youth to age, his age to death, his death to fame applied,</l>
               <l>His fame to time, his time to God, thus Saunders liued and dyed.</l>
               <l>O happy life, O happier death, O tenne times happy he,</l>
               <l>Whoſe hap it was, ſuch hap to haue, a Iudge this age to be.</l>
               <l>Oh ioyfull time, oh bleſſed ſoyle, where <hi>Pallas</hi> rules with witte,</l>
               <l>O noble ſtate, O ſacred ſeate, where <hi>Saba</hi> ſage dooth ſitte.</l>
               <l>Like <hi>Suſan</hi> ſound, like <hi>Sara</hi> ſad, with <hi>Hesters</hi> mace in hand,</l>
               <l>With <hi>Iudiths</hi> ſword <hi>Bellona</hi> like, to rule this noble land.</l>
               <l>I had my will, you haue your wiſh, I laugh, reioyce you may,</l>
               <l>I wan now much, you gaine no leſſe, to ſee this happy day.</l>
               <l>Wherein I dyed, wherein you liue, Oh treble happy coſt,</l>
               <l>Wherein I ioyed in glory great, wherin you triumpth moſt.</l>
               <l>
                  <pb facs="tcp:12052:18"/>Kneele on your knees, knock hard your breſts, ſound forth y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ioyful drome</l>
               <l>Clap loude your handes, ſound Eccho ſay, the golden world is come.</l>
               <l>Reioyce you Iudges may of right, your mirth may now be ſuch,</l>
               <l>As neuer earſt you Iudges had, in England mirth ſo much.</l>
               <l>Here <hi>Cuma</hi> is, here <hi>Sibill</hi> raignes, on <hi>Delphos</hi> ſeat to ſitte,</l>
               <l>Here ſhee like <hi>Phaebus</hi> rules, that can <hi>Gordius</hi> knot vnknitte.</l>
               <l>I liued to nature long ynough, I liued to honor much,</l>
               <l>I liued at wiſh, I died at will, to ſee my country ſuch.</l>
               <l>As neither needes it <hi>Numas</hi> lawes, nor yet <hi>Apollos</hi> ſweard,</l>
               <l>For Mauger Mars, yet Mars ſhalbe of this our Queene afeard.</l>
               <l>O peerleſſe pearle, O Diamond deer, O Queene of Queenes farwell,</l>
               <l>Your royall maieſtie God preſerue in England long to dwell.</l>
               <l>Farwell the <hi>Phaenix</hi> of the world, farwel my ſoueraigne Queene,</l>
               <l>Farwel moſt noble vertuous prince, <hi>Mineruas</hi> mate I weene.</l>
               <l>No Iuel, Gemme, no Gold to giue, no pearles from <hi>Pactolus</hi> lo,</l>
               <l>No Perſian Gaze, no Indian ſtones, no Tagus ſands to ſhow.</l>
               <l>But faith and will to natiue ſoyle a liue and dead I find,</l>
               <l>My hart my mind, my loue I leaue vnto my prince behind.</l>
               <l>Farwel you nobles of this land, farwel you Iudges graue,</l>
               <l>Farwel my felowes, frends and mates, your Queene I ſay God ſaue.</l>
               <l>What riſe in time, in time doth, fal, what floweth in time doth ebbe,</l>
               <l>What liues in time, in time ſhall dye, and yeelde to <hi>Parcas</hi> webbe.</l>
               <l>The ſunne to darknes ſhalbe turnd, the ſtarres from ſkies ſhall fall.</l>
               <l>The Moone to blood, the world with fire ſhalbe conſumed all.</l>
               <l>As ſmoke or vapour vaniſh ſtreight, as bubbles riſe and fall.</l>
               <l>As clowdes do paſſe or ſhadow ſhiftes we liue, we dye ſo all.</l>
               <l>Our pompe our pride, our triump moſte, our glory great herein,</l>
               <l>Like ſhattering ſhadow paſſe away, as though none ſuch had bin.</l>
               <l>Earth, water, ayre, and fire, as they were earſt before,</l>
               <l>A lumpe confuſed, and <hi>Chaos</hi> calld, ſo ſhall they once be more,</l>
               <l>And all to earth, that came from earth, and to the graue deſcend,</l>
               <l>For earth on earth, to earth ſhall goe, and earth ſhall be the end.</l>
               <l>As Chriſt aſcended vp in clowdes, ſo Chriſt in clowdes ſhall come,</l>
               <l>To iudge both good and bad on earth, at dreadful day of dome.</l>
               <l>From whence our fleſh ſhall riſe again, euen from the droſſy duſt,</l>
               <l>And ſo ſhall paſſe I hope, vnto the manſion of the iuſt.</l>
               <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
               <closer>
                  <signed>Lodowick LLoyd.</signed>
               </closer>
            </div>
            <div n="33" type="poem">
               <pb n="15" facs="tcp:12052:18" rendition="simple:additions"/>
               <head>
                  <hi>33.</hi> His good name being blemiſhed, he bewayleth.</head>
               <lg>
                  <l>FRamd in the front of forlorne hope, paſt all recouery.</l>
                  <l>I ſtayles ſtand tab ide the ſhocke of ſhame and infamy.</l>
                  <l>My life through lingring long is lodge, in lare of lothſome wayes.</l>
                  <l>My death delayd to keepe from life, the harme of hapleſſe dayes:</l>
                  <l>My ſprites, my hart, my witte and force, in deepe deſtreſſe are dround,</l>
                  <l>The onely loſſe of my good name, is of theſe greefes the ground.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>And ſince my mind, my wit, my head, my voyce, and tongue are weake:</l>
                  <l>To vtter, mooue, deuiſe, conceaue, ſound forth, declare, and ſpeake:</l>
                  <l>Such pearſing plaintes, as aunſwere might, or would my wofull caſe,</l>
                  <l>Helpe craue I muſt, and craue I will, with teares vpon my face:</l>
                  <l>Of all that may in heauen or hell, in earth or ayre be found,</l>
                  <l>To waile with me this loſſe of mine, as of theſe greefes the ground.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>Helpe gods, helpe ſaintes, helpe ſprits &amp; powers, y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> in y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> heauen do dwell,</l>
                  <l>Helpe ye the are to waile aye woont, ye howling houndes of hell:</l>
                  <l>Helpe man, helpe beaſts, helpe birds, &amp; wormes, that on y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> earth doth toile</l>
                  <l>Helpe fiſhe, helpe foule, that flockes and feedes vpon the ſalt ſea ſoyle.</l>
                  <l>Helpe eccho that in ayre doth flee, ſhril voyces to reſound,</l>
                  <l>To waile this loſſe of my good name, as of theſe greefes the ground.</l>
               </lg>
               <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
               <closer>
                  <signed>E. O.</signed>
               </closer>
            </div>
            <div n="34" type="poem">
               <head>
                  <hi>34.</hi> Of Fortunes power.</head>
               <lg>
                  <l>
                     <hi>POlicrates</hi> whoſe paſſing hap, cauſd him to loſe his fate,</l>
                  <l>A golden ring caſt in the ſeas to change his conſtant ſtate,</l>
                  <l>And in a fiſh yet at his bourd, the ſame he after found,</l>
                  <l>Thus Fortune loe, to whom ſhe takes, for bountie doth abound.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>The myzers vnto might ſhe mounts, a common caſe we ſee,</l>
                  <l>And mighty to great miſery, ſhe ſets in low degree:</l>
                  <l>Whom ſhe to day doth reare on hie, vpon her whirling wheele,</l>
                  <l>To morrow next ſhee dingeth downe, and caſteth at her heele.</l>
                  <l>
                     <pb facs="tcp:12052:19" rendition="simple:additions"/>No meaſure hath ſhee in her gifts, ſhee doth reward each ſort.</l>
                  <l>The wiſe that counſell haue, no more, then fooles that maketh ſport.</l>
                  <l>She vſeth neuer partiall handes, for to offend or pleaſe,</l>
                  <l>Geue me good Fortune al men ſayes, and throw me in the ſeas.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>It is no fault or worthines, that makes men fall or riſe,</l>
                  <l>I rather be borne Fortunate, then to be very wiſe.</l>
                  <l>The blindeſt man right ſoone, that by good Fortune guided is,</l>
                  <l>To whom that pleaſant Fortune pipes, can neuer daunce amis.</l>
               </lg>
               <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
               <closer>
                  <signed>M. Edwardes.</signed>
               </closer>
            </div>
            <div n="36" type="poem">
               <head>36.
<l>Though Triumpth after bloudy wars, the greates brags do beare.</l>
                  <l>Yet Triumph of a conquered mind, the crowne of fame ſhall weare.</l>
               </head>
               <lg>
                  <l>WHo ſo doth marke the careleſſe life, of theſe vnhappy dayes,</l>
                  <l>And ſees what ſmal and ſlender hold, the ſtate of vertue ſtayes,</l>
                  <l>He findes, that this accurſed trade, proceedeth of this ill,</l>
                  <l>That men be giuen too much to yeeld, to their vntamed will,</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>In lacke of taming witleſſe wil, the poore we often ſee,</l>
                  <l>Enuies the rich, becauſe that he, his equal cannot be:</l>
                  <l>The rich aduauncd to might by wealth, from wrong doth not refraine,</l>
                  <l>But will oppreſſeth weaker ſort, to heape exceſſiue gaine.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>If Fortune were ſo blind to giue to one man what he wil,</l>
                  <l>A world would not ſuffice the ſame, if he might haue his fill:</l>
                  <l>We wiſh, we ſearch, we ſtriue for all, and haue no more therein,</l>
                  <l>Then hath the ſlaue, when deth doth come, though <hi>Creſus</hi> welch he win.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>In getting much, we get but care, ſuch brittle wealth to keepe,</l>
                  <l>The rich within his walles of ſtone, doth neuer ſoundly ſleepe:</l>
                  <l>When poore in weake and ſlender houſe, do feare no loſſe of wealth,</l>
                  <l>And haue no further care but this, to keepe themſelues in health.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>Affection may not hide the ſword of ſway in iudgement ſeate,</l>
                  <l>Leaſt partiall fauor execute, the law in cauſes greate:</l>
                  <l>
                     <pb n="16" facs="tcp:12052:19" rendition="simple:additions"/>But if the mind in conſtant ſtate, affection quite do leaue,</l>
                  <l>The higher ſtate ſhall haue their rights, the poore no wrong receaue.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>It is accompted greater prayſe to <hi>Caeſers</hi> loftie ſtate,</l>
                  <l>Againſt his vanquiſt foes, in warres to bridle wrekeful hate:</l>
                  <l>Then when to <hi>Rome</hi> he had ſubdued the people long vnknowne,</l>
                  <l>Whereby as farre as land was found, the ſame abrode was blowne.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>If honor can ſelfe will refuſe, and iuſtice be vpright.</l>
                  <l>And priuate ſtate deſires but that, which good appeares in ſight:</l>
                  <l>Then vertue ſhall with ſoueraigne ſhow, to euery eye reueale,</l>
                  <l>A heauenly life, a wealeful ſtate, a happy common weale.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>Let vertue then the triumph win, and gouern all your deedes,</l>
                  <l>Your yeelding to her ſober heaſtes, immortall glory breedes:</l>
                  <l>Shee ſhall vpreare your worthy name, ſhining into the ſkies,</l>
                  <l>Her beames ſhall blaze in graue obſcure, where ſhrined carkaſſe lyes.</l>
               </lg>
               <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
               <closer>
                  <signed>M. Edwards.</signed>
               </closer>
            </div>
            <div n="37" type="poem">
               <head>
                  <hi>37.</hi> Of perfect wiſedome.</head>
               <lg>
                  <l>WHo ſo wil be accompted wiſe, and truely claime the ſame,</l>
                  <l>By ioyning vertue to his deedes, he muſt atchieue the ſame:</l>
                  <l>But few there be, that ſeeke thereby true wiſedome to attaine,</l>
                  <l>O God ſo rule our harts therfore, ſuch fondneſſe to refraine.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>The wiſedome which we moſt eſteeme, in this thing doth conſiſt,</l>
                  <l>With glorious talke to ſhew in words, our wiſedome when we liſt.</l>
                  <l>Yet not in talke, but ſeemely deedes, our wiſedome we ſhould plaſe,</l>
                  <l>To ſpeake ſo faire, and doe but ill, doth wiſedome quite diſgrace,</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>To bargaine well, and ſhunne the loſſe, a wiſedome counted is,</l>
                  <l>And thereby through the greedy coyne, no hope of grace to mis:</l>
                  <l>To ſeeke by honor to aduaunce his name to brittle prayſe,</l>
                  <l>Is wiſedome, which we dayly ſee, increaſeth in our dayes.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <pb facs="tcp:12052:20" rendition="simple:additions"/>
                  <l>But heauenly wiſedome ſower ſeemes to hard for them to win,</l>
                  <l>And weary of the ſute they ſeeme, when they do once begin:</l>
                  <l>It teacheth vs to frame our life, while vitall breath we haue,</l>
                  <l>When it diſſolueth earthly maſſe, the ſoule from death to ſaue.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>By feare of God to rule our ſteppes, from ſliding into vice,</l>
                  <l>A wiſedome is, which we neglect, although of greater price:</l>
                  <l>A poynt of wiſedome alſo this, we commonly eſteeme,</l>
                  <l>That euery man ſhould be in deede, that he deſires to ſeeme.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>To bridle that deſire of gaine, which forceth vs to ill,</l>
                  <l>Our hauty ſtomackes Lord repreſſe, to tame preſuming will:</l>
                  <l>This is the wiſedome that we ſhould, aboue each thing deſire,</l>
                  <l>O heauenly God from ſacred throne, that grace in vs inſpire.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>And print in our repugnant harts, the rules of wiſedome true,</l>
                  <l>That all our deedes in worldly life, may like therof inſue:</l>
                  <l>Thou onely art the liuing ſpring, from whome this wiſedome flowes,</l>
                  <l>O waſh therwith our ſinful harts, from vice that therin growes.</l>
               </lg>
               <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
               <closer>
                  <signed>M. Edwardes:</signed>
               </closer>
            </div>
            <div n="38" type="poem">
               <head>
                  <hi>38.</hi> A freendly admonition.</head>
               <lg>
                  <l>YE ſtately wightes, that liue in quiet reſt,</l>
                  <l>Through worldly wealth, which God hath giuen you.</l>
                  <l>Lament with teares and ſighes from doleful breſt:</l>
                  <l>The ſhame and power that vice obtaineth now.</l>
                  <l>Behold how God doth dayly profer grace,</l>
                  <l>Yet we diſdayne repentance to embrace.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>The ſuddes of ſinne do ſoke into the mind,</l>
                  <l>And cancred vice doth vertue quite expel:</l>
                  <l>No change to good alas can reſting finde,</l>
                  <l>Our wicked harts ſo ſtoutly do rebel.</l>
                  <l>Not one there is that haſteth to amend,</l>
                  <l>Though God from heauen his dayly threates downe ſend.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <pb n="17" facs="tcp:12052:20" rendition="simple:additions"/>
                  <l>We are ſo ſlow to change our blameful life,</l>
                  <l>We are ſo preſt to ſnach aluring vice:</l>
                  <l>Such greedy harts on euery ſide be rife,</l>
                  <l>So few that guide their will by counſel wiſe,</l>
                  <l>To let our teares lament the wretched caſe,</l>
                  <l>And call to God for vndeſerued grace.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>You worldy wightes, that haue your fancies fixt,</l>
                  <l>On ſlipper ioy of terreine pleaſure here:</l>
                  <l>Let ſome remorſe in all your deedes be mixt,</l>
                  <l>Whiles you haue time let ſome redreſſe appeare.</l>
                  <l>Of ſodaine death the houre you ſhall not know,</l>
                  <l>And looke for Death although he ſeemeth ſlow.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>Oh be no iudge in other mens offence,</l>
                  <l>But purge thy ſelfe and ſeeke to make thee free,</l>
                  <l>Let euery one apply his diligence,</l>
                  <l>A change to good within him ſelfe to ſee.</l>
                  <l>O God direct our feete in ſuch a ſtay,</l>
                  <l>From cancred vice to ſhun the hateful way.</l>
               </lg>
               <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
               <closer>
                  <signed>R. Hill.</signed>
               </closer>
            </div>
            <div n="39" type="poem">
               <head>
                  <hi>39.</hi> Sundry men ſundry affectes.</head>
               <lg>
                  <l>JN euery wight ſome ſundry ſort of pleaſure I do find,</l>
                  <l>Which after trauaile he doth ſeeke to eaſe his toyling minn.</l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Diana</hi> with her trayning chaſe, of hunting had delight,</l>
                  <l>Againſt the fearful Deare, ſhe could direct her ſhotte aright.</l>
                  <l>The lofty yeeres in euery age, doth ſtil embrace the ſame,</l>
                  <l>The ſport is good, if vertue doo aſſiſt the cheereful game.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Minerua</hi> in her chattering armes her courage doth aduaunce,</l>
                  <l>In trial of the bloudy wars, ſhe giueth luckie chaunce.</l>
                  <l>For ſauegard men imbrace the ſame, which do ſo needful ſeeme</l>
                  <l>That noble harts their cheefe delightes in vſe thereof eſteeme,</l>
                  <l>In warlike games to ride or trye the force of armes they vſe,</l>
                  <l>And baſe the man we do account that doth the ſame refuſe.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <pb facs="tcp:12052:21" rendition="simple:additions"/>
                  <l>The ſiluer ſound of muſickes cordes, doth pleaſe <hi>Apollos</hi> wit,</l>
                  <l>A ſcience which the heauens aduaunce, where it deſerues to ſit,</l>
                  <l>A pleaſure apt for euery wight, celeefe to careful mind,</l>
                  <l>For woe redreſſe, for care a ſalue, for ſadnes helpe we find.</l>
                  <l>The ſoueraigne praiſe of Muſicke ſtil, doth cauſe the Poets faine.</l>
                  <l>That whirling Spheres, and eake the heauens do hermonie retaine.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>I hard, that theſe three powers, at variance lateli fel,</l>
                  <l>Whiles each did prayſe his owne delight, the other to excel.</l>
                  <l>Then Fame, as an indifferent iudge, to end the caſe they call,</l>
                  <l>The praiſe pronounced by her to them, indifferently doth fall.</l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Diana</hi> health and ſtrength maintaine, <hi>Minerua</hi> force doth tame,</l>
                  <l>And Muſicke giues a ſweete delight, to further others game.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>Theſe three delightes to hawtie mindes the worthieſt are eſtemed,</l>
                  <l>If vertue be annexed to them, they rightly be ſo deemed.</l>
                  <l>With ioy they do reuiue the witte with ſorow oft oppreſt,</l>
                  <l>And neuer ſuffer ſolempne greefe to long in mind to reſt.</l>
                  <l>Be wiſe in mirth, and ſeeke delight, the ſame doe not abuſe,</l>
                  <l>In honeſt mirth a happy ioy we ought not to refuſe.</l>
               </lg>
               <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
               <closer>
                  <signed>R. Hill.</signed>
               </closer>
            </div>
            <div n="40" type="poem">
               <head>
                  <hi>40.</hi> Of a Freend and a Flatterer.</head>
               <lg>
                  <l>
                     <hi>A</hi> Truſtie frend is rare to find, a fawning foe may ſone be got:</l>
                  <l>A faithful frend bere ſtil in mind, but fawning foe regard thou not</l>
                  <l>A faithful freend no cloke doth craue, to colour knauery withal:</l>
                  <l>But <hi>Sicophant</hi> a Goun muſt haue, to beare a port what ere befal.</l>
                  <l>A noſe to ſmel out euery feaſt, a braſen face to ſet it out:</l>
                  <l>A ſhamles child or homly geaſt, whoſe life doth like to range about.</l>
                  <l>A fauning foe while wealth doth laſt, a thefe to rob and ſpoile his freend:</l>
                  <l>As ſtrong as oke til wealth doth laſt, but rotten ſticke doth proue in the end</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Looke first, then leape, beware the mire:</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Burnt Child is warnd to dread the fire.</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Take heede my freend, remember this.</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Short horſe (they ſay) ſoone curried is.</hi>
                  </l>
               </lg>
               <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
               <closer>
                  <signed>M. Edwardes.</signed>
               </closer>
            </div>
            <div n="41" type="poem">
               <pb n="18" facs="tcp:12052:21" rendition="simple:additions"/>
               <head>
                  <hi>41.</hi> Of ſufferaunce commeth eaſe.</head>
               <lg>
                  <l>TO ſeeme for to reuenge each wrong in haſty wiſe,</l>
                  <l>By proofe of guiltleſſe men, it hath not bene the guiſe.</l>
                  <l>In ſlaunders lothſome brute, where they condemned be,</l>
                  <l>With rageleſſe moode they ſuffer wrong, where truth ſhal try them free.</l>
                  <l>Theſe are the pacient pagnes, that paſſe within the breſt,</l>
                  <l>Of thoſe, that feele their cauſe by mine, where wrong hath right oppreſt.</l>
                  <l>I know how by ſuſpect, I haue bene iudgd awry,</l>
                  <l>And graunted gilty in the thing, that clerely I deny.</l>
                  <l>My faith may me defend, if I might loued be,</l>
                  <l>God iudge me ſo, as from the guilt I know me to be free.</l>
                  <l>I wrote but for my ſelfe, the griefe was all mine owne,</l>
                  <l>As, who would proue extremitie, by proofe it might be knowne.</l>
                  <l>Yet are there ſuch, that ſay they can my meaning deeme,</l>
                  <l>Without reſpect of this olde troth, things proue not as they ſeeme.</l>
                  <l>Whereby it may befall, in iudgement to be quicke,</l>
                  <l>To make them ſelues ſuſpect therewith, that needed not to kicke.</l>
                  <l>Yet in reſiſting wrong, I would not haue it thought,</l>
                  <l>I do amiſſe, as though I knew by whom it might be wrought.</l>
                  <l>If any ſuch there be, that herewithall be vext,</l>
                  <l>It were their vertue to beware, and deeme me better next.</l>
               </lg>
               <closer>
                  <signed>L. Vaux.</signed>
               </closer>
            </div>
            <div n="43" type="poem">
               <head>
                  <hi>43.</hi> All thinges are Vaine:</head>
               <l>ALthough the purple morning, bragges in brightnes of the ſunne,</l>
               <l>As though he had of chaſed night, a glorious conqueſt wonne:</l>
               <l>The time by day, giues place againe to force of drowſie night,</l>
               <l>And euery creature is conſtraind to change his luſty plight.</l>
               <l>Of pleaſures all, that here we taſte:</l>
               <l>We feele the contrary at laſte.</l>
               <l>In ſpring, though pleaſant <hi>Zephirus,</hi> hath fruteful earth inſpired,</l>
               <l>And nature hath each buſh, each branch, with bloſſomes braue attired:</l>
               <l>Yet fruites and flowers, as buds and blomes ful quickly withered be,</l>
               <l>When ſtormie winter comes to kill, the ſommers iolitie.</l>
               <l>By time are got, by time are loſt,</l>
               <l>All thinges wherin we pleaſure moſt.</l>
               <l>
                  <pb facs="tcp:12052:22" rendition="simple:additions"/>Although the Seas ſo calmely glide, as daungers none appeare,</l>
               <l>And dout of ſtormes, in ſkie is none, king <hi>Phaebus</hi> ſhines ſo cleare:</l>
               <l>Yet when the boiſtrous windes breake out, and raging waues do ſwel,</l>
               <l>The ſeely barke now heaues to heauen, now ſinckes againe to hel.</l>
               <l>Thus change in euery thing we ſee,</l>
               <l>And nothing conſtant ſeemes to be.</l>
               <l>Who floweth moſt in worldly wealth of welth is moſt vnſure,</l>
               <l>And he that cheefely taſtes of ioy, doth ſometime woe endure:</l>
               <l>Who vaunteth moſt of numbred freendes, forgoe them al he muſt,</l>
               <l>The faireſt fleſh and liueleſt bloud, is turnd at length to duſt.</l>
               <l>Experience giues a certen ground,</l>
               <l>That certen here, is nothing found.</l>
               <l>Then truſt to that which aye remaines, the bliſſe of heauens aboue,</l>
               <l>Which Time, nor Fate, nor Wind, nor Storme, is able to remoue,</l>
               <l>Truſt to that ſure celeſtial rocke, that reſtes in glorious throne,</l>
               <l>That hath bene, is, and muſt be ſtil, our anker hold alone.</l>
               <l>The world is but a vanitie,</l>
               <l>In heauen ſeeke we our ſuretie.</l>
               <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
               <closer>
                  <signed>F. K.</signed>
               </closer>
            </div>
            <div n="44" type="poem">
               <head>
                  <hi>44.</hi> A Vertuous Gentlewoman in the praiſe of hir loue.</head>
               <lg>
                  <l>
                     <hi>J</hi> Am a Virgin faire and free, and freely doe reioyce,</l>
                  <l>I ſweetely warble ſugred notes, from ſiluer voyce:</l>
                  <l>For which delightful ioyes, yet thanke I curteſie loue,</l>
                  <l>By whoſe almighty power, ſuch ſweete delightes I proue.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>I walke the pleaſant fieldes, adornd with liuely greene,</l>
                  <l>And view the fragrant flowers, moſt louely to be ſeene:</l>
                  <l>The purple Columbine, the Couſlippe and the Lillie,</l>
                  <l>The Violet ſweete, the Daizie and Daffadillie.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>The Wodbines on the hedge, the red Roſe and the white,</l>
                  <l>And each fine flowres els, that rendreth ſweete delight:</l>
                  <l>Among the which I chooſe, al thoſe of ſeemelieſt grace,</l>
                  <l>In thought, reſembling them to my deare louers face.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <pb n="19" facs="tcp:12052:22" rendition="simple:additions"/>
                  <l>His louely face I meane, whoſe golden flouring giftes,</l>
                  <l>His euer liuing Fame, to loftye ſkie vpliftes:</l>
                  <l>Whom louing me I loue, onely for vertues ſake,</l>
                  <l>When vertuouſly to loue, al onely care I take.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>Of al which freſh faire flowers, that flower that doth appeare,</l>
                  <l>In my conceit moſt like to him I hold ſo deare:</l>
                  <l>I gather it, I kiſſe it, and eake deuiſe with it,</l>
                  <l>Such kind of louely ſpeach, as is for louers fit.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>And then of all my flowres, I make a garlond fine,</l>
                  <l>With which my golden wyer heares, togither I do twine:</l>
                  <l>And ſette it on my head, ſo taking that delight,</l>
                  <l>That I would take, had I my louer ſtil in ſight.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>For as in goodly flowres, mine eyes great pleaſure find,</l>
                  <l>So are my louers giftes moſt pleaſant to my mind:</l>
                  <l>Vpon which vertuous giftes, I make more ſweete repaſt,</l>
                  <l>Then they that for loue ſportes, the ſweeteſt ioyes do taſt.</l>
               </lg>
               <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
               <closer>
                  <signed>F. K.</signed>
               </closer>
            </div>
            <div n="45" type="poem">
               <head>
                  <hi>45.</hi> Oppreſſed with ſorow he wiſheth death.</head>
               <lg>
                  <l>JF Fortune may enforce, the careful hart to cry</l>
                  <l>And griping griefe conſtraine, the wounded wight lament:</l>
                  <l>Who then alas to mourne, hath greater cauſe then I,</l>
                  <l>Againſt whoſe hard miſhap, both Heauen and earth is bent.</l>
                  <l>For whom no helpe remaines, for whom no hope is left,</l>
                  <l>From whom all happy happ is fled, and pleaſure quite bereft.</l>
                  <l>Whoſe life nought can prolong, whoſe health, nought can procure.</l>
                  <l>Whoſe paſſed proofe of pleaſant ioy,</l>
                  <l>Miſchaunce hath chaunged to greefes anoy:</l>
                  <l>And loe, whoſe hope of better day,</l>
                  <l>Is ouer whelmd with long delay.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>Oh hard miſhap.</l>
                  <l>
                     <pb facs="tcp:12052:23" rendition="simple:additions"/>Each thing I plainly ſee, whoſe vertues may auaile,</l>
                  <l>To eaſe the pinching paine, which gripes the groning wyght:</l>
                  <l>By Phiſicks ſacred ſkill, whoſe rule doth ſeldome fayle,</l>
                  <l>Through labours long inſpect, is playnly brought to light.</l>
                  <l>I know, there is no fruite, no leafe, no roote, no rind,</l>
                  <l>No hearbe, no plant, no iuyce, no gumme, no metal deepely mind:</l>
                  <l>No Pearle, no precious ſtone, ne Ieme of rare effect,</l>
                  <l>Whoſe vertues, learned <hi>Gallens</hi> bookes, at large do not detect.</l>
                  <l>Yet al their force can not appeaſe,</l>
                  <l>The furious fittes of my diſeaſe:</l>
                  <l>Nor any drugge of phiſickes art,</l>
                  <l>Can eaſe the greefe that gripes my hart.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>Oh ſtrange diſeaſe.</l>
                  <l>I heare the wiſe affirme, that Nature hath in ſtore,</l>
                  <l>A thouſand ſecrete ſalues, which Wiſedome hath out found:</l>
                  <l>To coole the ſcorching heate of euery ſmarting ſore,</l>
                  <l>And healeth deepeſt ſcarce, though greeuous be the wound.</l>
                  <l>The auncient prouerbe ſayes, that none ſo feſtred greefe,</l>
                  <l>Doth grow, for which the gods them ſelues, haue not ordayned releefe.</l>
                  <l>But I by proofe do know, ſuch prouerbs to be vaine,</l>
                  <l>And thinke that nature neuer knew the plague that I ſuſtaine.</l>
                  <l>And ſo not knowing my diſtreſſe,</l>
                  <l>Hath left my greefe remedileſſe:</l>
                  <l>For why, the heauens for me prepare,</l>
                  <l>To liue in thought, and dye in care.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>Oh laſting paine.</l>
                  <l>By chaunge of ayre I ſee, by hant of healthful ſoyle,</l>
                  <l>By dyet duely kept, groſe humors are expeld:</l>
                  <l>I know that greefes of mind, and inwards harts turmoile,</l>
                  <l>By faithful freendes aduiſe, in time may be repeld.</l>
                  <l>Yet al this nought auailes, to kil that me anoyes,</l>
                  <l>I meane to ſtop theſe flouds of care that ouerflow my ioyes.</l>
                  <l>No none exchange of place, can change my luckleſſe lot,</l>
                  <l>Like one I liue, and ſo muſt dye, whom Fortune hath forgot.</l>
                  <l>No counſel can preuaile with mee,</l>
                  <l>Nor ſage aduiſe with greefe agree:</l>
                  <l>
                     <pb n="20" facs="tcp:12052:23" rendition="simple:additions"/>For he that feeles the panges of hel,</l>
                  <l>Can neuer hope in heauen to dwel.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>Oh deepe deſpaire.</l>
                  <l>What liues on earth but I, whoſe trauaile reapes no gaine,</l>
                  <l>The wearied Horſe and Oxe, in ſtal and ſtable reſt:</l>
                  <l>The Ante with ſommers toyle beares out the winters paigne,</l>
                  <l>The fowle that flyes al day, at night returnes to reſt.</l>
                  <l>The Ploughmans weary worke, amid the winters mire,</l>
                  <l>Rewarded is with ſommers gaine, which yeeldes him double hire:</l>
                  <l>The ſilly laboring ſoule, which drudges from day to day,</l>
                  <l>At night his wages truely payd, contented goth his way.</l>
                  <l>And comming home, his drowſie head,</l>
                  <l>He cowcheth cloſe in homely bed:</l>
                  <l>Wherein no ſooner downe he lyes,</l>
                  <l>But ſleepe hath ſtraight poſſeſt his eyes,</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>Oh happy man.</l>
                  <l>The Souldier biding long the brunt of mortall warres,</l>
                  <l>Where life is neuer free, from dint of deadly foyle:</l>
                  <l>At laſt comes ioyful home, though mangled all with ſcarres,</l>
                  <l>Where frankly, voyde of feare, he ſpends the gotten ſpoyle.</l>
                  <l>The Pirate lying long, amid the fooming floods,</l>
                  <l>With euery flaw in hazard is to looſe both life and goods:</l>
                  <l>At length findes view of land, where wiſhed Porte he ſpies,</l>
                  <l>Which once obtained, among his mates, he partes the gotten priſe,</l>
                  <l>Thus euery man, for trauaile paſt,</l>
                  <l>Doth reape a iuſt reward at laſt:</l>
                  <l>But I alone, whoſe troubled mind,</l>
                  <l>In ſeeking reſt, vnreſt doth find.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>Oh luckleſſe lotte.</l>
                  <l>Oh curſed caitife wretch, whoſe heauy hard miſhappe,</l>
                  <l>Doth wiſh tenne thouſand times, that thou hadſt not ben borne:</l>
                  <l>Since fate hath thee condemned, to liue in ſorrowes lappe,</l>
                  <l>Where waylings waſte thy life, of all redreſſe forlorne.</l>
                  <l>What ſhal thy griefe appeaſe? who ſhal thy torment ſtay?</l>
                  <l>Wilt thou thy ſelfe, with murthering hands, enforce thy owndecay?</l>
                  <l>No, farre be thou from me, my ſelfe to ſtoppe my breath,</l>
                  <l>The gods forbid, whom I beſeech, to worke my ioyes by death.</l>
                  <l>
                     <pb facs="tcp:12052:24" rendition="simple:additions"/>For lingring length of lothſome life,</l>
                  <l>Doth ſtirre in me ſuch mortal ſtrife:</l>
                  <l>That whiles for life and death I cry,</l>
                  <l>In death I liue, and liuing dye.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>Oh froward fate.</l>
                  <l>Loe here my hard miſhap, loe here my ſtrange diſeaſe,</l>
                  <l>Loe here my deepe deſpaire, loe here my laſting paine:</l>
                  <l>Loe here my froward fate, which nothing can appeaſe,</l>
                  <l>Loe here how others toyle, rewarded is with gaine.</l>
                  <l>While luckleſſe, loe I liue, in loſſe of labours due,</l>
                  <l>Compeld by proofe of torment ſtrong, my endleſſe greefe to rue:</l>
                  <l>In which, ſince needes I muſt, conſume both youth and age,</l>
                  <l>If olde I liue, and that my care no comfort can aſſwage.</l>
                  <l>Henceforth I baniſhe from my breſt,</l>
                  <l>All fruſtrate hope of future reſt,</l>
                  <l>And trthleſſe truſt to times reward,</l>
                  <l>With al reſpects of ioyes regard.</l>
                  <l>Here I forſweare.</l>
               </lg>
            </div>
            <div n="47" type="poem">
               <head>47.
<l>Where reaſon makes request, ther wiſedome ought ſupply</l>
                  <l>With freendly aunſwere prest, to grant or els deny.</l>
               </head>
               <lg>
                  <l>
                     <hi>I</hi> Sigh, why ſo? for ſorrowe of her ſmart.</l>
                  <l>I morne, wherfore? or greefe that ſhe complaynes:</l>
                  <l>I pitie, what? her oppreſſed hart,</l>
                  <l>I dread what harme? the danger ſhe ſuſtaines.</l>
                  <l>I greeue whereat? at her oppreſſing paines.</l>
                  <l>I feele, what force the fittes of her diſeaſe,</l>
                  <l>Whoſe harme doth me and her, alike diſpleaſe.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>I hope, what happe? her happy healthes retyre,</l>
                  <l>I wiſh, what wealth? no wealth, nor worldly ſtore:</l>
                  <l>But craue, what craft? by cunning to aſpire,</l>
                  <l>Some ſkil, whereto? to ſalue her ſickly ſore.</l>
                  <l>What then? why then would I her health reſtore,</l>
                  <l>Whoſe harme me hurtes, how ſo? ſo workes my will,</l>
                  <l>To wiſh my ſelfe and her, like good and yll.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <pb n="21" facs="tcp:12052:24" rendition="simple:additions"/>
                  <l>What moues thy mind, whereto? to ſuch deſire,</l>
                  <l>Ne force, ne fauour, what then? free fancies choyſe:</l>
                  <l>Art thou to choſe? my charter to require,</l>
                  <l>Each Ladyes loue is fred by cuſtumes voyce,</l>
                  <l>Yet are there grauntes, the euidence of their choyſe.</l>
                  <l>What then, our freedome is at large in chooſing,</l>
                  <l>As Womens wils is froward in refuſing.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>Wotes ſhee thy wil? ſhe knowes what I proteſt,</l>
                  <l>Daynde ſhe thy ſute? ſhe daungerd not my talke:</l>
                  <l>Gaue ſhe conſent? ſhe graunted my requeſt,</l>
                  <l>What didſt thou craue? the roote, the fruite, the ſtalke,</l>
                  <l>I aſked them all, what gaue ſhee, Cheeſe, or chalke?</l>
                  <l>That taſt muſt try, what taſt? I meane the proofe,</l>
                  <l>Of freendes, whoſe wils withhold ther bowe aloofe.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>Meanſt thou good faith? what els, hopeſt thou to ſpeede?</l>
                  <l>Why not, O foole vntaught in carpel trade,</l>
                  <l>Knoweſt not what proofes from ſuch delayes proceede,</l>
                  <l>Wilt thou like headleſſe Cocke be caught in glade?</l>
                  <l>Art thou like aſſe, too apt for burden made?</l>
                  <l>Fy, fy, wilt thou for ſaint adore the ſhrine?</l>
                  <l>And woo her freend, eare ſhe be wholy thine?</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>Who drewes this drift? moued ſhe, or thou this match?</l>
                  <l>Twas I: oh foole vnware of womens wyles,</l>
                  <l>Long maiſt thou waite, like hungry hounde at hatch,</l>
                  <l>She crafty Foxe, the ſeely Gooſe beguiles.</l>
                  <l>Thy ſute is ſhaped ſo fit for long delay,</l>
                  <l>That ſhe at wil may chek, from yea to nay.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>But in good ſoothe, tel me her freendes intent:</l>
                  <l>Beſt learne it firſt, their purpoſe I not know,</l>
                  <l>Why then thy wil to worſe and worſe is bent,</l>
                  <l>Doſt thou delight, the vnkindled cole to blow?</l>
                  <l>Or childlike loueſt, in anckred bote to rowe,</l>
                  <l>
                     <pb facs="tcp:12052:25" rendition="simple:additions"/>What meane theſe termes? who ſith thy ſute is ſuch,</l>
                  <l>Know of or on, or thou afect too much.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>No haſte but good, why no, the meane is beſt,</l>
                  <l>Admit ſhe loue, miſlike in lingring growes:</l>
                  <l>Suppoſe ſhe is caught, then Woodcocke on thy creſt,</l>
                  <l>Til end approues, what ſkorneful ſeedes ſhe ſowes.</l>
                  <l>In loytring loue, ſuch daugers ebbes and flowes,</l>
                  <l>What helpe herein? why wake in dangerous watch,</l>
                  <l>That too, nor fro, may make thee marre the match:</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>Is that the way to end my weary worke?</l>
                  <l>By quicke diſpatch, to leſſon long turmoyle,</l>
                  <l>Well wel, though loſſe in lingering wontes to lurke,</l>
                  <l>And I a foole, moſt fitte to take the foyle:</l>
                  <l>Yet proofe from promiſe, neuer ſhall recoyle.</l>
                  <l>My words with deedes, and deedes with wordes ſhall wend,</l>
                  <l>Til ſhee or hers, gainſay that I intend.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>Art thou ſo fond? not fond, but firmely faſt,</l>
                  <l>Why foole her freendes wote how thy wil is bent:</l>
                  <l>Yet thou like doult, whoſe witte and ſence is paſt,</l>
                  <l>Seſt not what frumpes, do follow thy entent.</l>
                  <l>Ne know, how loue in lewe of ſkorne is lent,</l>
                  <l>Adewe, for ſightes ſuch folly ſhould preuent.</l>
                  <l>Wel wel, their ſkoffes with ſcornes might be repayd,</l>
                  <l>If my requeſtes were fully yead or nayd,</l>
                  <l>Wel, wel, let theſe with wiſedomes payſe be wayd,</l>
                  <l>And in your cheſt of cheefeſt ſecreates layd.</l>
               </lg>
               <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
               <epigraph>
                  <q>My lucke is loſſe.</q>
               </epigraph>
            </div>
            <div n="48" type="poem">
               <head>
                  <hi>48.</hi> What ioy to a contented mind.</head>
               <lg>
                  <l>THe faith that fayles, muſt needes bethought vntrue,</l>
                  <l>The freend that faines, who holdeth not vniuſt,</l>
                  <l>Who likes that loue, that changeth ſtil for new:</l>
                  <l>Who hopes for trueth, where troth is voyde of truſt,</l>
                  <l>No faith, no freend, no loue, no troth ſo ſure,</l>
                  <l>But rather failes then ſtedfaſtly endure.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <pb n="22" facs="tcp:12052:25" rendition="simple:additions"/>
                  <l>What head ſo ſtayed? that altereth not intent,</l>
                  <l>What thought ſo ſure? that ſtedfaſt doth remaine,</l>
                  <l>What witte ſo wiſe? that neuer needes repent:</l>
                  <l>What tongue ſo true? but ſometime wonts to faine,</l>
                  <l>What foote ſo firme? that neuer treades awrie.</l>
                  <l>What ſoner dimde? then ſight of cleareſt eye.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>What hart ſo fixt? but ſone enclines to change,</l>
                  <l>What moode ſo milde? that neuer moued debate:</l>
                  <l>What faith ſo ſtrong, but lightly likes to range,</l>
                  <l>What loue ſo true? that neuer lernd to hate.</l>
                  <l>What life ſo pure? that laſts, without offence,</l>
                  <l>What worldly minde? but moues with ill pretence.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>What knot ſo faſt? that may not be vntide,</l>
                  <l>What ſeale ſo ſure? but fraude or force ſhall breake:</l>
                  <l>What prop of ſtay? but one time ſhrinkes aſide,</l>
                  <l>What ſhip ſo ſtauche? that neuer had a leke.</l>
                  <l>What graunt ſo large? that no exception makes,</l>
                  <l>What hoped helpe, but freend at neede forſakes.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>What ſeate ſo high? but low to ground may fall,</l>
                  <l>What hap ſo good? that neuer found miſlike:</l>
                  <l>What ſtate ſo ſure? but ſubiect is to thrall.</l>
                  <l>What force preuailes? where Fortune liſt to ſtrik.</l>
                  <l>What wealth ſo much? but time may turne to want,</l>
                  <l>What ſtore ſo great? but waſting maketh ſkant.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>What profites hope in depth of dangers thrall.</l>
                  <l>What ruſte in time, but waxeth worſe and worſe:</l>
                  <l>What helpes good harte, if Fortune froun withall,</l>
                  <l>What bleſſing thriues, againſt heauenly helples curſe.</l>
                  <l>What winnes deſire to get and can not gayne,</l>
                  <l>What botes to wiſh and neuer to obtaine.</l>
               </lg>
               <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
               <epigraph>
                  <q>My lucke is loſse</q>
               </epigraph>
            </div>
            <div n="47" type="poem">
               <pb facs="tcp:12052:26" rendition="simple:additions"/>
               <head>47.
<q xml:lang="lat">
                     <l>Donec eris Felix multos numerabis amicos.</l>
                     <l>Nullus ad a miſſus ibit amicus opes.</l>
                  </q>
               </head>
               <lg>
                  <l>EVen as the Rauen, the Crow, and greedy Kite,</l>
                  <l>Do ſwarming flocke, where carren corpes doth fall:</l>
                  <l>And tiring teare with beak and talentes might,</l>
                  <l>Both ſkin and fleſh to gorge their guttes withall.</l>
                  <l>And neuer ceaſe, but gather moe to moe,</l>
                  <l>Doe all to pull the carkaſe to and froe,</l>
                  <l>Till bared bones at laſt they leaue behinde,</l>
                  <l>And ſeeke elſewhere ſome fatter foode to find.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>Euen ſo I ſee, where wealth doth waxe at will,</l>
                  <l>And Gold doth grow to heapes of great encreaſe:</l>
                  <l>There freendes reſort, and profering freendſhip ſtill,</l>
                  <l>Ful thicke they throng, with neuer ceaſing preaſe.</l>
                  <l>And ſlilie make a ſhewe of true intent,</l>
                  <l>When nought but guile, and inward hate is ment:</l>
                  <l>For when miſchance ſhall change ſuch wealth to want,</l>
                  <l>They packe them thence to place of richer haunt.</l>
               </lg>
               <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
               <epigraph>
                  <q>My lucke is loſſe.</q>
               </epigraph>
            </div>
            <div n="49" type="poem">
               <head>
                  <hi>49.</hi> Amantium irae amoris redinti graciae est.</head>
               <lg>
                  <l>IN going to my naked bed as one that would haue ſlept,</l>
                  <l>I hard a wife ſing to her child, that long before had wept:</l>
                  <l>She ſighed ſore and ſang ful ſweete, to bring the babe to reſt,</l>
                  <l>That would not ceaſe but cryed ſtil, in ſucking at her breſt.</l>
                  <l>She was full wearie of her watch, and greeued with her child,</l>
                  <l>She rocked it and rated it, til that on her it ſmilde:</l>
                  <l>Then did ſhe ſay now haue I found, this prouerbe true to proue,</l>
                  <l>The falling out of faithfull frends, renuing is of loue.</l>
                  <l>Then tooke I paper, penne and ynke, this prouerbe for to write,</l>
                  <l>In regeſter for to remaine, of ſuch a worthy wight:</l>
                  <l>As ſhe proceeded thus in ſong vnto her little bratt,</l>
                  <l>Much matter vttered ſhe of waight, in place whereas ſh<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>e ſatt.</l>
                  <l>And proued plaine, there was no beaſt, nor creature bearing life,</l>
                  <l>Could well be knowne to liue in loue, without diſcord and ſtrife:</l>
                  <l>
                     <pb n="23" facs="tcp:12052:26" rendition="simple:additions"/>Then kiſſed ſhe her little babe, and ſware by God aboue,</l>
                  <l>The falling out of faithfull frendes, renuing is of loue,</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>She ſayd that neither king ne prince, ne lord could liue aright,</l>
                  <l>Vntil their puiſſaunce the did proue their manhod and their might.</l>
                  <l>When manhode ſhal be matched ſo, that feare can take no place,</l>
                  <l>Then weary workes make warriours, each other to embrace,</l>
                  <l>And leaued their forſe that fayled them, which did conſume the rout,</l>
                  <l>That might before haue liued their time, and nature out:</l>
                  <l>Then did ſhe ſing as one that thought, no man could her reproue,</l>
                  <l>The falling out of faith ful freendes, renuing is of loue.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>She ſayd ſhe ſaw no fiſhe ne foule, nor beaſt within her haunt,</l>
                  <l>That mett a ſtranger in their kind, but could giue it a taunt:</l>
                  <l>Since fleſhe might not endure, but reſt muſt wrath ſuccede,</l>
                  <l>And forſe the fight to fall to play, in paſture where they feede,</l>
                  <l>So noble nature can well ende, the worke ſhe hath begone,</l>
                  <l>And bridle well that will not ceaſe, her tragedy in ſome:</l>
                  <l>Thus in ſong ſhe oft reherſt, as dyd her wel behoue,</l>
                  <l>The falling out of faithful frendes, is the renuing of loue.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>I meruaile much pardy quoth ſhe, for to behold the route,</l>
                  <l>To ſee man, woman, boy &amp; beaſt, to toſſe the world about:</l>
                  <l>Some knele, ſome crouch, ſome beck, ſome chek, &amp; ſome can ſmothly ſmile</l>
                  <l>And ſome embrace others in arme, and there thinke many a wile.</l>
                  <l>Some ſtand aloufe at cap and knee, ſome humble and ſome ſtoute,</l>
                  <l>Yet are they neuer freendes in deede, vntill they once fall out:</l>
                  <l>Thus ended ſhe her ſong, and ſayd before ſhe did remoue,</l>
                  <l>The falling out of faithful freends, is the renuing of loue.</l>
               </lg>
               <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
               <closer>
                  <signed>M. Edwardes.</signed>
               </closer>
            </div>
            <div n="43" type="poem">
               <head>
                  <hi>43.</hi> Thinke to dye.</head>
               <lg>
                  <l>THe life is long, which lothſomly doth laſt,</l>
                  <l>The doleful dayes draw ſlowly to their date:</l>
                  <l>The preſent panges, and painful plages ſorepaſt,</l>
                  <l>Yeldes grefe aye grene, to ſtabliſh this eſtate.</l>
                  <l>
                     <pb facs="tcp:12052:27" rendition="simple:additions"/>So that I feele in this great ſtorme and ſtrife,</l>
                  <l>That death is ſweete, that ſhortneth ſuch a life.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>And by the ſtroke of this ſtrange ouerthrowe,</l>
                  <l>All which conflict in thraldome I was thruſt:</l>
                  <l>The Lord he prayſed, I am well taught to know,</l>
                  <l>From whence man came, and eke whereto he muſt.</l>
                  <l>And by the waye, vpon how feeble force.</l>
                  <l>His terme doth ſtand, till death doth end his courſe.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>The pleaſant yeeres that ſeemes ſo ſweetely ronne,</l>
                  <l>The mery dayes to ende, ſo faſt that flete:</l>
                  <l>The ioyfull wightes, of which dayes drawes ſo ſone,</l>
                  <l>The happy howres which <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                        <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                     </gap> do miſſe then mete.</l>
                  <l>Do all conſume as ſnowe againſt the Sunne,</l>
                  <l>And death makes end of all that life begunne.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>Since death ſhall dure till all the world be waſt,</l>
                  <l>What meaneth man to dreade death then ſo ſore?</l>
                  <l>As man might make, that life ſhould alway laſt,</l>
                  <l>Without regard the Lord hath ledde before.</l>
                  <l>The daunce of death, which all muſt runne on rowe,</l>
                  <l>The hower wherin onely himſelfe doth knowe.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>If man would mind, what burdeins life doth bring,</l>
                  <l>What greeuous crimes to God he doth commit:</l>
                  <l>What plagues, what perill thereby ſpring,</l>
                  <l>With no ſure hower in all his dayes to ſit.</l>
                  <l>He would ſure thinke, as with great cauſe I doe,</l>
                  <l>The day of death is happier of the two.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>Death is the doore whereby we draw to ioy,</l>
                  <l>Life is the lake that drowneth all in payne:</l>
                  <l>Death is ſo dole it ſeaſeth all away,</l>
                  <l>Life is ſo leude, that al it yelds is vayne.</l>
                  <l>And as by life, in bondage man is brought,</l>
                  <l>Euen ſo by death is freedome likewiſe wrought.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <pb n="24" facs="tcp:12052:27" rendition="simple:additions"/>
                  <l>Wherefore with Paule let all men wiſh and pray,</l>
                  <l>To be diſolued of this foule fleſhly maſſe:</l>
                  <l>Or at the leaſt be armd againſt the day,</l>
                  <l>That they be found good ſouldiers preſt to paſſe.</l>
                  <l>From life to death, from death to life againe,</l>
                  <l>And ſuch a life as euer ſhall remaine.</l>
               </lg>
               <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
               <closer>
                  <signed>D. S.</signed>
               </closer>
            </div>
            <div type="acrostic_poem">
               <head>51.
<l>If thou deſire to liue in quiet rest,</l>
                  <l>geue care and ſe but ſay the best.</l>
               </head>
               <lg>
                  <l>
                     <hi>If thou:</hi> delight, in quietnes of life,</l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Deſire:</hi> to ſhoun, from bralls, debate and ſtrife,</l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>To liue:</hi> in loue with god, with frend and foe,</l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>In rest:</hi> ſhalt ſleepe: when others cannot ſo.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Giue eare:</hi> to all, yet doo not all beleeue,</l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>And ſee:</hi> the end, and then do ſentence ge eue:</l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>But ſay:</hi> for truth of happy liues aſſind,</l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>The best:</hi> hath he that quiet is in mind.</l>
               </lg>
               <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
               <closer>
                  <signed>M. Hunnis.</signed>
               </closer>
            </div>
            <div n="52" type="poem">
               <head>
                  <hi>52.</hi> Beeing forſaken of his frend he complaineth.</head>
               <lg>
                  <l>WHy ſhould I lenger long to liue,</l>
                  <l>In this deſeaſe of fantaſie,</l>
                  <l>Sins fortune doth not ceaſe to giue,</l>
                  <l>Thinges to my mind moſt contrarie.</l>
                  <l>And at my ioyes doth lowre and frowne,</l>
                  <l>Till ſhe hath tourned them vpſidowne,</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>A freende I had to me moſt deere,</l>
                  <l>And of long time faithfull and iuſt:</l>
                  <l>There was no one, my hart ſo neere,</l>
                  <l>Nor one in whome I had more truſt.</l>
                  <l>
                     <pb facs="tcp:12052:28" rendition="simple:additions"/>Whom now of late without cauſe why,</l>
                  <l>Fortune hath made my enemy.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>The graſſe me thinkes ſhould grow in ſkie,</l>
                  <l>The ſtarres, vnto the earth cleaue faſte:</l>
                  <l>The water ſtreame ſhould paſſe awrie,</l>
                  <l>The winds ſhould leaue their ſtrength of blaſt.</l>
                  <l>The Sunne and Moone by one aſſent,</l>
                  <l>Should both forſake the firmament.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>The fiſhe in ayre ſhould flye with finne,</l>
                  <l>The foules in floud, ſhould bring forth fry:</l>
                  <l>All thinges methinkes ſhould erſt beginne,</l>
                  <l>To take their courſe vnnaturally.</l>
                  <l>Afore my frend ſhould alter ſo,</l>
                  <l>Without a cauſe to be my foe:</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>But ſuch is Fortunes hate I ſay,</l>
                  <l>Such is his will on me to wreake:</l>
                  <l>Such ſpite he hath at me alway,</l>
                  <l>And ceaſſeth not my hart to breake.</l>
                  <l>With ſuch deſpite of crueltie,</l>
                  <l>Wherefore then longer liue ſhould I.</l>
               </lg>
               <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
               <closer>
                  <signed>E. S.</signed>
               </closer>
            </div>
            <div n="53" type="poem">
               <head>
                  <hi>53.</hi> Prudens. The history of Damacles, &amp; Dioniſe.</head>
               <l>WHo ſo is ſet in princely throne, and craueth rule to beare,</l>
               <l>Is ſtill beſet on euery ſide, with peril and with feare.</l>
               <l>High trees by ſtormy windes are ſhakt, and rent vp from the ground,</l>
               <l>And flaſhy flackes of lightning flames on turrets do rebound.</l>
               <l>When little ſhrubs in ſauetie lurke, in couert all alowe,</l>
               <l>And freſhly floriſh in their kind, what euer wind doe blowe.</l>
               <l>The cruel king of <hi>Sciſili:</hi> who ſearing Barbars hands.</l>
               <l>Was wont to ſings his beard himſelfe, with cole and fire brands.</l>
               <l>Hath taught vs this, the proofe whereof, ful plainly we may ſee,</l>
               <l>
                  <pb n="25" facs="tcp:12052:28" rendition="simple:additions"/>Was neuer thing more liuely touched, to ſhewe it ſo to be.</l>
               <l>This king did ſeeme to <hi>Damacles,</hi> to be the happieſt wight,</l>
               <l>Becauſe he thought none like to him, in power or in might.</l>
               <l>Who did alone ſo farre excell the reſt in his degree,</l>
               <l>As doth the Sunne in brightnes cleare, the darkeſt ſtarre we ſee.</l>
               <l>Wilt thou (then ſayd this cruell king) proue this my preſent ſtate,</l>
               <l>Poſſeſſe thou ſhalt this ſeate of mine, and ſo be fortunate.</l>
               <l>Ful gladly then this <hi>Damacles,</hi> this proferd honour tooke,</l>
               <l>And ſhooting at a princely life, his quiet reſt forſooke.</l>
               <l>In honours ſeat then was he plaſt, according to his will,</l>
               <l>Forthwith a banquet was prepard, that he might feaſt his fill.</l>
               <l>Nothing did want wherin twas thought, that he could take delite,</l>
               <l>To feede his eye, to fill his mouth, or pleaſe the appetite.</l>
               <l>Such ſtore of plate, I thinke in Grece, there ſcarſly was ſo much,</l>
               <l>His ſeruitours did angels ſeeme, their paſſing ſhape was ſuch.</l>
               <l>No daynty diſh but there it was, and thereof was ſuch ſtore,</l>
               <l>That through out Greece ſo princly cheere, was neuer ſeene before.</l>
               <l>Thus while in pompe and pleaſures ſeat, this <hi>Damacles</hi> was plaſt,</l>
               <l>And did begin with gladſome hart, each dainty diſh to taſt.</l>
               <l>At length by chaunce caſt vp his eyes, and gan the houſe to vewe,</l>
               <l>And ſaw a ſight that him enforſt, his princely ſtate to rewe.</l>
               <l>A ſword forſooth with downeward poynt, that had no ſtronger thread,</l>
               <l>Then one horſe heere that peiſed it, direct vpon his head.</l>
               <l>Wherewith he was ſo ſore amaſde, and ſhoke in euery part,</l>
               <l>As though the ſword that hong aboue, had ſtroke him to the hart.</l>
               <l>Then all their pleaſures tooke their leaue, &amp; ſorrow came in place,</l>
               <l>His heauie hart the teares declard, that trickled down his face.</l>
               <l>And then forthwith with ſobbing voyce, beſought the king of grace,</l>
               <l>That he would licence him with ſpeede, to depart out of that place.</l>
               <l>And ſayd that he full long enough, had tried now with feare,</l>
               <l>What tis to be a happy man, and princely rule to beare.</l>
               <l>This deede of thine oh <hi>Dioniſe,</hi> deſerues immortal fame,</l>
               <l>This deede ſhall alwayes liue with prayſe, though thou didſt liue w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> ſhame</l>
               <l>Whereby both kinges be put in mind, their dangers to be great,</l>
               <l>And ſubiects be forbid to clime, high ſteppes of honours ſeat.</l>
               <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
               <closer>
                  <signed>M. Edwardes.</signed>
               </closer>
            </div>
            <div n="48" type="poem">
               <pb facs="tcp:12052:29" rendition="simple:additions"/>
               <head>
                  <hi>48.</hi> Fortitude. A young man of Aegypt, and Valerian.</head>
               <l>EChe one deſerues great prayſe to haue, but yet not like I thinke,</l>
               <l>Both he that can ſuſtaine the yoke of paines, &amp; doth not ſhrinke.</l>
               <l>And he whom <hi>Cupids</hi> couert craft can nothing moue at all,</l>
               <l>Into the hard and tangled knottes of <hi>Venus</hi> ſnares to fall.</l>
               <l>Beſturre you then who ſo delightes in vertues race to ronne,</l>
               <l>The flying boye with bow ibent, by ſtrength to ouer come.</l>
               <l>As one dyd once when he was young, and in his tender dayes,</l>
               <l>Whoſe ſtoute and noble deede of his, hath got immortall prayſe.</l>
               <l>The wicked Romaines did purſue the ſely Chriſtians than,</l>
               <l>What time <hi>Valerian</hi> Emperour was a wicked cruel man.</l>
               <l>Who ſpared not with bloudy draughtes, to quench his owne deſire,</l>
               <l>Diſpatching all that ſtucke to Chriſt with hote conſuming fire.</l>
               <l>At length a man of tender yeeres was brought before his ſight,</l>
               <l>Such one as Nature ſeemed to make a witnes of her migh.</l>
               <l>For euery part ſo well was ſet, that nothing was depraued,</l>
               <l>So that the cruell king himſelfe, would gladly him haue ſaued.</l>
               <l>So loth he was to ſee a worke, ſo rare of Natures power,</l>
               <l>So finely built ſo ſodainly deſtroyed within an howre.</l>
               <l>Then meanes he ſought to ouercome, or win him at the leſt,</l>
               <l>To ſlip from Chriſt whom he before had earneſtly profeſt.</l>
               <l>A bedde preparde, ſo finely dect, ſuch diuers pleaſant ſmels,</l>
               <l>That well it might appeare a place, where pleaſure onely dwels,</l>
               <l>By him he layd a naked wench, a <hi>Venus</hi> darling ſure,</l>
               <l>With ſugred ſpeach &amp; louely toyes, that might his mind allure.</l>
               <l>Such wanton lewres as theſe he thought, might eaſly him entiſe,</l>
               <l>Which thinges he knew with luſtie youth, had alwayes ben in priſe.</l>
               <l>Such wayes I thinke the Gods themſelues, could haue inuented none,</l>
               <l>For flattering <hi>Venus</hi> ouercomes the ſences euery chone,</l>
               <l>And he himſelfe was euen at poynt, to <hi>Venus</hi> to conſent,</l>
               <l>Had not his ſtout and manly mind reſiſted his entent.</l>
               <l>When he perceiued his fleſh to yeeld to pleaſures wanton toyes,</l>
               <l>And was by flight almoſt prouoked, to taſt of <hi>Venus</hi> ioyes.</l>
               <l>More cruel to himſelfe then thoſe, that glad would him vndoo,</l>
               <l>With bloudy toth, his tender tongue, bote quite and cleane in twoo.</l>
               <l>
                  <pb n="39" facs="tcp:12052:29" rendition="simple:additions"/>Thus was the paine ſo paſſyng greate of this his bloudie bite,</l>
               <l>That all the fire and carnall luſte, was quenched euery whitt.</l>
               <l>Doe ill and all thy pleaſures then full ſone will paſſe awaie,</l>
               <l>But yet the ſhame of thoſe thy dedes, will neuermore decaie.</l>
               <l>Doe well and though thy paines be great, yet ſone eche one will ceaſe,</l>
               <l>But yet, the praiſe of thoſe thy deedes will euermore increaſe.</l>
               <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
               <closer>
                  <signed>M. Edwardes.</signed>
               </closer>
            </div>
            <div n="58" type="poem">
               <head>
                  <hi>58.</hi> Iustice. Zaleuch and his Sonne.</head>
               <l>LEt rulers make moſte perfect lawes, to rule bothe greate and ſmal</l>
               <l>If thei them ſelues obeye them not, it boteth not at all.</l>
               <l>As lawes be nought but rulers dome, continyng egall might,</l>
               <l>So rulers ſhould bee ſpeakyng Lawes, to rule by line of right.</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Zaleuch</hi> the Prince of <hi>Locrine</hi> once, appoincted by decree,</l>
               <l>Eche Lecherer ſhould bee puniſhed, with loſſe of either eye.</l>
               <l>His ſonne by chaunce offended firſt, whiche when his father ſawe,</l>
               <l>Lorde God how earneſt then was he, to execute the Lawe.</l>
               <l>Then ranne the people all by flocks, to hym with weepyng eyes,</l>
               <l>Not one emong the route there was, but pardon, pardon cries.</l>
               <l>By whoſe outcries and earneſt ſute, his ſonne in hope did ſtande,</l>
               <l>That he thereby ſhould then obtaine, ſome pardon at his hande.</l>
               <l>But all in vaine, for he is founde to bee the man he was,</l>
               <l>And maketh haſte ſo muche the more, to haue the Lawe to paſſe.</l>
               <l>The people yet renued their ſute, in hope of ſome relief,</l>
               <l>Whoſe faces all beſprent with teares, did teſtifie their grief.</l>
               <l>And cried all for pities ſake, yelde now to our requeſt,</l>
               <l>If all you will not cleane remit, yet eaſe the paine at leaſt.</l>
               <l>Then ſomewhat was the father moued, with all the peoples voyce,</l>
               <l>And euery man did giue a ſhoote, to ſhewe thei did reioyce.</l>
               <l>Well then ꝙ he, it ſhall bee thus, the Lawe ſhall bee fulfilde,</l>
               <l>And yet my ſonne ſhall fauour haue, accordyng as you wilde.</l>
               <l>One eye of his ſhall bee pulde out, thus hath his leudneſſe got,</l>
               <l>And likewiſe ſo ſhall one of myne, though I deſerue it not.</l>
               <l>This worde no ſoner was pronounced, but ſtraite the deede was doen,</l>
               <l>Twoo eyes, no mo were lefte, betwene the father and the ſonne.</l>
               <l>Saie nowe who can, and on my faithe <hi>Apollo</hi> he ſhall bee,</l>
               <l>Was he more gentle father lo? or iuſter Iudge trowe ye.</l>
               <l>This man would not his Lawes belike, the webbs the Spiders weue,</l>
               <l>
                  <pb facs="tcp:12052:30" rendition="simple:additions"/>Wherein thei lurke when thei intende, the ſimple to deceiue.</l>
               <l>Wherewith ſmall flies full ſone be caught, and tangled ere thei wiſte,</l>
               <l>When greate ones flie and ſcape awaie, and breake them as thei liſte.</l>
               <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
               <closer>
                  <signed>M. Edwardes.</signed>
               </closer>
            </div>
            <div n="59" type="poem">
               <head>
                  <hi>59.</hi> Temperaunce. Spurina and the Romaine Ladies.</head>
               <l>IF nature beare thée ſo greate Loue, that ſhe in thee haue beautie plaſt</l>
               <l>Full hard it is as we doe proue, to keepe the bodie cleane and chaſt:</l>
               <l>Twixt comelineſſe and chaſtitie,</l>
               <l>A deadlie ſtrife is thought to be.</l>
               <l>For beautie whiche ſome men ſuppoſe, to be as tware a golden ill,</l>
               <l>Prouoketh ſtrief and many foes, that ſeke on her to worke her will:</l>
               <l>Aſſaults to Tounes if many make,</l>
               <l>No Toune ſo ſtrong but maie be take.</l>
               <l>And this Spurina witneſſe can, who did for beautie beare the bell,</l>
               <l>So cleane a wight ſo comely made, no dame in Rome but loued well</l>
               <l>Not one could coole her hote deſire,</l>
               <l>So burnyng was the flame of fire.</l>
               <l>Like as when baite caſte in the floud, forthw<hi rend="sup">t</hi> doeth cauſe the fiſhes come</l>
               <l>Tha<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> pleaſauntly before did plaie, now preſently to death to runne:</l>
               <l>For when thei ſee the baite to fall,</l>
               <l>Straight waie thei ſwallowe hooke and all.</l>
               <l>So when Spurina thei did ſee, to hym thei flocked out of hande,</l>
               <l>She happeſt dame was thought to be, that in his fauour moſte did ſtand</l>
               <l>Not knowyng vnder ſweete deceits,</l>
               <l>How Venus hides her poiſoned baits.</l>
               <l>But whe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> he ſawe them thus to range, who<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> loue had linked in his chain</l>
               <l>This meanes he ſought for to aſſwage, theſe Ladies of their greeuous pain.</l>
               <l>His ſhape intendyng to diſgrace,</l>
               <l>With many wounds he ſcorcht his face,</l>
               <l>By which his deede it came to paſſe, that he that ſemed an angell bright</l>
               <l>Euen now ſo cleane diſfigured was, that he became a lothſome wight.</l>
               <l>And rather had he be foule and chaſte,</l>
               <l>Then faire, and filihie ioyes to taſte.</l>
               <l>What pen can write, or tong expreſſe, the worthy praiſes of this déede,</l>
               <l>Me thinke that God ca<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> do no leſſe, then grau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t him heaue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> for his méede</l>
               <l>Who for to ſaue hym ſelf vpright,</l>
               <l>Hym ſelf hath firſt deſtroied quite.</l>
               <trailer>Finis</trailer>
               <closer>
                  <signed>M. E.</signed>
               </closer>
            </div>
            <div n="60" type="poem">
               <pb n="32" facs="tcp:12052:30" rendition="simple:additions"/>
               <head>
                  <hi>60.</hi> A bunche of hearbes and flowers.</head>
               <l>IF that eche flower, the Gods haue framed, or ſhapt by ſacred ſkill,</l>
               <l>Where as I would (no wrong to wiſhe) and myne to weare at will.</l>
               <l>Or els eche tree, with luſtie top, would lende me leaue to Loue,</l>
               <l>With ſpriggs diſplaied to ſpread my ſute, a wailyng harte to proue.</l>
               <l>Vpon my helme ſone ſhould you ſee, my hedde aduaunced hie,</l>
               <l>Some ſlipp for ſolace there to ſet, and weare the ſame would I.</l>
               <l>Yet would I not for greate delight, the Daiſes ſtraunge deſire,</l>
               <l>The Lillie would not like my luſte, nor Roſe would I require.</l>
               <l>The Marigolde might growe for me, Roſemarie well might reſte,</l>
               <l>The Fenell to, that is more fitt, for ſome vnfrendly geſte.</l>
               <l>Nor Cowſlopps would I craue at all, ſometymes thei ſeem to coye,</l>
               <l>Some ioly youth the Gelliflower, eſtemeth for his ioye.</l>
               <l>The Lauender ſometymes alofte, alures the lookers eyes,</l>
               <l>The Paunſie ſhall not haue the praiſe, where I maie giue the priſe.</l>
               <l>And thus no flower my fanſie feedes, or liketh ſo my luſte,</l>
               <l>As that I maie ſubiecte my ſelf, to toyes of tickle truſte.</l>
               <l>For flowers though thei be faire and freſhe, of ſent excellyng ſweete,</l>
               <l>Yet growe thei on the grounde belowe, we tread them with our feete.</l>
               <l>And ſhall I then goe ſtoupe to ſuche? or els goe ſeke to thoſe,</l>
               <l>Shall flowers enforce me once to faune, for feare of frends or foze.</l>
               <l>Yet rather yelde I to the right, as reaſon hath aſſinde,</l>
               <l>Myne aucthour ſaied there was no ſalue, in flowers for me to finde.</l>
               <l>And yet perhaps ſome Tree there is, to ſhroude me from the ſhower,</l>
               <l>That with her armes maie ſalue the ſoule, that yeldeth to her power.</l>
               <l>Where I maie finde ſome pleaſaunt ſhade, to ſalue me from the Sunne</l>
               <l>Eche thyng we ſee that reaſon hath, vnto the Trees doe runne.</l>
               <l>Bothe men and beaſts ſuche foules as flyes, the treaſures are the trees,</l>
               <l>And for my parte when braunches fall, I wiſhe no other fees.</l>
               <l>But when that ſtormes beſett me rounde, ſuche ſuccour God me ſende.</l>
               <l>That I maie finde a frendlie Tree, that will me well defende.</l>
               <l>No Tree there is whiche yelds no good, to ſome that doeth it ſeke:</l>
               <l>And as thei are of diuerſe kinds, their vſes are vnlike.</l>
               <l>The Eue tree ſerues the Bowyers tourne, the Aſhe the Coupers arte,</l>
               <l>The puiſſaunt Oke doeth make the poſte, the Pine ſome other parte.</l>
               <l>The Elme doeth helpe to hide the birds, in wearie Winters night,</l>
               <l>The Briers I geſſe are nothyng worthe, thei ſerue but for deſpight.</l>
               <l>
                  <pb facs="tcp:12052:31" rendition="simple:additions"/>The Willowe wiſht I farre from hence, good will deſerue no wrong,</l>
               <l>The Sallowe well maie ſerue their ſtates, that ſyng ſo ſad a ſong.</l>
               <l>The Boxe and Beeche eche for hym ſelf, aboue the reſte doeth boſte,</l>
               <l>The Eglantine for pleaſure ofte, is pricked vpon the poſte,</l>
               <l>The Hauthorne ſo is had in priſe, the Baies doe beare the bell,</l>
               <l>And that theſe Baies did bryng no bliſſe, I like it not ſo well.</l>
               <l>As erſt I doe that ſemely Tree, by whiche thoſe Baies I founde,</l>
               <l>And where withall vnwittyngly, I tooke ſo greate a wounde.</l>
               <l>As if the Tree by whiche I lent, doeth lende me no relief,</l>
               <l>There is no helpe but doune I fall, ſo greate is growne my grief.</l>
               <l>And therefore at the laſte I craue, this fauour for to finde,</l>
               <l>When euery Tree that here is tolde, beginns to growe vnkinde.</l>
               <l>The B. for beautie whom I boſte, and ſhall aboue the reſte,</l>
               <l>That B. maie take me to her truſt, for B. doeth pleaſe me beſte.</l>
               <l>It liks me well to walke the waie, where B. doeth keepe her bower,</l>
               <l>And when it Raines to B. I runne to ſaue me from the ſhower.</l>
               <l>This braunche of B. whiche here I meane, to kepe and chiefly craue,</l>
               <l>At becke vnto this B. I bowe, to ſerue that beautie braue.</l>
               <l>What ſhall I ſaie the tyme doeth paſſe, the tale to tedious is,</l>
               <l>Though lothe to leaue, yet leaue I muſt, and ſaie no more but this.</l>
               <l>I wiſhe this B. I might embrace, when as the ſame I ſee,</l>
               <l>A league for life then I require, betwene this B. and me.</l>
               <l>And though vnworthy, yet good will, doeth worke the waie herein</l>
               <l>And B. hath brought the ſame about, which beautie did begin.</l>
               <trailer>Finis.</trailer>
            </div>
            <div n="62" type="poem">
               <head>
                  <hi>62.</hi> In commendation of Muſick.</head>
               <lg>
                  <l>WHere griping grief y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> hart would wou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>de, &amp; dolfull du<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>pes y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> mind oppreſſe,</l>
                  <l>There Muſick with her ſiluer ſou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d, is wont w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> ſpede to giue redreſſe:</l>
                  <l>Of troubled mynds for euery ſore, ſweete Muſick hath a ſalue in ſtore.</l>
                  <l>In ioy it maks our mirth abound, in grief it chers our heauie ſprits,</l>
                  <l>The carefull head relief hath found, by Muſicks pleaſant ſwete delits:</l>
                  <l>Our ſenſes, what ſhould I ſaie more, are ſubiecte vnto Muſicks lore.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>The Gods by Muſick hath their praie, the foule therein doeth ioye,</l>
                  <l>For as the Romain Poets ſaie, in ſeas whom Pirats would deſtroye,</l>
                  <l>A Dolphin ſaude from death moſte ſharpe, Arion plaiyng on his harpe</l>
                  <l>Oh heaue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ly gift, y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> turnes the minde, like as the ſterne doeth rule y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſhip,</l>
                  <l>Of muſick who<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the gods aſſignde to co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>fort ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, whom cares would nip</l>
                  <l>Sith y<hi rend="sup">u</hi> both man &amp; beaſt doeſt moue, what wiſema<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> will thée reproue.</l>
               </lg>
               <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
            </div>
            <div n="63" type="verse_dialogue">
               <pb n="33" facs="tcp:12052:31" rendition="simple:additions"/>
               <head>
                  <hi>63.</hi> A dialog betwene the auctour and his eye.</head>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Auctour.</speaker>
                  <l>MY eye why didſt thou light on that, whiche was not thyne?</l>
                  <l>Why haſt thou with thy ſight, thus ſlaine an harte of myne?</l>
                  <l>O thou vnhappie eye, would God thou hadſt been blinde,</l>
                  <l>When firſt thou didſt her ſpie, for whom this grief I finde.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Eye.</speaker>
                  <l>Why ſir it is not I, that doe deſerue ſuche blame,</l>
                  <l>Your fancie not your eye, is cauſer of the ſame:</l>
                  <l>For I am readie preſt as page that ſerues your eaſe,</l>
                  <l>To ſearche what thyng is beſte, that might your fancie pleaſe.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Aucthour.</speaker>
                  <l>I ſent thée forthe to ſee, but not ſo long to bide,</l>
                  <l>Though fancie went with thee, thou wert my fancies guide:</l>
                  <l>Thy meſſage beyng doen, thou mights retourne againe,</l>
                  <l>So Cupid Venus ſonne, no whit my harte ſhould paine.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Eye.</speaker>
                  <l>Where fancie beareth ſwaye, there Cupid will bee bolde,</l>
                  <l>And reaſon flies awaie, from Cupids ſhafte of golde:</l>
                  <l>If you finde cauſe thereby, ſome deale of painfull ſmarte,</l>
                  <l>Alas blame not your eye, but blame conſent of harte.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Auctour.</speaker>
                  <l>My harte muſt I excuſe, and laye the fault on thee,</l>
                  <l>Becauſe thy ſight did chuſe, when harte from thought was free:</l>
                  <l>Thy ſight thus brought conſente, conſent hath bred my grief,</l>
                  <l>And grief bids bee content, with ſorrowe for relief.</l>
               </sp>
               <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
               <closer>
                  <signed>M. Hunnis.</signed>
               </closer>
            </div>
            <div n="64" type="poem">
               <head>
                  <hi>64.</hi> Fyndyng no ioye, he deſireth death.</head>
               <lg>
                  <l>THe Conie in his caue, the Feret doeth annoye,</l>
                  <l>And fleyng thence his life to ſaue, hym ſelf he doeth deſtroye.</l>
                  <l>His Berrie rounde about beſet, with Hunters ſnares,</l>
                  <l>So that when he to ſcape ſtarts out, is caught therein vnwares,</l>
                  <l>Like choiſe poore man haue I, to bide and reſte in Loue,</l>
                  <l>Or els from thence to flie, as badde a death to proue.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>I ſee, in Loue to reſte, vnkindneſſe doeth purſue,</l>
                  <l>To rent the harte out of his breaſt, whiche is a Louer true:</l>
                  <l>
                     <pb facs="tcp:12052:32" rendition="simple:additions"/>And if from Loue I ſtarte, as one that Loue forſaks,</l>
                  <l>Then penſiue thoughts my harte doeth pearce, and ſo my life it taks.</l>
                  <l>Then thus to flie or bide, hard is the choiſe to chuſe,</l>
                  <l>Since death hath campd, and trenched eche ſide, &amp; ſaith life now refuſe.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>Content I am therefore, my life therein to ſpende,</l>
                  <l>And death I take a ſalue for ſore, my wearie daies to ende.</l>
                  <l>And thus I you require, that faithfull Loue profeſſe,</l>
                  <l>When carcas caſed is in cheſte, and bodie laied on hearſe.</l>
                  <l>Your briniſhe teares to ſaue, ſuche as my corſe ſhall moue,</l>
                  <l>And therewith write vpon my graue, beholde the force of Loue.</l>
               </lg>
               <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
               <closer>
                  <signed>M. Hunnis.</signed>
               </closer>
            </div>
            <div type="poem">
               <head>Hope well and haue well.</head>
               <lg>
                  <l>IN hope the Shipman hoiſeth ſaile, in hope of paſſage good,</l>
                  <l>In hope of healthe the ſicke man, doeth ſuffer loſſe of blood:</l>
                  <l>In hope the priſoner linckt in chaines, hopes libertie to finde,</l>
                  <l>Thus hope breds health, and health breds eaſe, to euery troubled mind.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>In hope deſire getts victorie, in hope greate comfort ſpryngs,</l>
                  <l>In hope the Louer liues in ioyes, he feares no dreadfull ſtyngs:</l>
                  <l>In hope we liue and maie abide, ſuche ſtormes as are aſſignde,</l>
                  <l>Thus hope breds health, &amp; health breds eaſe, to euery troubled mynde.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>In hope we eaſely ſuffer harme, in hope of future tyme,</l>
                  <l>In hope of fruite, the paine ſemes ſweete, that to the tree doeth clime:</l>
                  <l>In hope of Loue ſuche glorie growes, as now by propfe I finde,</l>
                  <l>That hope breds health, &amp; health breds eaſe to euery troubled mynde.</l>
               </lg>
               <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
               <closer>
                  <signed>M. Hunnis.</signed>
               </closer>
            </div>
            <div type="poem">
               <head>He requeſteth ſome frendly comfort, affirmyng his conſtancie.</head>
               <l>THe mountaines hie whoſe loftie topps, doeth mete the hautie ſky</l>
               <l>The craggie rocke that to the ſea, free paſſage doeth deny:</l>
               <l>The aged Oke that doeth reſiſt, the force of bluſtryng blaſte,</l>
               <l>The pleaſaunt hearbe that euery where, a fragrant ſmell doeth caſte.</l>
               <l>The Lions force whoſe courage ſtout, declares a princelike might,</l>
               <l>The Eagle that for worthineſſe, is borne of kyngs in fight:</l>
               <l>The Serpent eke whoſe poiſoned iaws, doeth belche out venime vile,</l>
               <l>The lothſome Tode that ſhumeth light, and liueth in exile.</l>
               <l>Theſe theſe I ſaie and thouſands more, by trackt of tyme decaie,</l>
               <l>And like to tyme doe quite conſume, and bade from tyme to claie:</l>
               <l>
                  <pb n="34" facs="tcp:12052:32" rendition="simple:additions"/>But my true harte and ſeruice vowed, ſhall laſte tyme out of minde,</l>
               <l>And ſtill remaines as thyne by dome, as Cupid hath aſſingde.</l>
               <l>My faithe loe here I vowe to thee, my trothe thou knoweſt right well,</l>
               <l>My goods my frends, my life is thyne, what neede I more to tell?</l>
               <l>I am not myne, but thyne I vowe, thy heſts I will obeye,</l>
               <l>And ſerue thee as a ſeruaunt ought, in pleaſyng if I maie:</l>
               <l>And ſithe I haue no fliyng wyngs, to ſee thee as I wiſhe,</l>
               <l>Ne ſinnes to cut the ſiluer ſtreames, as doeth the glidyng fiſhe.</l>
               <l>Wherefore leaue now forgetfulneſſe, and ſende againe to me,</l>
               <l>And ſtraine thy azured vaines to write, then I maie gretyng ſee:</l>
               <l>And thus farewell more deare to me, then chiefeſt frende I haue,</l>
               <l>Whoſe Loue in harte I minde to ſhrine, till death his fee doe craue.</l>
               <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
               <closer>
                  <signed>M. Edwardes.</signed>
               </closer>
            </div>
            <div type="poem">
               <head>His complaneth his miſhapp.</head>
               <lg>
                  <l>SHall rigour raigne where ruth hath run, ſhall fanſie now forſake?</l>
                  <l>Shall fortune loſe that fauour wonne, ſhall not your anger ſlake?</l>
                  <l>Shall hatefull harte be had in you, that frendly did pretende,</l>
                  <l>Shall ſlipper thought and faithe vntrue, that harte of yours defende?</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>Shall nature ſhewe your beautie faire, that gentle ſemes to bee?</l>
                  <l>Shall frowardneſſe your fancies heire, be of more force then ſhe?</l>
                  <l>Shall now diſdaine the dragg of death, directe and leade the waie?</l>
                  <l>Shall all the imps vpon the yearth, reioyce at my decaie?</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>Shall this the ſeruice of my youth, haue ſuche reward at laſte?</l>
                  <l>Shall I receiue rigour of ruthe, and be from fauour caſte?</l>
                  <l>Shall I therefore berent my heares, with wights that wiſhe to dye?</l>
                  <l>Or ſhall I bathe my ſelf with teares, to feede your fickle eye.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>No, no, I ſhall in paine lye ſtill, with turtle Doue moſte true,</l>
                  <l>And vowe my ſelf to witt and will, their counſels to enſue:</l>
                  <l>Good Ladies all that Louers be, and that to be pretende,</l>
                  <l>Giue place to witt, let reaſon ſeme, your enemie to defende.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>Leſt that you thinke as I haue thought, your ſelf to ſtroue in vaine,</l>
                  <l>And ſo to be in thraldome brought, with me to ſuffer paine.</l>
               </lg>
               <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
               <closer>
                  <signed>M. Hunnis.</signed>
               </closer>
            </div>
            <div type="poem">
               <head>No foe to a flatterer.</head>
               <lg>
                  <l>
                     <hi>I</hi> Would it were not as I thinke I would it were not ſo,</l>
                  <l>I am not blinde although I winke, I feele what winds doe blowe:</l>
                  <l>
                     <pb facs="tcp:12052:33" rendition="simple:additions"/>I knowe where crafte, with ſmilyng cheare, creps into boldned breaſte.</l>
                  <l>I heare how fained ſpeache ſpeaks faire, where hatred is poſſeſſe.</l>
                  <l>I ſee the Serpent lye and lurcke, vnder the greene alowe,</l>
                  <l>I ſee hym watche a tyme to worke, his poyſon to beſtowe.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>In frendly lookes ſuche fraude is founde, as faithe for feare is fled,</l>
                  <l>And frendſhip hath receiude ſuche wounde, as he is almoſte ded.</l>
                  <l>And hatefull harte with malice greate, ſo boiles in cankred mynde,</l>
                  <l>That flatterie flearyng in the face, had almoſte made me blinde.</l>
                  <l>But now I ſee all is not golde, that glittereth in the eye,</l>
                  <l>Nor yet ſuche frends as thei profeſſe, as now by proofe I trye.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>Though ſecret ſpight by crafte, hath made a coate of Panter ſkin,</l>
                  <l>And thinks to finde me in the ſhade, by ſleight to wrapp me in,</l>
                  <l>Yet God bee praiſed my eye is cleare, and can beholde the Sunne:</l>
                  <l>When falſhood dare not once appeare, to ende that he begunne,</l>
                  <l>Thus tyme ſhall trie the thyng amiſſe, whiche God ſaue ſhortly ſende,</l>
                  <l>And tourne the harte that fained is, to bee a faithfull frende.</l>
               </lg>
               <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
               <closer>
                  <signed>M. Hunnis.</signed>
               </closer>
            </div>
            <div type="poem">
               <head>His compariſon of Loue.</head>
               <lg>
                  <l>THe Spider with greate ſkill, doeth trauell daie by daie,</l>
                  <l>His lymmes no tyme lye ſtill, to ſet his houſe in ſtate:</l>
                  <l>And when he hath it wrought, thinkyng therein to raigne,</l>
                  <l>A blaſte of winde vnthought, doeth driue it doune againe.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>The proofe whereof is true, to make his worke indure,</l>
                  <l>He paines hym ſelf a newe, in hope to dwell more ſure:</l>
                  <l>And in ſome ſecret place, a corner of a wall,</l>
                  <l>He frameth hym ſelf a pace, to builde and reſt withall.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>His pleaſure ſweete to ſtaie, when he to reſt is bent,</l>
                  <l>An vgly ſhamble Flee, approcheth to his tent:</l>
                  <l>And htere entendes by force, his labours greate to win,</l>
                  <l>Or els to yelde his corſe, by fatall death therein.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>Thus is the Spiders neſt, from tyme to tyme throwne downe,</l>
                  <l>And he to labour preſt, with endleſſe paine vnknowne:</l>
                  <l>So ſuche as Louers bee, like trauell doe attaine,</l>
                  <l>Thoſe endleſſe works ye ſee, are alwaies full of paine.</l>
               </lg>
               <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
               <closer>
                  <signed>M. Hunnis.</signed>
               </closer>
            </div>
            <div type="poem">
               <pb n="35" facs="tcp:12052:33" rendition="simple:additions"/>
               <head>A Louers ioye.</head>
               <l>
                  <hi>I</hi> Haue no ioye, but dreame of ioye, and ioye to thinke on ioye,</l>
               <l>A ioye I withſtoode, for to enioye, to finiſhe myne annoye,</l>
               <l>I hate not without cauſe alas, yet Loue I knowe not why,</l>
               <l>I thought to hate, I can not hate, although that I ſhould dye.</l>
               <l>A foe moſte ſweete, a frende moſte ſower, I ioye for to embrace.</l>
               <l>I hate the wrong, and not the wight, that workt my wofull caſe:</l>
               <l>What thyng it is I knowe not I, but yet a thyng there is,</l>
               <l>That in my fancie ſtill perſwads, there is no other bliſſe.</l>
               <l>The ioyes of life, the pangs of death, it make me feele eche daie,</l>
               <l>But life nor death, this humour can, deuiſe to weare awaie.</l>
               <l>Faine would I dye, but yet in death no hope I ſee remaines,</l>
               <l>And ſhall I liue? ſince life I ſee, a courſe of ſorie paines:</l>
               <l>What is it then that I doe ſeeke, what ioye would I aſpire,</l>
               <l>A thyng that is deuine belike, to high for mans deſire.</l>
               <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
               <closer>
                  <signed>F. K.</signed>
               </closer>
            </div>
            <div type="poem">
               <head>Euill to hym that euill thinketh.</head>
               <lg>
                  <l>THe ſubtill ſtilie ſleghts, that worldly men doe woorke,</l>
                  <l>The friendly ſhowes, vnder whoſe ſhade, moſte craft doeth often lurke:</l>
                  <l>Enforceth me alas, with yernfull voyce to ſaie,</l>
                  <l>Wo worthe the wilie heads that ſeeks, the ſimple mans decaie,</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>The birde that dreads no guile, is ſoneſt caught in ſnare,</l>
                  <l>Eche gentle harte deuoide of crafte, is ſoneſt brought to care:</l>
                  <l>Good nature ſoneſt trapt, whiche giues me cauſe to ſaie,</l>
                  <l>Wo worthe the wilie heads, that ſeeks the ſimple mans decaie.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>I ſee the Serpent vile, that lurkes vnder the grene,</l>
                  <l>How ſubtilly he ſhroods hym ſelf, that he maie not be ſene:</l>
                  <l>And yet his foſters bane, his leryng lookes bewraie,</l>
                  <l>Wo worthe the wilie heads that leeks, the ſimple mans decaie.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>Wo worthe the feinyng looks, on fauour that we doe waite,</l>
                  <l>Wo worthe the feined frendly harte, that harbours deepe deceite:</l>
                  <l>Wo worthe the Vipers broode, oh thriſe wo worthe I ſaie,</l>
                  <l>All worldlie wilie heads, that ſeeks the ſimple mans decaie.</l>
               </lg>
               <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
               <closer>
                  <signed>M. Edwardes.</signed>
               </closer>
            </div>
            <div type="poem">
               <head>He aſſureth his constancie.</head>
               <lg>
                  <pb facs="tcp:12052:34" rendition="simple:additions"/>
                  <l>WIth painted ſpeache I liſt not proue, my cunnyng for to trie,</l>
                  <l>Nor yet will vſe to fill my penne, with gilefull flatterie:</l>
                  <l>With pen in hand, &amp; hart in breſt, ſhall faithful promiſe make</l>
                  <l>To loue you beſte, and ſerue you moſte, by your greate vertuts ſake.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>And ſure dame Nature hath you deckt, with gifts aboue the reſte,</l>
                  <l>Let not Diſdaine a harbour finde, within your noble breſte:</l>
                  <l>For Loue hath lead his lawe alike, to men of eche degrre,</l>
                  <l>So that the Begger with the Prince ſhall Loue as well as he.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>I am no Prince I muſte confeſſe, nor yet of Princes line,</l>
                  <l>Nor yet a brutiſhe Begger borne, that feeds emong the Swine:</l>
                  <l>The fruite ſhall trie the Tree at laſte, the bloſſomes good or no,</l>
                  <l>Then doe not iudge of me the worſe, till you haue tried me ſo.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>As I deſerue, ſo then reward, I make you iudge of all,</l>
                  <l>If I be falſe in woorde or deede, let Lightnyng Thunder fall:</l>
                  <l>And Furies fell with franticke fi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ts, bereue and ſtay my breathe,</l>
                  <l>For an example to the reſte, if I ſhall breake my faithe.</l>
               </lg>
               <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
               <closer>
                  <signed>M. Hunnis.</signed>
               </closer>
            </div>
            <div type="verse_dialogue">
               <head>Complainyng his miſhapp to his frende, he complaineth wittely.</head>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>A.</speaker>
                  <l>THe fire ſhall freze, the froſt ſhall frie the frozen mou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tains hie</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>B.</speaker>
                  <l>What ſtraunge things hath dame natures force, to turne her courſe awrie</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>A.</speaker>
                  <l>My Loue hath me left, and taken a newe man:</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>B.</speaker>
                  <l>This is not ſtraunge, it happes ofte tymes, the truthe to ſcan,</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>A.</speaker>
                  <l>The more is my paine,</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>B.</speaker>
                  <l>her Loue then refraine.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>A.</speaker>
                  <l>Who thought ſhe would flitt,</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>B.</speaker>
                  <l>eche one that hath witt,</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>A.</speaker>
                  <l>Is this not ſtraunge,</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>B.</speaker>
                  <l>light Loue will chaunge.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>A.</speaker>
                  <l>By ſkilfull meanes I here reclaime, to ſtoope vnto my lure,</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>B.</speaker>
                  <l>Suche haggard Haukes will ſoare awaie, of them who can be ſure</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>A.</speaker>
                  <l>With ſiluer bells and hoode, my ioye was her to decke,</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>B.</speaker>
                  <l>She was full gorgde, ſhe would the ſoner giue the checke,</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>A.</speaker>
                  <l>The more is my paine,</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>B.</speaker>
                  <l>her Loue then refraine:</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>A.</speaker>
                  <l>Who thought ſhe would flitt,</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>B.</speaker>
                  <l>eche one that hath witt,</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>A.</speaker>
                  <l>Is not this ſtraunge,</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>B.</speaker>
                  <l>light Loue will chaunge.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>A.</speaker>
                  <l>Her chirpyng lips ſhould chirpe to me, ſwete words of her deſire</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>B.</speaker>
                  <l>Suche chirpyng birdes who euer ſawe, to preach ſtill on one brire,</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>A.</speaker>
                  <l>She ſaied ſhe loued me beſte, and would not till ſhe die,</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>B.</speaker>
                  <l>She ſaied in wordes, ſhe thought it not, as tyme doeth trie.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <pb n="36" facs="tcp:12052:34" rendition="simple:additions"/>
                  <speaker>A.</speaker>
                  <l>The more is my paine,</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>B.</speaker>
                  <l>her Loue then refraine:</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>A.</speaker>
                  <l>Who thought ſhe would flitt,</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>B.</speaker>
                  <l>eche one that hath witt,</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>A.</speaker>
                  <l>Is not this ſtraunge,</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>B.</speaker>
                  <l>light Loue will chaunge.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>A,</speaker>
                  <l>Can no man winne a woman ſo, to make her Loue endure,</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>B.</speaker>
                  <l>To make the Foxe his wiles to leaue, what man will put in vre?</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>A.</speaker>
                  <l>Why then there is no choiſe, but all women will chaunge,</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>B.</speaker>
                  <l>As men doe vſe, ſo ſome women doe Loue to raunge.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>A.</speaker>
                  <l>The more is my paine,</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>B.</speaker>
                  <l>her Loue then refraine,</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>A.</speaker>
                  <l>Who thought ſhe would flitt,</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>B.</speaker>
                  <l>eche one that hath witt,</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>A.</speaker>
                  <l>Is not this ſtraunge,</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>B.</speaker>
                  <l>light Loue will chaunge.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>A,</speaker>
                  <l>Sith ſlipper gaine falles to my lot, farewell that glidyng praie,</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>B.</speaker>
                  <l>Sith that the dice doeth runne awrie, betymes leaue of thy plaie.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>A.</speaker>
                  <l>I will no more lamente, the thyng I maie not haue,</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>B.</speaker>
                  <l>Then by exchaunge the loſſe to come, all ſhalt thou ſaue.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>A.</speaker>
                  <l>Loue will I refraine,</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>B.</speaker>
                  <l>thereby thou ſhalt gaine,</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>A,</speaker>
                  <l>With loſſe I will leaue,</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>B.</speaker>
                  <l>ſhe will thee deceiue:</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>A.</speaker>
                  <l>That is not ſtraunge,</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>B.</speaker>
                  <l>then let her raunge.</l>
               </sp>
               <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
               <closer>
                  <signed>M. Edwardes.</signed>
               </closer>
            </div>
            <div type="poem">
               <head>No paines comparable to his attempt.</head>
               <l>LIke as the dolefull Doue, delights alone to bee,</l>
               <l>And doeth refuſe the bloumed branche, chuſyng the leafleſſe tree.</l>
               <l>Whereon wailyng his chaunce, with bitter teares beſprent,</l>
               <l>Doeth with his bill, his tender breaſte ofte pearſe and all to rent.</l>
               <l>Whoſe greeuous gronyngs tho: whoſe grips of pinyng paine,</l>
               <l>Whoſe gaſtly lookes, whoſe bloudie ſtreams out flowyng fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ech vain.</l>
               <l>Whoſe fallyng from the tree, whoſe pantyng on the grounde,</l>
               <l>Examples bee of myne eſtate, tho there appere no wounde.</l>
               <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
               <closer>
                  <signed>W. Hunnis.</signed>
               </closer>
            </div>
            <div type="poem">
               <head>He repenteth his follie.</head>
               <lg>
                  <l>
                     <hi>A</hi> Lacke when I looke backe, vpon my youth thatz paſte,</l>
                  <l>And deepely pouder youthes offence, and youths reward at laſte.</l>
                  <l>With ſighes and teares I ſaie, O God I not denie,</l>
                  <l>My youth with follie hath deſerued, with follie for to die.</l>
                  <l>But yet if euer ſynfull man, might mercie moue to ruthe,</l>
                  <l>Good Lorde with mercie doe forgiue, the follies of my youthe.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>In youth I rangde the feelds, where vices all did growe,</l>
                  <l>
                     <pb facs="tcp:12052:35" rendition="simple:additions"/>In youth alas I wanted grace, ſuche viſe to ouerthrowe,</l>
                  <l>In youth what I thought ſwéete, moſte bitter now do finde,</l>
                  <l>Thus hath the follies of my youth, with folly kept me blind</l>
                  <l>Yet as the Egle caſts her bill, whereby her age renueth,</l>
                  <l>So Lorde with mercie doe forgiue, the follies of my youth.</l>
               </lg>
               <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
               <closer>
                  <signed>M. Hunnis.</signed>
               </closer>
            </div>
            <div type="poem">
               <head>No pleaſure without ſome paine.</head>
               <lg>
                  <l>HOw can the tree but waſt, and wither awaie,</l>
                  <l>That hath not ſometyme comforte of the Sunne:</l>
                  <l>How can that flower but fade, and ſone decaie,</l>
                  <l>That alwaies is with darcke clouds runne.</l>
                  <l>Is this a life, naye death you maie it call,</l>
                  <l>That feeles eche paine, and knoweth no ioye at all.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>What foodleſſe beaſt can liue long in good plight?</l>
                  <l>Or is it life, where ſences there be none:</l>
                  <l>Or what auaileth eyes without their light?</l>
                  <l>Or els a tongue, to hym that is alone.</l>
                  <l>Is this a life? naye death you maie it call,</l>
                  <l>That féeles eche paine, and knowes no ioy at all.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>Wherto ſerue eares, if that there be no ſound</l>
                  <l>Or ſuche a head, where no deuiſe doeth growe:</l>
                  <l>But all of plaints, ſince ſorrowe is the grounde,</l>
                  <l>Whereby the harte doeth pine in deadlie woe.</l>
                  <l>Is this a life, naye death you maie it call,</l>
                  <l>That feles eche paine, and knowes no ioy at al.</l>
               </lg>
               <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
               <closer>
                  <signed>L. Vaux.</signed>
               </closer>
            </div>
            <div type="poem">
               <head>The fruite of feined frendes.</head>
               <lg>
                  <l>IN choiſe of frends what hap had I, to chuſe one of Cire<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s kind</l>
                  <l>whoſe harp, whoſe pipe, whoſe melody could fede my ears &amp; make me blind</l>
                  <l>Whoſe pleaſant voice made me forget, y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> in ſure truſt is gret deceit.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>In truſt I ſee is treaſon founde, and man to man deceitfull is,</l>
                  <l>And whereas treaſure doeth abounde, of flatterers there doe not miſſe:</l>
                  <l>Whoſe painted ſpeache, &amp; outward ſhow, do ſeme as frends &amp; be not ſo.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>Would I haue thought in thee to be, the nature of the Crocadill:</l>
                  <l>Whiche if a man a ſlepe maie ſee, with bloudie thirſt deſires to kill:</l>
                  <l>And then w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> teares a while gan wepe, the death of him thus ſlain a ſlepe</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <pb n="38" facs="tcp:12052:35" rendition="simple:additions"/>
                  <l>O fauell falſe, thou traitor borne, what miſchief more might y<hi rend="sup">u</hi> deuiſe</l>
                  <l>Then thy deare frend to haue in ſcorne, &amp; hym to wound in ſundry wiſe</l>
                  <l>Whiche ſtill a frende pretends to bee, and are not ſo by proofe I ſee,</l>
                  <l>Fie, fie, vpon ſuche trecherie. <hi>W. H.</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>If ſuche falſe Shippes doe haunte the ſhore,</l>
                  <l>Strike doune the ſaile and truſt no more.</l>
               </lg>
               <closer>
                  <signed>M. Edwardes.</signed>
               </closer>
            </div>
            <div type="verse_dialogue">
               <head>A dialogue betwene a Gentleman and his Loue.</head>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>A.</speaker>
                  <l>SHall I no waie winne you, to graunt my deſire?</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>B.</speaker>
                  <l>What woman will graunt you, the thyng you require:</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>A.</speaker>
                  <l>You onely to Loue me, is all that I craue,</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>B.</speaker>
                  <l>You onely to leaue me, is all I would haue.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>A.</speaker>
                  <l>My deare alas, now ſaie not ſo,</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>B.</speaker>
                  <l>To Loue you beſte I muſt ſaie no:</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>A.</speaker>
                  <l>Yet will I not flitt,</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>B.</speaker>
                  <l>then plaie on the bitt.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>B.</speaker>
                  <l>I will,</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>B.</speaker>
                  <l>doe ſtill,</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>A.</speaker>
                  <l>yet kill not,</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>B.</speaker>
                  <l>I will not.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>A.</speaker>
                  <l>Make me your man,</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>B.</speaker>
                  <l>beſhrewe me than.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>A.</speaker>
                  <l>The ſwifter I followe, then you flie awaie,</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>B.</speaker>
                  <l>Swift hauks in their fliyng, oft tymes miſſe their praie,</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>A.</speaker>
                  <l>Yet ſome killeth deadly, that flie to the marke:</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>B.</speaker>
                  <l>You ſhall touche no feather, thereof take no carke.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>A.</speaker>
                  <l>Yet hope ſhall further my deſire,</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>B.</speaker>
                  <l>You blowe the coales, and raiſe no fire,</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>A.</speaker>
                  <l>Yet will I not flitt,</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>B.</speaker>
                  <l>then plaie on the bitt,</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>B.</speaker>
                  <l>I will,</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>B.</speaker>
                  <l>doe ſtill,</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>A.</speaker>
                  <l>yet kill not,</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>B,</speaker>
                  <l>I will not,</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>A.</speaker>
                  <l>Make me your man,</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>B.</speaker>
                  <l>beſhrewe me than.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>A.</speaker>
                  <l>To Loue is no daunger, where true Loue is ment,</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>B.</speaker>
                  <l>I will Loue no ranger, leaſt that I repent:</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>A.</speaker>
                  <l>My Loue is no raunger, I make God auow,</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>B.</speaker>
                  <l>To truſt your ſmothe ſaiyngs, I ſure knowe not how.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>A.</speaker>
                  <l>Moſte truthe I meane, as tyme ſhall well trie,</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>B.</speaker>
                  <l>No truthe in men, I ofte eſpie,</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>A.</speaker>
                  <l>Yet will I not flitt,</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>B.</speaker>
                  <l>then plaie on the bitt.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>B.</speaker>
                  <l>I will,</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>B.</speaker>
                  <l>doe ſtill,</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>A.</speaker>
                  <l>yet kill not,</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>B.</speaker>
                  <l>I will not,</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>A.</speaker>
                  <l>Make me your man,</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>B.</speaker>
                  <l>beſhrewe me than.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>A.</speaker>
                  <l>Some women maie ſaie naie, and meane Loue moſte true,</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>B.</speaker>
                  <l>Some women can make fooles, of as wiſe men as you:</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <pb facs="tcp:12052:36"/>
                  <speaker>A.</speaker>
                  <l>In tyme I ſhall catche you, I knowe when and where:</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>B.</speaker>
                  <l>I will ſone diſpatche you, you ſhall not come there.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>A.</speaker>
                  <l>Some ſpeds at length, that ofte haue miſte,</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>B.</speaker>
                  <l>I am well armde, come when you liſte.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>A.</speaker>
                  <l>Yet will I not flitt,</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>B.</speaker>
                  <l>then plaie on the bitt.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>A.</speaker>
                  <l>I will,</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>B.</speaker>
                  <l>doe ſtill,</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>A.</speaker>
                  <l>yet kill not,</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>B.</speaker>
                  <l>I will not,</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>A.</speaker>
                  <l>Make me your man,</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>B.</speaker>
                  <l>beſhrewe me than.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>A.</speaker>
                  <l>Yet worke your kinde kindly, graunt me Loue for Loue,</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>B.</speaker>
                  <l>I will vſe you frendly, as I ſhall you proue:</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>A.</speaker>
                  <l>Moſte true you ſhall finde me, I this doe proteſt,</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>B.</speaker>
                  <l>Then ſure you ſhall binde me, to graunte your requeſt.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>A.</speaker>
                  <l>O happie threede, now haue I ſpunne,</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>B.</speaker>
                  <l>You ſyng before the conqueſt wonne.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>A.</speaker>
                  <l>Why then, will you ſwarue,</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>B.</speaker>
                  <l>euen as you deſarue:</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>A</speaker>
                  <l>Loue ſtill,</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>B.</speaker>
                  <l>I will,</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>A.</speaker>
                  <l>yet kill not,</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>B.</speaker>
                  <l>I will not,</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>A.</speaker>
                  <l>Make me your man,</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>B.</speaker>
                  <l>come to me than.</l>
               </sp>
               <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
               <closer>
                  <signed>M. Edwardes.</signed>
               </closer>
            </div>
            <div type="verse_dialogue">
               <head>Exclamyng vpon his vnkinde Loue, his frende replieth wittely.</head>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>M.</speaker>
                  <l>WHat death maie bee, compared to Loue?</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>H.</speaker>
                  <l>What grief therein, now doeſt thou proue?</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>M.</speaker>
                  <l>My paines alas, who can expreſſe,</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>H.</speaker>
                  <l>I ſee no cauſe of heauineſſe.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>M.</speaker>
                  <l>My Ladies looks, my woe hath wrought:</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>H.</speaker>
                  <l>Then blame thyne eyes, that firſte hath ſought,</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>M.</speaker>
                  <l>I burne alas, and blowe the fire,</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>H.</speaker>
                  <l>A foole conſumes by his deſire,</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>M.</speaker>
                  <l>What ſhall I doe than?</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>H.</speaker>
                  <l>come out and thou can.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>M.</speaker>
                  <l>Alas I die,</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>H.</speaker>
                  <l>what remedie?</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>M.</speaker>
                  <l>My ſugred ſweete, is mixed with gall,</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>H.</speaker>
                  <l>Thy Ladie can not doe with all:</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>M.</speaker>
                  <l>The more I ſeeke, the leſſe I finde,</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>H.</speaker>
                  <l>Then ſtriue not with the ſtreame and wind.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>M.</speaker>
                  <l>Her muſt I Loue, although I ſmarte,</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>H.</speaker>
                  <l>With her owne ſworde, thou ſlaieſt thy hart</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>M.</speaker>
                  <l>Suche pleaſaunt baits, who can refraine,</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>H.</speaker>
                  <l>Suche baits will ſure breede thee greate paine,</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <pb facs="tcp:12052:36" rendition="simple:additions"/>
                  <speaker>M.</speaker>
                  <l>What ſhall I doe than?</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>H.</speaker>
                  <l>Come out and thou can.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>M.</speaker>
                  <l>Alas I die,</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>H.</speaker>
                  <l>what remedie.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>M.</speaker>
                  <l>Her golden beames, myne eyes doe daze,</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>H.</speaker>
                  <l>Vpon the Sunne thou maieſt not gaze:</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>M.</speaker>
                  <l>She might reward my cruell ſmarte,</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>H.</speaker>
                  <l>She thinks thou hardſt a fained harte.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>M.</speaker>
                  <l>She laughs to heare my wofull cries,</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>H.</speaker>
                  <l>Forſake her then, in tyme bee wiſe:</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>M.</speaker>
                  <l>No, no, alas, that maie not bee,</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>H.</speaker>
                  <l>No wiſe man then, will pitie thee,</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>M.</speaker>
                  <l>What ſhall I doe than?</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>H.</speaker>
                  <l>come out and thou can.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>M.</speaker>
                  <l>Alas I die,</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>H.</speaker>
                  <l>what remedie.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>M,</speaker>
                  <l>A liuyng death, loe thus I proue,</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>H.</speaker>
                  <l>Suche are the fruits of froward Loue:</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>M.</speaker>
                  <l>O that I might her Loue once gaine,</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>H.</speaker>
                  <l>Thy gaine would not, halfe quite the paine.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>M.</speaker>
                  <l>Her will I Loue, though ſhe be coye,</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>H.</speaker>
                  <l>A foole hym ſelf, will ſtill annoye:</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>M.</speaker>
                  <l>Who will not die, for ſuche a one?</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>H.</speaker>
                  <l>Bee wiſe at length, let her alone:</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>M.</speaker>
                  <l>I can not doe ſo,</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>H.</speaker>
                  <l>then be thy owne fo,</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>M.</speaker>
                  <l>Alas I die,</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>H.</speaker>
                  <l>what remedie.</l>
               </sp>
               <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
               <closer>
                  <signed>E. S.</signed>
               </closer>
            </div>
            <div type="poem">
               <head>The complaint of a Louer, wearyng Blacke and Taunie.</head>
               <lg>
                  <l>A Croune of Baies ſhall that man weare,</l>
                  <l>That triumphs ouer me:</l>
                  <l>For Blacke and Taunie will I weare,</l>
                  <l>Whiche mournyng coulers bee.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>The more I followe on, the more ſhe fled awaie,</l>
                  <l>As Daphne did full long agoe, Apollos wiſhfull praie:</l>
                  <l>The more my plaints reſounde, the leſſe ſhe pities me,</l>
                  <l>The more I ſought, the leſſe I founde, that myne ſhe meant to be.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>Melpomene, alas with dolefull tunes helpe than,</l>
                  <l>And ſyng <hi>Bis</hi> woe worthe on me forſaken man:</l>
                  <l>
                     <pb facs="tcp:12052:37" rendition="simple:additions"/>Then Daphnes Baies ſhall that man weare, that triumphs ouer me,</l>
                  <l>For Blacke and Taunie will I weare, whiche mournyng colours be.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>Droune me you tricklyng teares, you wailefull wights of woe,</l>
                  <l>Come helpe theſe hands to rent my heares, my rewfull hap to ſhowe:</l>
                  <l>On whom the ſcorchyng flames of Loue, doeth feede you ſee,</l>
                  <l>Ah a lalalantida my deare Dame, hath thus tormented me.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>Wherefore you Muſes nine, with dolefull tunes helpe than,</l>
                  <l>And ſyng <hi>Bis</hi> woe worthe on me forſaken man:</l>
                  <l>Then Daphnes Baies ſhall that man weare, that triumphs ouer me,</l>
                  <l>For Blacke and Taunie will I weare, whiche mournyng colours be.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>An Ancres life to leade, with nailes to ſcratche my graue,</l>
                  <l>Where yearthly wormes on me ſhall feede, is all the ioyes I craue:</l>
                  <l>And hide my ſelf from ſhame, ſithe that myne eyes doe ſee,</l>
                  <l>Ah a lalalantida my deare dame, hath thus tormented me.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>And all that preſent bee, with dolefull tunes helpe than:</l>
                  <l>And ſyng <hi>Bis</hi> woe worthe on me, forſaken man,</l>
               </lg>
               <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
               <closer>
                  <signed>E. O.</signed>
               </closer>
            </div>
            <div type="poem">
               <head>Findyng no releef, he complaineth thus.</head>
               <lg>
                  <l>INqueſt of my releef, I finde diſtreſſe,</l>
                  <l>In recompence of Loue, moſte depe diſdaine:</l>
                  <l>My langour ſuche, as words maie not expreſſe,</l>
                  <l>A ſhower of teares, my watriſhe eye doeth raine.</l>
                  <l>I dreame of this, and doe deuine of woe,</l>
                  <l>I wander in the thoughts of my ſweete foe.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>I would no peace, the cauſe of warre I flie,</l>
                  <l>I hope, I feare, I burne, I chill in Froſte:</l>
                  <l>I lye a lowe, yet mounts my mynde on hie,</l>
                  <l>Thus doubtfull ſtormes, my troubled thoughts haue toſte,</l>
                  <l>And for my paine, this pleaſure doe I proue,</l>
                  <l>I hate my ſelf, and pine in others Loue.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>The worlde I graſpe, yet holde I nought at all,</l>
                  <l>At libertie I ſeme, in priſon pent:</l>
                  <l>I taſte the ſweete, more ſower then bitter gall,</l>
                  <l>My ſhipp ſemes ſounde, and yet her ribbs bee rent.</l>
                  <l>And out alas, on Fortune falſe I crie,</l>
                  <l>
                     <pb n="51" facs="tcp:12052:37" rendition="simple:additions"/>Looke what I craue, that ſtill ſhe doeth denie.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>Bothe life and death, be equall vnto me,</l>
                  <l>I doe deſire to die, yet craue I life.</l>
                  <l>My witts with ſondrie thoughts doe diſagree,</l>
                  <l>My ſelf am with my ſelf at mortall ſtrife.</l>
                  <l>As warmth of Sunne, doeth melte the ſiluer Snowe,</l>
                  <l>The heate of Loue, beholde conſumes me ſo.</l>
               </lg>
               <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
               <closer>
                  <signed>R. Hall.</signed>
               </closer>
            </div>
            <div type="poem">
               <head>A Louer diſdained, complaineth.</head>
               <lg>
                  <l>IF euer man had loue to dearly bought,</l>
                  <l>Lo I am he that plaies within her maze:</l>
                  <l>And finds no waie, to get the ſame I ſought,</l>
                  <l>But as the Dere are driuen vnto the gaze.</l>
                  <l>And to augment the grief of my deſire,</l>
                  <l>My ſelf to burne, I blowe the fire:</l>
                  <l>But ſhall I come nye you?</l>
                  <l>Of force I muſt flie you.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>What death alas, maie be compared to this,</l>
                  <l>I praie within the maze of my ſweete foe:</l>
                  <l>And when I would of her but craue a kis,</l>
                  <l>Diſdaine enforceth her awaie to goe.</l>
                  <l>My ſelf I checke: yet doe I twiſte the twine,</l>
                  <l>The pleaſure hers, the paine is myne,</l>
                  <l>But ſhall I come nye you.</l>
                  <l>Of force I muſt flie you.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>You courtly wights, that wants your pleaſaunt choyſe,</l>
                  <l>Lende me a floud of teares, to waile my chaunce:</l>
                  <l>Happie are thei in Loue, that can reioyſe,</l>
                  <l>To their greate paines, where Fortune doeth aduaunce,</l>
                  <l>But ſith my ſute alas, can not preuaile,</l>
                  <l>Full fraight with care, in grief ſtill will I waile:</l>
                  <l>Sith you will nedes flie me,</l>
                  <l>I maie not come nye you.</l>
               </lg>
               <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
               <closer>
                  <signed>L. <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>aux.</signed>
               </closer>
            </div>
            <div type="poem">
               <head>Beyng in Loue, he complaineth.</head>
               <lg>
                  <pb facs="tcp:12052:38" rendition="simple:additions"/>
                  <l>IF care or ſkill, could conquere vaine deſire,</l>
                  <l>Or reaſons raignes, my ſtrong affection ſtaie</l>
                  <l>Then ſhould my ſighs to quiet breſt retire,</l>
                  <l>And ſhunne ſuche ſignes, as ſecret thoughts bewraie.</l>
                  <l>Vncomely Loue, whiche now lurks in my breaſt,</l>
                  <l>Should ceaſe my grief, through wiſedomes power oppreſt.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>But who can leaue, to looke on Venus face?</l>
                  <l>Or yeldeth not, to Iunos high eſtate:</l>
                  <l>What witt ſo wiſe, as giues not Pallas place,</l>
                  <l>Theſe vertues rare, eche Gods did yelde amate.</l>
                  <l>Saue her alone, who yet on yearth doeth raigne,</l>
                  <l>Whoſe beauties ſtryng, no God can well deſtraine.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>What worldly wight, can hope for heauenly hire,</l>
                  <l>When onely ſights, muſt make his ſecret moue:</l>
                  <l>A ſilent ſute, doeth ſelde to grace aſpire,</l>
                  <l>My hapleſſe happ doeth roule the reſtleſſe ſtone,</l>
                  <l>Yet Phebe faire, diſdainde the heauens aboue,</l>
                  <l>To ioye on yearth, her poore Edimions loue.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>Rare is reward, where none can iuſtly craue,</l>
                  <l>For chaunce is choiſe, where reaſon maks no claime:</l>
                  <l>Yet lucke ſometymes, diſpairyng ſoules doeth ſaue,</l>
                  <l>A happie Starre made Giges ioye attaine.</l>
                  <l>A ſlauiſhe Smithe, of rude and raſcall race,</l>
                  <l>Founde meanes in tyme, to gaine a Goddes grace.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>Then loftie Loue, thy ſacred ſailes aduaunce,</l>
                  <l>My ſithyng ſeas ſhall flowe with ſtreames of teares:</l>
                  <l>Amidds diſdaine, driue forthe my dolefull chaunce.</l>
                  <l>A valiaunt mynde, no deadly daunger feares.</l>
                  <l>Who loues alofte, and ſetts his harte on hie,</l>
                  <l>Deſerues no paine, though he doe pine and die.</l>
               </lg>
               <trailer>FINIS,</trailer>
               <closer>
                  <signed>E. O.</signed>
               </closer>
            </div>
            <div type="poem">
               <head>A Louer reiected, complaineth.</head>
               <lg>
                  <l>THe tricklyng teares, that falles along my cheeks,</l>
                  <l>The ſecret ſighs, that ſhewes my inward grief:</l>
                  <l>The preſent paines perforce, that Loue aye ſeeks,</l>
                  <l>Bidds me renewe, my cares without relief.</l>
                  <l>
                     <pb facs="tcp:12052:38" rendition="simple:additions"/>In wofull ſong in dole diſplaie,</l>
                  <l>My penſiue harte for to bewraie.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>Bewraie thy grief, thy wofull harte with ſpeede,</l>
                  <l>Reſigne thy voyce, to her that cauſde thy woe:</l>
                  <l>With irkſome cries, bewaile thy late doen deede,</l>
                  <l>For ſhe thou loueſt, is ſure thy mortall foe,</l>
                  <l>And helpe for thee, there is none ſure,</l>
                  <l>But ſtill in paine, thou muſt endure.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>The ſtriken Deare hath helpe to heale his wounde,</l>
                  <l>The haggerd Hauke, with toyle is made full tame:</l>
                  <l>The ſtrongeſt Tower, the Canon laies on grounde,</l>
                  <l>The wiſeſt witt, that euer had the fame.</l>
                  <l>Was thrall to Loue, by Cupids ſleights,</l>
                  <l>Then waie my caſe with equall weights.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>She is my ioye, ſhe is my care and wo,</l>
                  <l>She is my paine, ſhe is my eaſe therefore:</l>
                  <l>She is my death, ſhe is my life alſo,</l>
                  <l>She is my ſalue, ſhe is my wounded ſore.</l>
                  <l>In fine, ſhe hath the hande and knife,</l>
                  <l>That maie bothe ſaue, and ende my life.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>And ſhall I liue on yearth to be her thrall?</l>
                  <l>And ſhall I ſue, and ſerue her all in vaine?</l>
                  <l>And kiſſe the ſtepps, that ſhe letts fall,</l>
                  <l>And ſhall I praie the Gods, to keepe the paine.</l>
                  <l>From her, that is ſo cruell ſtill.</l>
                  <l>No, no, on her woorke all your will.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>And let her feele the power of all your might</l>
                  <l>And let her haue her moſte deſire with ſpeede:</l>
                  <l>And let her pine awaie, bothe daie and night,</l>
                  <l>And let her mone, and none lament her neede,</l>
                  <l>And let all thoſe, that ſhall her ſee,</l>
                  <l>Deſpiſe her ſtate, and pitie me.</l>
               </lg>
               <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
               <closer>
                  <signed>E. O.</signed>
               </closer>
            </div>
            <div type="poem">
               <head>Not attainyng to his deſire, he complaineth.</head>
               <lg>
                  <l>
                     <hi>I</hi> Am not as ſeme to bee, nor when I ſmile, I am not glad:</l>
                  <l>A thrall although you count me frée, I moſte in mirth, moſt pe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſiue ſad:</l>
                  <l>
                     <pb facs="tcp:12052:39"/>I ſmile to ſhade my bitter ſpight, as Haniball that ſawe in ſight:</l>
                  <l>His cou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>trie ſoile with Carthage toune: by Romain force defaced doun.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>And Ceſar that preſented was, with noble Pompeis princely heade,</l>
                  <l>As twere ſome iudge to rule the cace a flould of teares he ſemde to ſhed</l>
                  <l>Although in deede it ſprong of ioye, yet other thought it was annoye,</l>
                  <l>Thus contraries be vſed I finde, of wiſe to cloke the couert mynde.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>I Haniball that ſmiles for grief, and let you Ceſars grief ſuffice,</l>
                  <l>The one that laughs at his miſchief, the other all for ioye that cries:</l>
                  <l>I ſmile to ſee me ſcorned ſo, you weepe for ioye to ſee me woe,</l>
                  <l>And I a harte by Loue ſlaine deade, preſents in place of Pompeis head.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>O cruell happ, and harde eſtate, that forceth me to loue my fo,</l>
                  <l>Accurſed bee ſo foule a fate, my choyſe for to prefixe it ſo:</l>
                  <l>So long to fight with ſecret ſore, and finde no ſecret ſalue therefore,</l>
                  <l>Some urge their paine by plaint I finde, but I in vain doe breath my winde.</l>
               </lg>
               <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
               <closer>
                  <signed>E. Ox.</signed>
               </closer>
            </div>
            <div type="poem">
               <head>His mynde not quietly ſetled, he writeth thus.</head>
               <lg>
                  <l>EVen as the waxe doeth melte, or dewe conſume awaie</l>
                  <l>Before the Sunne, ſo I behold through carefull thoughts decaie:</l>
                  <l>For my beſte lucke leads me, to ſuche ſiniſter ſtate,</l>
                  <l>That I doe waſte with others Loue, that hath my ſelf in hate.</l>
                  <l>And he that beats the buſhe, the wiſhed birde not getts,</l>
                  <l>But ſuche I ſee as ſitteth ſtill, and holds the foulyng netts.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>The Drone more Honie ſucks, that laboureth not at all,</l>
                  <l>Then doeth the Bee, to whoſe moſte paine, leaſt pleaſure doeth befall:</l>
                  <l>The Gardner ſowes the ſeeds, whereof the flowers doe growe,</l>
                  <l>And others yet doe gather them, that tooke leſſe paine I knowe.</l>
                  <l>So I the pleaſaunt Grape haue pulled from the Vine,</l>
                  <l>And yet I languiſhe in greate thirſte, while others drinke the wine.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>Thus like a wofull wight, I woue the webb of woe,</l>
                  <l>The more I would weede out my cares, the more thei ſeme to growe:</l>
                  <l>The whiche betokeneth, forſaken is of me,</l>
                  <l>That with the carefull Culuer climes, the worne and withered tree.</l>
                  <l>To entertaine my thoughts, and there my happ to mone,</l>
                  <l>That neuer am leſſe idle loe, then when I am alone.</l>
               </lg>
               <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
               <closer>
                  <signed>E. Ox.</signed>
               </closer>
            </div>
            <div type="poem">
               <pb facs="tcp:12052:39" rendition="simple:additions"/>
               <head>That Loue is requited by diſdaine.</head>
               <lg>
                  <l>IN ſearche of thyngs that ſecret are, my mated muſe began,</l>
                  <l>What it might be, moleſted moſte the head and mynde of man.</l>
                  <l>The bendyng brow of princes face, to wrathe that doeth attende,</l>
                  <l>Or want of parents, wife or childe, or loſſe of faithfull frende.</l>
                  <l>The roryng of the Canon ſhot, that makes the peece to ſhake,</l>
                  <l>Or terrour ſuche as mightie Ioue, from heauen aboue can make.</l>
                  <l>All theſe in fine maie not compare experience ſo doeth proue,</l>
                  <l>Vnto the torments ſharpe and ſtrange, of ſuche as be in loue.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>Loue lookes a loft and laughs to ſcorne all ſuche as grefe anoye.</l>
                  <l>The more extreme their paſſions be, the greater is his ioye.</l>
                  <l>Thus Loue as victor of the felde, triumps aboue the reſt,</l>
                  <l>And ioyes to ſee his ſubiects lye, with liuyng death in breſt.</l>
                  <l>But dire diſdaine letts driue a ſhaft, and gauls this braggyng foole,</l>
                  <l>He plucks his plumes, vnbendes his bowe and ſets hym newe to ſcole,</l>
                  <l>Whereby this boye, that bragged late, as conquerer ouer all,</l>
                  <l>Now yelds hym ſelf vnto diſdaine his veſſall and his thrall.</l>
               </lg>
               <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
               <closer>
                  <signed>W. Hunnis.</signed>
               </closer>
            </div>
            <div type="poem">
               <head>Of a contented ſtate.</head>
               <lg>
                  <l>IN wealth we ſe ſome wealthie men, abound in wealth moſte welthely</l>
                  <l>In wealth we ſe thoſe men again, in wealth do liue moſte wretchedly.</l>
                  <l>And yet of wealthe hauyng more ſtore,</l>
                  <l>Then erſt of wealth thei had before.</l>
                  <l>Theſe welthy men do ſeme to want, thei ſeme to want y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> moſt thei haue</l>
                  <l>The more poſtes, y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> more thei craue, the more thei craue y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> greater ſtore</l>
                  <l>That moſte thei haue, thei thinke but ſkant.</l>
                  <l>Yet not content, wo be therefore,</l>
                  <l>The ſimple men that leſſe wealth haue with leſſer wealth we ſe conte<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t,</l>
                  <l>Content are thei twixt wealth and ſcath, a life to lead indifferent.</l>
                  <l>And thus of wealth theſe men haue more,</l>
                  <l>Then thoſe of whiche we ſpoke before.</l>
               </lg>
               <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
               <closer>
                  <signed>W. Hunnis.</signed>
               </closer>
            </div>
            <div type="poem">
               <pb facs="tcp:12052:40"/>
               <head>Beyng diſdained, he complaineth.</head>
               <lg>
                  <l>IF frendleſſe faithe? if giltleſſe thought maie ſhielde?</l>
                  <l>If ſimple truthe that neuer meant to ſwarue:</l>
                  <l>If deare deſire accepted fruite doe yelde,</l>
                  <l>If greedie luſte in loyall life doeth ſarue.</l>
                  <l>Then maie my plainte bewaile my heauie harme:</l>
                  <l>That ſeekyng calme, haue ſtumbled on the ſtorme.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>My wonted cheare, ecclipſed by the cloude,</l>
                  <l>Of deepe diſdaine, through errour of reporte:</l>
                  <l>If wearie woe enwrapped in the ſhroude,</l>
                  <l>Lies ſlaine by tongue of the vnfrendly ſorte.</l>
                  <l>Yet heauen and yearth and all that Nature wrought,</l>
                  <l>I call to vowe of my vnſpotted thought.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>No ſhade I ſeeke in parte, to ſhield my tainte,</l>
                  <l>But ſimple truthe, I hunte no other ſute:</l>
                  <l>On that I gape, the iſſue of my plainte,</l>
                  <l>If that I quaile, let Iuſtice me confute.</l>
                  <l>If that my place, emongs the giltleſſe ſorte,</l>
                  <l>Repaie by dome, my name and good reporte.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>Goe heauie verſe, purſue deſired grace,</l>
                  <l>Where pitie ſhrinde in cell of ſecret breſt:</l>
                  <l>Awaits my haſte, the rightfull lot to place,</l>
                  <l>And lothes to ſee, the giltleſſe man oppreſt.</l>
                  <l>Whoſe vertues greate, hath crounde her more with fame,</l>
                  <l>Then kyngly ſtate, though largely ſhine the ſame.</l>
               </lg>
               <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
               <closer>
                  <signed>L. <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>aux.</signed>
               </closer>
            </div>
            <div type="poem">
               <head>Of the meane estate.</head>
               <lg>
                  <l>THe higher that the Ceder tree, vnto the heauens doe growe,</l>
                  <l>The more in daunger is the top, when ſturdie winds gan blowe,</l>
                  <l>
                     <pb n="46" facs="tcp:12052:40" rendition="simple:additions"/>Who Iudges then in princely throne, to bee deuoide of hate,</l>
                  <l>Doeth not yet knowe, what heapes of ill, lies hid in ſuche eſtate.</l>
                  <l>Suche dangers great, ſuche gripes of minde, ſuche toile do thei ſuſtain</l>
                  <l>That often tymes, of God thei wiſhe, to bee vnkyngde again.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>For as the huge and mightie rockes, withſtande the ragyng ſeas,</l>
                  <l>So kyngdomes in ſubiection bee, whereas dame Fortune pleaſe:</l>
                  <l>Of brittle ioye, of ſmilyng cheare, of Honie mixte with Gall,</l>
                  <l>Alotted is to euery Prince, in freedome to bee thrall.</l>
                  <l>What watches long, what ſteps vnſure, what grefes and care of minde</l>
                  <l>What bitter broiles, what endleſſe toiles, to kyngdomes bee aſſingde.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>The ſubiect then maie well compare, with prince for pleaſant daies,</l>
                  <l>Whoſe ſilent nighe bryngs quiet reſt, whoſe ſteps no ſtorme bewraies:</l>
                  <l>How muche bee we, then bounde to God, who ſuche prouiſion makes,</l>
                  <l>To late our cares vpon the Prince, thus doeth he for our ſakes.</l>
                  <l>To hym therefore, let vs lifte vp our harts, and praie a maine,</l>
                  <l>That euery Prince that he hath plaſt, maie long in quiet raigne.</l>
               </lg>
               <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
               <closer>
                  <signed>W. H.</signed>
               </closer>
            </div>
            <div type="poem">
               <head>Of a contented mynd.</head>
               <lg>
                  <l>WHen all is doen and ſaied, in the ende thus ſhall you finde,</l>
                  <l>The moſte of all doeth hath in bliſſe, that hath a quiet minde:</l>
                  <l>And cleare from worldlie cares, to deame can bee content,</l>
                  <l>The ſweeteſt tyme, in all this life, in thinkyng to bee ſpent,</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>The bodie ſubiecte is, to fickle Fortunes power,</l>
                  <l>And to a million of miſhapps, is caſuall euery hower:</l>
                  <l>And death in tyme doeth chaunge it to a clodde of claie,</l>
                  <l>When as the mynde whiche is deuine, runnes neuer to decaie.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>Companion none is like, vnto the mynde alone,</l>
                  <l>For many haue been harmde by ſpeach, through thinking few or none:</l>
                  <l>Fewe often tymes reſtraineth words, but maks not thoughts to ceaſe,</l>
                  <l>And he ſpeaks beſte that hath the ſkill, when for to holde his peace.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <pb facs="tcp:12052:41" rendition="simple:additions"/>
                  <l>Our wealth leaues vs at death, our kinſmen at the graue,</l>
                  <l>But vertues of the mynde, vnto the heauens with vs haue:</l>
                  <l>Wherefore for vertues ſake, I can be well content,</l>
                  <l>The ſweeteſt tyme of all my life, to deeme in thinkyng ſpent.</l>
               </lg>
               <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
               <closer>
                  <signed>L. <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>aux.</signed>
               </closer>
            </div>
            <div type="poem">
               <head>Trie before you trust.</head>
               <lg>
                  <l>TO counſell my eſtate, abandonde to the ſpoile,</l>
                  <l>Of forged frendes whoſe groſeſt fraude, it ſet with fineſt foile.</l>
                  <l>To verifie true dealyng wights, whoſe truſt no treaſon dreads,</l>
                  <l>And all to deare thacquaintaunce be, of ſuche moſte harmfull heads.</l>
                  <l>I am aduiſed thus who ſo doeth frende, frende ſo,</l>
                  <l>As though to morrowe nexte he feared, for to become a fo.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>To haue a fained frende, no perill like I finde,</l>
                  <l>Oft fleryng face maie mantell beſt, a miſchief in the minde:</l>
                  <l>A paire of angels eares oft tymes, doeth hide a ſerpents harte,</l>
                  <l>Vnder whoſe gripes who ſo doeth come, to late complaines the ſmart.</l>
                  <l>Wherefore I doe aduiſe, who ſo doeth frende frende ſo,</l>
                  <l>As though to morrowe next he ſhould become a mortall fo.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>Refuſe reſpectyng frends, that courtly knowe to faine,</l>
                  <l>For gold that winnes for golde, ſhall loſe, the ſelf ſame frende againe:</l>
                  <l>The Quaile needes neuer feare, in foulers netts to fall,</l>
                  <l>If he would neuer bende his eare to liſten to his call.</l>
                  <l>Therefore truſt not to ſone, but when you frende frende ſo,</l>
                  <l>As though to morrowe next, ye feard for to become a fo.</l>
               </lg>
               <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
               <closer>
                  <signed>L. Vaux.</signed>
               </closer>
            </div>
            <div type="poem">
               <head>He renounceth all the affectes of Loue.</head>
               <lg>
                  <l>LIke as the Harte that lifteth vp his eares,</l>
                  <l>To heare the hounds, that hath hym in the chaſe:</l>
                  <l>Doeth caſt the winde, in daungers and in feares,</l>
                  <l>
                     <pb n="47" facs="tcp:12052:41" rendition="simple:additions"/>With fliyng foote, to paſſe awaie apace,</l>
                  <l>So muſt I flie of Loue the vaine purſute,</l>
                  <l>Whereof the gaine is leſſer then the fruite.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>And I alſo muſt lothe thoſe learyng looks,</l>
                  <l>Where Loue doeth lurke ſtill with his ſubtill ſlaite,</l>
                  <l>With painted mocks, and inward hidden hoks,</l>
                  <l>To trapp by truſt, that lieth not inwaite.</l>
                  <l>The ende whereof, aſſaie it who ſo ſhall,</l>
                  <l>As ſugred ſmart, and inward bitter gall.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>And I muſt flie ſuche Cirian ſongs,</l>
                  <l>Wherewith that Circes, Vliſſes did enchaunt:</l>
                  <l>Theſe wilie Watts I meane, with filed tongs,</l>
                  <l>That harts of ſteele, haue power to daunt,</l>
                  <l>Who ſo as Hauke, that ſtoupeth to their call,</l>
                  <l>For moſte deſarte, receiueth leaſt of all.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>But woe to me that firſt behelde theſe eyes,</l>
                  <l>The trapp wherein I ſaie, that I was tane:</l>
                  <l>An outward ſalue, whiche inward me deſtroies,</l>
                  <l>Whereto I runne, as Rat vnto her bane.</l>
                  <l>As to the fiſhe, ſometyme it doeth befall,</l>
                  <l>That with the baite, doth ſwallow hooke and al.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>Within my breaſt, wherewith I daiely fedd,</l>
                  <l>The vaine repaſt of amourous hott deſire:</l>
                  <l>With loitryng luſt, ſo long that hath me fedd,</l>
                  <l>Till he hath brought me to the flamyng fire.</l>
                  <l>In tyme as Phenix ends her care and carks,</l>
                  <l>I make the fire, and burne my ſelf with ſparks.</l>
               </lg>
               <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
               <closer>
                  <signed>L. <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>aux.</signed>
               </closer>
            </div>
            <div type="poem">
               <head>Bethinking hym ſelf of his ende, writeth thus.</head>
               <lg>
                  <l>WHen I beholde the baier, my laſte and poſtyng horſſe,</l>
                  <l>That bare ſhall to the graue, my vile and carren corſſe.</l>
                  <l>Then ſaie I ſeely wretche, why doeſt thou put thy truſte,</l>
                  <l>In thyngs eithe made of claye, that ſone will tourne to duſte,</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <pb facs="tcp:12052:42" rendition="simple:additions"/>
                  <l>Doeſt thou not ſee the young, the hardie and the faire,</l>
                  <l>That now are paſte and gone, as though thei neuer were:</l>
                  <l>Doeſt thou not ſee thy ſelf, drawe hourly to thy laſte,</l>
                  <l>As ſhafts whiche that is ſhotte, at birds that flieth faſte.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>Doeſt thou not ſee how death, through ſmiteth with his launce,</l>
                  <l>Some by warre, ſome by plague, and ſome with worldlie chaunce:</l>
                  <l>What thyng is there on yearth, for pleaſure that was made,</l>
                  <l>But goeth more ſwifte awaie, then doeth the Sommer ſhade.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>Loe here the Sommer floure, that ſprong this other daie,</l>
                  <l>But Winter weareth as faſte, and bloweth cleane awaie:</l>
                  <l>Euen ſo ſhalt thou conſume, from youth to lothſome age,</l>
                  <l>For death he doeth not ſpare, the prince more then the page.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>Thy houſe ſhall be of claie, a clotte vnder thy hedde,</l>
                  <l>Vntill the latter daie, the graue ſhall be thy bedde:</l>
                  <l>Vntill the blowyng trumpe, doeth ſaie to all and ſome,</l>
                  <l>Riſe vp out of your graue, for now the Iudge is come.</l>
               </lg>
               <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
               <closer>
                  <signed>L. <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>aux.</signed>
               </closer>
            </div>
            <div type="poem">
               <head>Beyng in Loue, he complaineth.</head>
               <lg>
                  <l>ENforſt by Loue and feare, to pleaſe and not offende,</l>
                  <l>Within the words you would me write, a meſſage muſt I ſende:</l>
                  <l>A wofull errande ſure, a wretched man muſte write,</l>
                  <l>A wrecched tale, a wofull head, beſemeth to endite.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>For what can he but waile, that hath but all he would.</l>
                  <l>And yet that all, is nought at all, but lacke of all he ſhould:</l>
                  <l>But lacke of all his mynde, what can be greater grief,</l>
                  <l>That haue and lacke, that likes hym beſt, muſt neds be moſte miſchief.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>Now foole what makes thee waile, yet ſome might ſaie full well,</l>
                  <l>That haſte no harme but of thy ſelf, as thou thy ſelf canſt tell:</l>
                  <l>To whom I aunſwere thus, ſince all my harmes doe growe,</l>
                  <l>Vpon my ſelf, ſo of my ſelf, ſome happ maie come I trowe.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <pb n="48" facs="tcp:12052:42" rendition="simple:additions"/>
                  <l>And ſince I ſee bothe happ, and harme betids to me,</l>
                  <l>For preſent woe, my after bliſſe, will make me not forget thee:</l>
                  <l>Who hath a fielde of golde, and maie not come therein,</l>
                  <l>Muſt liue in hope till he haue forſe, his treaſure well to winne.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>Whoſe ioyes by hope of dread, to conquere or to loſe,</l>
                  <l>So greate a wealth doeth riſe, and for example doeth diſcloſe,</l>
                  <l>To winne the golden Fleſe, ſtoode Iaſon not in drede,</l>
                  <l>Till that Medeas hope of helpe, did giue hym hope to ſpede.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>Yet ſure his mynde was muche, and yet his feare the more,</l>
                  <l>That hath no happ but by your helpe, maie happ for to reſtore:</l>
                  <l>The ragyng Bulls he dread, yet by his Ladies charme,</l>
                  <l>He knewe it might be brought to paſſe, thei could doe little hame.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>Vnto whoſe grace yelde he, as I doe offer me,</l>
                  <l>Into your hands to haue his happ, not like hym for to be:</l>
                  <l>But as kyng Priamus, did binde hym to the will,</l>
                  <l>Of Creſſed falſe whiche hym forſoke, with Diomed to ſpill.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>So I to you commende my faithe, and eke my ioye,</l>
                  <l>I hope you will not bee ſo falſe, as Creſſed was to Troye:</l>
                  <l>For if I bee vntrue, her Lazares death I wiſhe,</l>
                  <l>And eke in thee if thou bee falſe, her clapper and her diſhe.</l>
               </lg>
               <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
               <closer>
                  <signed>R. L.</signed>
               </closer>
            </div>
            <div type="poem">
               <head>Beyng in trouble, he writeth thus.</head>
               <lg>
                  <l>IN terrours trapp with thraldome thruſte,</l>
                  <l>Their thornie thoughts to taſte and trie:</l>
                  <l>In conſcience cleare from cauſe vniuſte,</l>
                  <l>With carpyng teares did call and crie.</l>
                  <l>And ſaied O God, yet thou art he,</l>
                  <l>That can and will deliuer me. <hi>Bis.</hi>
                  </l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>Thus tremblyng there with teares I trodd,</l>
                  <l>To totter tide in truthes defence:</l>
                  <l>
                     <pb facs="tcp:12052:43" rendition="simple:additions"/>With ſighes and ſobs, I ſaied O God,</l>
                  <l>Let right not haue this recompence.</l>
                  <l>Leſt that my foes might laugh to ſe,</l>
                  <l>That thou wouldeſt not deliuer me. <hi>Bis.</hi>
                  </l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>My ſoule then to repentance ranne,</l>
                  <l>My ragged clothes all rent and torne:</l>
                  <l>And did bewaile the loſſe it wanne,</l>
                  <l>With lothſome life ſo long forlorne.</l>
                  <l>And ſaied O God, yet thou art he,</l>
                  <l>That can and will deliuer me. <hi>Bis.</hi>
                  </l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>Then comfort came with clothes of ioye,</l>
                  <l>Whoſe ſemes were faithfull ſtedfaſtneſſe:</l>
                  <l>And did bedecke the naked boye,</l>
                  <l>That erſt was full of wretchedneſſe.</l>
                  <l>And ſaied be glad for God is he,</l>
                  <l>That ſhortly will deliuer thee. <hi>Bis.</hi>
                  </l>
               </lg>
               <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
               <closer>
                  <signed>W. H.</signed>
               </closer>
            </div>
            <div type="poem">
               <head>Beyng troubled in mynde, he writeth as followeth.</head>
               <lg>
                  <l>THe bitter ſweate that ſtraines my yelded harte,</l>
                  <l>The careleſſe count, that doeth the ſame emrace:</l>
                  <l>The doubtfull hope, to reape my due deſarte,</l>
                  <l>The penſiue pathe that guids my reſtleſſe race.</l>
                  <l>Are at ſuche warre within my wounded breſt,</l>
                  <l>As doeth bereue my ioye and eke my reſt.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>My greedie will, that ſeeks the golden gaine,</l>
                  <l>My luckleſſe lot, doeth alwaie take in worthe:</l>
                  <l>My mated mynde, that dreades my ſutes in vaine,</l>
                  <l>My piteous plaint, doeth helpe to ſet it forthe.</l>
                  <l>So that betwene twoo waues of ragyng ſeas,</l>
                  <l>I driue my daies in troubles and deſeaſe.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <pb n="49" facs="tcp:12052:43" rendition="simple:additions"/>
                  <l>My wofull eyes doe take their chief delight,</l>
                  <l>To feede their fill vpon the pleaſaunt maze:</l>
                  <l>My hidden harmes that growe in me by ſight,</l>
                  <l>With pinyng paines, doe driue me fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the gaze.</l>
                  <l>And to my hope I reape no other hire,</l>
                  <l>But burne my ſelf, and I doe blowe the fire.</l>
               </lg>
               <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
               <closer>
                  <signed>I. Haiwood.</signed>
               </closer>
            </div>
            <div type="poem">
               <head>Looke or you leape.</head>
               <lg>
                  <l>IF thou in ſuertie ſafe wilt ſitt,</l>
                  <l>If thou delight at reſte to dwell,</l>
                  <l>Spende, no more words then ſhall ſeme fitt,</l>
                  <l>Let tonge in ſilence talke expell,</l>
                  <l>In all things that thou ſeeſt men bent,</l>
                  <l>Se all, ſaie nought, hold thee content.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>In worldly woorks degrees are three,</l>
                  <l>Makers, doers, and lookers on:</l>
                  <l>The lookers on haue libertie,</l>
                  <l>Bothe the others to iudge vpon,</l>
                  <l>Wherefore in all, as men are bent,</l>
                  <l>See all, ſaie nought, holde thee content.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>The makers ofte are in faulte founde,</l>
                  <l>The doers doubte, of praiſe or ſhame:</l>
                  <l>The lookers on finde ſureſt grounde,</l>
                  <l>Thei haue the fruite, yet free from blame,</l>
                  <l>This doeth perſwade in all here ment,</l>
                  <l>See all, ſaie nought, holde thee content.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>The Prouerbe is not South and Weſt,</l>
                  <l>Whiche hath bee ſaied, long tyme agoe:</l>
                  <l>Of little medlyng cometh reſt,</l>
                  <l>The buſie man neuer wanteth woe.</l>
                  <l>The beſte waie is, in all worlds ſent,</l>
                  <l>See all, ſaie nought, holde thee content.</l>
               </lg>
               <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
               <closer>
                  <signed>Iaſper Heywood.</signed>
               </closer>
            </div>
            <div type="poem">
               <pb facs="tcp:12052:44" rendition="simple:additions"/>
               <head>
                  <l>Though Fortune haue ſet thee on hie,</l>
                  <l>Remember yet that thou ſhalt die.</l>
               </head>
               <lg>
                  <l>TO die, Dame nature did man frame,</l>
                  <l>Death is a thyng moſte perfecte ſure:</l>
                  <l>We ought not natures workes to blame,</l>
                  <l>She made nothyng, ſtill to endure.</l>
                  <l>That lawe ſhe made, when we were borne,</l>
                  <l>That hence we ſhould retourne againe:</l>
                  <l>To render right, we muſt not ſcorne,</l>
                  <l>Death is due debt, it is no paine.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>The ciuill lawe doeth bid reſtore,</l>
                  <l>That thou haſt taken vp of truſte:</l>
                  <l>Thy life is lent, thou muſt therefore,</l>
                  <l>Repaie, except thou be vniuſte.</l>
                  <l>This life is like a pointed race,</l>
                  <l>To the ende wherof when man hath trode,</l>
                  <l>He muſt retourne to former place,</l>
                  <l>He maie not ſtill remaine abrode.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>Death hath in all the yearth a right,</l>
                  <l>His power is greate, it ſtretcheth farre:</l>
                  <l>No Lorde, no Prince, can ſcape his wight,</l>
                  <l>No creature can his duetie barre,</l>
                  <l>The wiſe, the iuſt, the ſtrong, the hie,</l>
                  <l>The chaſt, the meke, the free of hart,</l>
                  <l>The riche, the poore, who can denie,</l>
                  <l>Haue yelded all vnto his darte.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>Could Hercules that tamde eche wight?</l>
                  <l>Or els Vliſſes with his witte?</l>
                  <l>Or Ianus who had all foreſight?</l>
                  <l>Or chaſt Hypolit ſcape the pitte?</l>
                  <l>Could Creſus with his bagges of golde?</l>
                  <l>Or Irus with his hungrie paine?</l>
                  <l>Or Signus through his hardineſſe bolde?</l>
                  <l>Driue backe the daies of Death againe.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <pb facs="tcp:12052:44" rendition="simple:additions"/>
                  <l>Seyng no man then can Death eſcape,</l>
                  <l>Nor hire hym hence for any gaine:</l>
                  <l>Wee ought not feare his carraine ſhape,</l>
                  <l>He onely bryngs euell men to paine,</l>
                  <l>If thou haue ledde thy life a right,</l>
                  <l>Death is the ende of miſerie:</l>
                  <l>If thou in God haſt thy delight,</l>
                  <l>Thou dieſt to liue eternallie.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>Eche wight therefore while he liues here,</l>
                  <l>Let hym thinke on his diyng daie:</l>
                  <l>In midſt of wealthe, in midſt of chere,</l>
                  <l>Let hym accompt he muſt awaie.</l>
                  <l>This thought makes man to God a frende.</l>
                  <l>This thought doeth baniſhe pride and ſynne:</l>
                  <l>This thought doeth bryng a man in thende,</l>
                  <l>Where he of Death the field ſhall winne.</l>
               </lg>
               <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
               <closer>
                  <signed>T. Marſhall.</signed>
               </closer>
            </div>
            <div type="poem">
               <head>The complaint of a Synner.</head>
               <lg>
                  <l>
                     <hi>O</hi> Heauenly God, O Father deare, caſt doune thy tender eye,</l>
                  <l>Vpon a wretche that proſtrate here, before thy throne doeth lye:</l>
                  <l>O powre thy precious oyle of grace, into my wounded harte,</l>
                  <l>O let the dropps of mercie ſwage, the rigour of my ſmarte.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>My faintyng foule ſuppreſſed ſore, with carefull clogge of ſynne,</l>
                  <l>In humble ſorte ſubmitts it ſelf, thy mercie for to winne:</l>
                  <l>Graunt mercie then O Sauiour ſweete, to me moſte wofull thrail,</l>
                  <l>Whoſe mornfull crie to thee, O Lorde, doeth ſtill for mercie call.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>Thy bleſſed will I haue deſpiſed, vpon a ſtubborne mynde,</l>
                  <l>And to the ſwaie of worldly thyngs, my ſelf I haue enclinde:</l>
                  <l>Forgettyng heauen and heaue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ly powers, where God &amp; ſaincts do dwell</l>
                  <l>My life had like to tread the pathe, that leads the waie to hell.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>But now my Lorde my lode ſtarre bright, I will no more doe ſo,</l>
                  <l>To thynke vpon my former life, my harte doeth melte for woe:</l>
                  <l>Alas I ſigh, alas I ſobbe, alas I doe repent:</l>
                  <l>That euer my licencious will, ſo wickedly was bent.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <pb facs="tcp:12052:45" rendition="simple:additions"/>
                  <l>Sith thus therefore with yernfull plaint, I doe thy mercie craue,</l>
                  <l>O Lorde for thy greate mercies ſake, let me thy mercie haue:</l>
                  <l>Reſtore to life the wretched ſoule, that els is like to die,</l>
                  <l>So ſhall my voyce vnto thy name, ſyng praiſe eternallie.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>Now bleſſed be the Father firſt, and bleſſed be the Sonne,</l>
                  <l>And bleſſed be the holie Ghoſte, by whom all thyngs are doen:</l>
                  <l>Bleſſe me O bleſſed Trinitie, with thy eternall grace,</l>
                  <l>That after death my ſoule maie haue, in heauen a dwellyng place.</l>
               </lg>
               <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
               <closer>
                  <signed>F. Kindlemarſh.</signed>
               </closer>
            </div>
            <div type="poem">
               <head>
                  <l>The fruite that ſprynges from wilfull wits, is ruthe and ruins rage:</l>
                  <l>And ſure what heedeleſſe youth committes, repentaunce rues in age.</l>
               </head>
               <l>
                  <hi>I</hi> Rage in reſtleſſe ruthe, and ruins rule my daies,</l>
               <l>I rue (to late) my rechleſſe youth, by rules of reaſons waies:</l>
               <l>I ranne ſo long a race, in ſearche of ſureſt waie,</l>
               <l>That leaſure learnde me tread the trace, that ledde to leude decaie.</l>
               <l>I gaue ſo large a raine, to vnreſtrained bitt,</l>
               <l>That now with proofe of after paine, I waile my want of witt:</l>
               <l>I trifled forthe the tyme, with truſt to ſelf conceites,</l>
               <l>Whilſt plenties vſe prickt forthe my prime, to ſearch for ſugred baites</l>
               <l>Wherein once learnde to finde, I founde ſo ſweete a taſte,</l>
               <l>That due foreſight of after ſpeede, ſelf will eſtemed waſte.</l>
               <l>Whiche will through wilfulneſſe, hath wrought my witleſſe fall,</l>
               <l>And heedeleſſe youthes vnſkilfulneſſe, hath lapt my life in thrall.</l>
               <l>Whereby by proofe I knowe, that pleaſure breedeth paine,</l>
               <l>And he that euill ſeede doeth ſowe, euill fruite muſt reape againe.</l>
               <l>Let ſuche therefore whoſe youth, and purſes are in Prime,</l>
               <l>Foreſee and ſhun the helpeleſſe ruthe, whiche ſues miſſpence of tyme.</l>
               <l>For want is nexte to waſte, and ſhame doeth ſynne enſue,</l>
               <l>Euill ſpeedyng proofe hath heedeleſſe haſte, my ſelf haue proued it true.</l>
               <l>When neighbours nexte houſe burnes, tis tyme thereof take heede,</l>
               <l>For Fortunes wheele hath choiſe of turnes, whiche change of chances breede</l>
               <l>My ſaile hath been a lofte, though now I beare but lowe,</l>
               <l>Who clims to high ſelde falleth ſofte, dedſt ebbe hath higheſt flowe.</l>
               <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
               <closer>
                  <signed>ꝙ <hi>Yloop.</hi>
                  </signed>
                  <dateline>
                     <date>1578.</date>
                  </dateline>
               </closer>
               <pb facs="tcp:12052:45"/>
            </div>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
